You ready?
Yep.
Okay.
Today, we are going to talk about the refugee protests.
Today's video is called
Refugee Riots, Salience and Storytelling.
And what I want to do today is look at the recent
growth in refugee asylum seeker protests
here in the UK, and I want to use it to explain some
really important terms and concepts about media,
and in particular, economics and political media.
We're going to talk about salience, storytelling,
wedge issues, and the bifurcated society, and
you're going to understand how the media works.
Okay, so first, a little bit of
context for our international viewers.
In the last month or two, there have been
lots and lots of protests outside hotels which are
being used by the government to house asylum seekers.
Asylum seekers have come, they have not been
processed, and they're being put up in hotels, and
it has led to lots and lots of protests all over
the country by British people saying they're not
happy with asylum seekers being kept in hotels.
Okay, so for a long time, I avoided speaking
about immigration on the channel because I
am an economist, and I like to focus on the
economy and things which I'm an expert on.
But we started to see a couple of years ago
like the growth and the growth and the growth in
people talking about immigration in the comments,
basically saying, "What are talking about?
The problem is not rich people.
The problem is not inequality.
The problem is immigration.
Why don't you talk about that?" And we saw the
popularity of this grow and grow and grow, and it
started to become increasingly clear that basically
anti-immigration sentiment was becoming basically
the key opposition to ideas about taxing the rich.
So, I did a video a couple of years ago,
my first video on immigration, which
we'll link here so you can see.
And really, by and large, I haven't touched it so
much since, but I wanted to do a video on it now
because I think it's again become really relevant
to our work on dealing with the problem with the
economy, dealing with the problem on inequality.
And I think what we've seen is... I came back from
holiday about two months ago now, two and a half months
ago, and at that time, it really felt like we kind
of had our foot on the neck of the media, basically.
Everybody was talking about wealth taxes.
Everybody was constantly asking politicians,
"Why don't you do something about wealth taxes?
Why don't you do something about inequality?"
And there was kind of an effort made by the
media, especially by the right-wing media, to
kind of discredit the ideas on wealth taxes, and
really, to be honest, it kind of failed.
I think they didn't really successfully poke many
holes in the idea of taxing the rich more and
the idea of doing something about inequality,
and it felt like we had won the argument.
But then what basically happened was the media
pretty much stopped talking about inequality and started
to talk more and more and more and more about refugees
and asylum seekers and these protests at these hotels.
And what this teaches us is the importance
of the first media idea we're going
to explain today, which is salience.
Okay, so what is salience?
I'm going to explain what salience is by
telling a story about when I first started
talking about economics in the media.
So, I started this YouTube channel in 2020, and at
the time, I started to do quite a little bit of,
like, radio, talking about inequality, talking about
the economy, I was lucky because I was one of
the first guys who realised there was going to be a
big inequality crisis, that there was going to be a big
inflation crisis, so I started to tell everybody
about it, and I went on loads and loads of radio shows.
If you look back through this channel,
if you like the really, really, really early
videos, we used to upload all of my radio
interviews, so you'll see them on there.
And you'll see, I was basically saying like,
years in advance, we were going to have an inequality
crisis and we were going to have an inflation crisis.
And I was in a really strong position basically
because I was a very good economist, I had a very good
history, I was one of the top traders in the city, and
economists who are this good basically
don't normally appear in the media because
they get paid a lot more to work for banks.
So in my personal opinion, I was
kind of head and shoulders above the
competition talking about the economy.
I went on loads of shows, I spoke about the
economy, I was doing really well, and eventually,
I got invited to go on with Nick Ferrari,
who is the most right-wing presenter on LBC.
So, again, for our foreign viewers, LBC is like
a really popular talk radio show in this country,
people call in,
they talk about the politics, mainly politics,
the economy, social issues, and they like to
consider themselves like neither left nor right.
They have like more left-wing presenters,
like James O'Brien, and they have more
right-wing presenters, like Nick Ferrari, and Nick
Ferrari is considered the most right-wing one.
And I got called up late one evening, I was
playing football with my friends, and they wanted
me to come on and talk about what I thought was
the economy, basically, and I broke my rib
playing football, but I really wanted to do it
because Nick Ferrari is like their big presenter.
So, I barely slept, and I went on early in the morning
on Nick Ferrari, and I wanted to talk about the
economy, I wanted to talk about inequality, I wanted
to talk about how COVID was massively increasing
inequality, how it was going to cause an economic crisis.
And what Nick Ferrari did was he didn't allow the
conversation to ever be about anything except for
extremely narrow consumption decisions about what
kind of energy provider an ordinary family uses.
And every time I tried to move it to something
bigger about the economy, about inequality,
he was like, "What energy provider should
our viewers use?" Again and again and again.
And that is an example of salience, because salience
is not about winning the argument, it is
about controlling what topics are discussed.
It's about controlling the topic of discussion.
And once you start thinking about salience...
So, my background is not in media.
My background is in maths
and economics, and trading.
And in my heart of hearts, I'm like a
very sort of logic-y, mathsy guy, and
I think a lot of people are like that,
they think that political debate is about
debate and about winning the argument.
I make my points, you make your point,
and we, the public will decide who's the winner.
But what this Nick Ferrari interview showed
me is a massive thing that you can do is to
make sure you basically understand,
"What is it that my opponent is good at?
What area is he good at?
What area is he weak at?
What area am I good at?
What area am I weak at?" And you make sure that
you only ever speak about the area that you are
strong at, and you don't allow the subject to,
be anything that your opponent might be good at.
That is controlling the salience.
Salience is basically how visible a particular topic is.
So rather than try to win the debate, you try to
make sure only one side of the debate is visible, has
any volume, gets heard, and that is the side of the
debate... side of the debate upon which you are strong.
And this idea of salience in a debate or
in a conversation, which if you keep an eye
out for it, you'll see all over the media.
You will see everybody doing it
in every political conversation.
It doesn't just apply to an individual
conversation or an individual debate.
We can apply it to the media as a whole, one media
show or basically, like, the whole media, like,
all of the TV, all of the newspapers, all of the
online, social media, what topics are getting
discussed and what topics are not getting discussed.
And back when I came back from holiday in late
June, early July, the economy and inequality
and taxation and taxation of the rich were being
discussed every single day on every single news show.
We had massive salience.
We were the issue that was being spoken about.
We were the issue that was dominating media time.
And now, if you look at the TV, what you see
is immigration and asylum seekers and refugee
riots, refugee protests outside hotels are
being spoken about much, much, much more.
And issues of inequality, taxation, distribution
have kind of been put on the shelf, which basically
means we, as much as we maybe won the argument on the
economy, we are now losing the battle for salience.
So, how do you win the battle for salience?
And that brings us to my next important
point, which we're going to discuss about
the media, which is storytelling.
Okay, so storytelling.
Now, I, if you have been watching for a long time,
you'll know this, or if you go back and watch some
of our older videos, I have been saying for years
that in this country what would happen was,
Rishi Sunak would fail really badly for popularity.
Keir Starmer and Labour would
have a massive electoral win.
Then Keir Starmer and Labour would fail really
badly, and then Nigel Farage and Reform would win.
I've been saying this for years.
I said this is, right back when
Boris Johnson was still prime minister
and Rishi Sunak was coming in.
So I've made a lot of very good, correct predictions
on politics, which were not consensus at the time.
And the way I've been able to make these correct
predictions is simply through understanding two
things, which is the economy and storytelling.
Okay, so it wasn't particularly difficult to predict
the failure of successive UK governments if you
understand our basic economic problem, which is we have
rapidly growing inequality of wealth that is sucking
wealth out of the middle class and the government,
which is sucking spending power out of the economy.
It's accumulating wealth with the very rich,
which is driving asset prices up, which is
making it harder for ordinary people to live.
Because we knew that both Rishi Sunak and the
Conservatives and Keir Starmer and Labour would come
in and do nothing about this growing inequality, we
basically knew that they would fail economically.
It's like you've got a hole in the bottom of your boat.
Wealth is sucking out of that hole at
an unbelievably rapid accelerating pace.
If you don't patch that hole, you're going to fail.
So it was relatively easy to know that we would have
a sequence of failing governments.
But how was I able also to predict the rise of
Reform and the rise of Nigel Farage, who for
those of you who might not know, who are not from the UK,
are our sort of new far-right party and leader?
That was because I understood
the importance of storytelling.
So when you have an economic crisis, especially
what we have had in the last 5, 10, sort of coming
up to 20 years now, a long-term economic crisis,
which seems protracted, feels like it has no
end, feels like it's going to get worse and worse,
ordinary families are really struggling, you
create this urgent need in the mind of the public
for something new, something different, right?
People do not want their... People can have a sense
for, like, the direction that their country is headed
and the direction that living standards are headed.
And if you go to a place like India or like China,
where living standards have for a long time been worse
than they are in the UK, because people have a sense
that life is getting better and their kids will be
richer than they are, they're happy to accept that.
But when people sense that their life is getting worse,
people really worry and people don't consider
that to be acceptable and they want something different.
And what people think they want is, like, a
new economic model or a new way of dealing
with the economy that doesn't collapse.
But the truth is... or maybe they
want a new political system.
But the truth is most people are not
experts on the economy and politics, and
what people really want is a new story.
People want there to be a new story that does
not involve their kids being poor, that does not
involve them getting worse and worse off over time.
And it creates this massive
demand for basically a new story.
There's this quote that I use from Milton Friedman,
the American economist, which is, "At times of
crisis, the solution will be chosen from the ideas
lying around at the time." If you have a collapsing
economy, it creates what I think of as a kind of
economic boom for stories and ideas, which is when
people are extremely unsatisfied with the status quo,
they start to look around and think, "Well, what are
our other options?" And that meant that because
we knew we would have a sequence of failing
governments, because the governments wouldn't deal
with growing wealth inequality, anybody who could
put together a compelling story that was different,
that was new, would inevitably get drawn into power.
And what really matters with regards to
these stories is, again, the salience.
So when the economy is collapsing, lots of different
people will have lots of different ideas about
how do we fix the economy, and basically, whichever
one is loudest is going to be the guy that will win.
When you understand this basic idea, number
one, until we deal with growing inequality,
living standards continue to worsen, which means
we have this continuing sense of collapsing
economy and desperate need for change.
You kind of always know what's going to happen
in politics, which is whoever is the loudest
alternative voice at any point in
time is going to win the next election.
And Labour won the last election with a very,
very simple story of the Conservatives are really
****, let's kick them out, and that basically won.
And that was, that was the
dominant story at the time.
But then Labour come in, and you get this even deeper
kind of story power vacuum essentially, which is
in this country, we've only had one... we've only had two
political parties in power for nearly a hundred years
essentially, and one of them was massively discredited.
Then the other one comes in, basically
purely on the story of we are not the first
party, and they become massively discredited.
And really, you end up in a situation of
whoever can control the media salience,
whoever has the biggest story of being new
and different will become Prime Minister.
And if you look at the situation now,
it was always pretty clear that Nigel Farage
and Reform and the far right would win.
And I want to be clear when I say
that this is not at all UK-specific.
The same thing is happening in basically
every country in the entire Western world.
When your center-left has no story and your
center-right has no story, really, anyone else
who has a compelling story can basically walk
into your president's or prime minister's office.
So that is where we are basically.
We have this collapsing economy.
We have this vacuum of stories, and it becomes, in
a bizarre way, like fantastically easy to become
president or prime minister, and that is why you're
seeing across the world sort of random guys who are
not even politicians, not even political parties
which didn't even exist recently, suddenly turning
up, becoming president, becoming prime minister.
You know, you saw Macron in France.
We saw Trump in the US.
We've seen the collapse of... You know, we've seen
the rise of the far-right parties basically across
Europe, new political parties taking power in Italy.
When the economy is collapsing,
anyone who can tell a compelling story
will be able to take control of that country.
And the problem with that at the moment is, really, if
you look around the political world at the moment, there
are basically no loud stories other than the far right.
So the far right has, like a pretty
clear story that everybody knows.
Like if I were to pull someone in in my country and say,
"What do you think Nigel Farage or Reform stands for?
What do they believe?" If I did the same thing in
your country, wherever you were, people would know.
They'd say they want there to be lower immigration.
They want there to be, fewer asylum seekers.
You know, that, that's like, that's what they want.
It's, it's really, really clear.
But if I was to ask somebody, "What is the story
of Labour or Keir Starmer in this country?"
If I were to ask somebody, "What is the
story of the Democrats in your country?"
I don't think they would know,
You know, and there are
groups of politicians in society.
You know, I went on The Rest Is Politics
a few weeks ago, which is the biggest
politics podcast here in the UK.
If you watch, if you want to see it,
you can... The video's there online.
And it's a very high-profile podcast,
and it's two sort of centrist politicians.
One is from the center-left
party, one is from the center-right.
They're... neither of
them active in politics anymore.
You go on there, there's a lot of hand-wringing
about the failures of Labour, the failures
of the Conservative Party, the failures
of the far right, Reform and Nigel Farage.
And for all that they like to criticise the
existing political system, what is their story?
What is their story?
I mean, I think it seems to be
largely about criticising other groups.
So that, that's where we are.
You know, if we talk about the left, if I
was to bring someone in on the street and say, "What do
you think, you know, the left believes in this country?
What is their story?" You know,
differentiating a little between the center and
the center-left and the left, the center-right,
the Conservatives are basically dead.
Really, what you have is you only have one group
that has a story, and people get behind that story.
They support that story.
In the absence of competing
stories, basically, you win.
So we have this period of time where there's
this massive absence of stories, which creates
this unbelievable power of storytelling, and
yet seemingly no group in society other than
the far right has been able or is able to
tell a compelling political economic story.
So now we've established these two really important
concepts that you need to understand if you want to
take political power, salience, and storytelling.
I want to talk about another element which, the far
right and the refugee protesters have, have
done really well in understanding these concepts.
So one of these protests, which they're very
regular now, is super, super close to where I
live, and, and I went down there with, with Jack the
cameraman, who films these videos, a few weeks ago.
To be honest, more than anything, just to sort of
witness what was happening because, I was worried,
I am worried about this sort of, growing movement.
And one thing that I found really, really
interesting that I saw there was there were enormous...
The actual number of protesters... So there were
protesters protesting against hotels and there were
counter-protesters, protesting against the protesters.
The number of protesters was not that huge, but what
there were a huge number of was citizen journalists.
And what I mean when I say citizen journalist is
somebody who's not presumably professional journalist.
Just a guy or a woman with a camera, sort of
live streaming, doing selfies, showing the, showing
the protest, and uploading the video to Facebook.
And there were loads and loads and loads of these guys.
And it was really, really noticeable how
much media presence there was relative to
what was actually a relatively small protest.
And I think what that shows is basically that the,
the far right has done a much better job, in a
sense, of understanding storytelling and salience.
And also understanding a thing which
I've spoken about a lot on this channel,
which is the need to be present online.
So, I think a thing has happened in media,
especially politics media in the last few
years, which is there has been
a massive shift towards online media.
I think this has really accelerated during COVID, which
is more and more and more people want to get their
news online, on Instagram, on YouTube, on Facebook.
And it has created this real opportunity
to aggressively dominate the salience of online
platforms because the existing media institutions
like BBC, Sky News, the existing political
parties have just been slow to move into it.
And what this... or what is interesting about these
citizen journalists is these citizen journalists
individually, the vast majority of them, won't
get anything like the number of views that we
get on this video that we get on our channel.
But the way that they succeed is that
there is simply an enormous amount of them.
And I think what this shows is in a weird
way, it's kind of inspirational because I've been
saying for a long time... you know, I made the decision
rather than writing for the big newspapers, to
try to do a push for online and a push for social.
Because I felt that that's where people were.
And recently, I've been trying to encourage our
viewers, you, to create more yourself and to make
more videos yourself and throw things out there.
And that is basically because people
are online nowadays, and there is,
there's this massive space.
I think what, what you see is
stories... stories are these really interesting things.
Stories are kind of like, they're
like a computer virus in a way.
Like, we like to think that the media
comes in and decides what stories get placed where.
But as the media has lost power and people have
moved online, you're kind of seeing it's more like
a kind of like a virus model, almost like this COVID
model, which is if enough people get out there and
spread it, it can spread really, really quickly.
And you can dominate the salience of a subject
without necessarily having that top level media support.
And I think that is what the far right
have done super, super, super, super well.
And they've created this kind of...
I mean, obviously, they do have media support.
They do have financial support.
We have things like GB News in this country, which
is, you know, a very well-funded, loss-making
media channel that supports these far right ideas.
You have obviously people like Elon Musk
buying things like Twitter.
But they have really effectively spread these
messages from the ground up, from the bottom.
And I think really we need to learn a lesson
from these guys, which is I think people like me,
I need to be constantly making these ideas, these
messages, these... the idea that the problem is
inequality, the idea that living standards will get
worse because of growing inequality, I need to make
that as simple as possible again and again and again.
So that people like you can take
the message and run with it.
I think what you've seen also with these guys is
basically the importance of being, like, multi-platform.
So we're really popular on YouTube.
We're really popular on Instagram.
We're popular with like basically younger
people, people in their 20s, 30s, 40s.
We're less popular with older
people in their 50s or 60s.
And that is largely because those guys are on
Facebook, and we are not popular on Facebook, basically.
So what you have seen is, and this is the last
concept I need to add before I get onto, well, one
more, phenomenal ability to craft a simple message,
give it to ordinary people, and this unbelievable
message discipline around the simple message to
flood the zone, tell everybody the problem is
immigrants, get everybody down to the protest,
make your videos, put them on Facebook, tell
your friends, tell your family, tell your mum.
And what you've basically seen is the far right
using basically exactly the model that I've been
saying we need to do for years, which is we put
a message out on here and all of you take it,
run with it, make your own videos, spread it in
your community, spread it amongst your family.
And what they've shown is it works.
It works.
And, we need to do it.
We need to do it better.
We need to copy them.
So to be clear here, I am trying to make a pitch
that essentially this needs to be the story.
The story needs to be growing inequality
of wealth is destroying living standards.
If you don't do anything about the
billionaires, your kids will be poor.
We've got plenty of videos out there
that I think support that story.
The best ones are probably The Squeeze Out or
the Channel 4 video with Krishna Guru-Murthy.
But we need to get behind this.
We need message discipline.
And I want this video...
Really, this is a call-out to the
left, to the center, to the centrist dads.
If you want to stop Nigel Farage from winning the
next election, you need to get behind a story.
You need a story.
I think we are the second loudest story in the room.
I think we are a story that can win.
But we need you to get behind it.
We need some message discipline.
We need people to be willing to
put their egos down for a little bit,
pick the message that's going to win, get behind it,
get out there, make the videos, get spreading it.
Because if we do not win the battle for salience,
we will lose the control of the country.
The last thing I wanted to talk about was
introduce this concept of a bifurcated society.
And this is something which I've been thinking
about a lot recently, which is the idea that
as wealth and equality increases, it kind of splits
society into two groups, which is wealth gets sucked
out of ordinary families and they start to become poor.
But you have this group of societies, this group of
families at the top which become unbelievably wealthy,
and as the top gets richer and the rest get poorer,
these groups kind of separate off from one another.
And what that leads to is a situation where all of
these elites in society, which includes the politicians
and the policymakers and the economists, basically
have a very poor understanding of what is happening in
ordinary people's lives, and it makes them basically
unable to sort of view these people with compassion.
I'll be thinking about this more through going to
these protests and talking to people at the protests.
Because what I found when I went to the
protests was a lot of people who have had a very
difficult time in the last few years, and
in particular had a difficult time during COVID
and since COVID, that have become very, very
distrustful of the societies that they live in.
And what struck me really was how in many cases
they were kind of right to be distrustful because
they think the politicians don't care about
them, and to a degree, that's right.
The politicians don't care about them.
They feel like they're ignored,
and to a degree, that they are ignored.
They feel like their financial position is
bad and their financial futures are uncertain,
and those are true facts as well ,
and they don't really understand why.
And I think it's important to recognise that if
you put somebody in that kind of situation where
their life is insecure, their future is insecure, their
family's insecure, things are changing, they don't
understand why, they don't feel connected at all to the
media or the TV or like they're having the situation
explained to them, it's kind of normal to go crazy.
And this reminded me, so I've not spoken about
this much on the channel, but my parents are
Mormons, and, Mormonism is a kind of a, a very
strict kind of American Christianity.
And what's interesting about that is a
lot of people think that Mormonism only exists
in America, but there's actually a lot of
Mormon- a lot of Mormons all over the world.
And the reason that there's a lot of Mormons all over
the world is the Mormons send young men and young
women dressed in very smart sort of white shirts
all around the world to knock on people's doors and
to tell them, "Hey, do you want to become a Mormon?"
And it is surprisingly successful, and three
of my grandparents were converted to Mormonism
by these guys who came knocking on their doors.
And sometimes I've wondered, you know, what
it was about, you know, my dad's parents
are very sort of stiff-upper-lip, English,
working-class people, why they became Mormons.
But, you know, my grandad, he came back from
the war, he was, he was a mem- he was in the
army since before the war started, you know, he
probably killed people in Egypt, and I think maybe
he was in a bit of a confused emotional space.
And you get a couple of young preppy-looking Americans
in nice smart shirts knock on your door and say,
"Hey, you know, we're going to teach you about God.
Come with us.
We're going to give you a community.
We're going to give you a space where you feel safe.
We're going to give you a future" I think if you
put someone in a space where they feel unprotected
and unsupported and confused, and somebody
knocks on their door with a smiling face and a hand
out, and says, "We're going to be here for you, we're
going to support you" a lot of people are going to go.
And when I went down to that protest
When I went down to that protest and
I saw the protesters on one side
and the counter-protestors on the other side
shouting each other and calling each other names,
I found it quite upsetting, to be honest, and I couldn't
help but ask myself, "Before I call these people
names, have I knocked on their door with my hand out?
Have we been there to offer them a story of hope,
a future, something that can bring us together,
rather than driving us apart?" Because I worry if that
is the future of this country, half of us on one side
of the road, half of us on the other, shouting names
at each other, responding to hatred with more hatred,
I wonder whether this could get worse and worse.
I think if the working people of this country
are divided, that's only going to benefit the rich
and ordinary families will get poorer and poorer.
But if we're united, we can win.
So this video is ultimately about the importance
of understanding how the media works,
salience, storytelling, how we win the future.
But I think more than that,
it's about whether we're able to view each other
as people and with compassion.
Because if you can do that,
then we can come together.
And if we can come together, we can win.
So that's the end.
Good luck.
Thank you.