Okay. Welcome back to Garys Economics.
Today we are going to do the fourth part
of our online course about inequality and the economy.
And we are going to explain
why wealth inequality is a central problem.
Okay. So we're back on the course again.
So far we've had three episodes.
Episode one was What is Wealth?
Episode two was What is Wealth Inequality
and How Does It Affect The Economy?
And episode three was
If Inequality Is So Important,
Why Don't Most Economists Talk About It?
Today we are going to explain
how I came to travel from
being a classically trained economist,
I did my undergrad at London School of Economics,
and then I went to work in the city
to believing
that, basically, contrary
to most mainstream economic opinion,
wealth inequality
is actually the central problem
that we're facing right now.
Okay, so I studied economics from 2005
to 2008 at London School of Economics.
It's a very elite economics university.
It teaches economics in the classic way.
It doesn't look much at inequality.
So when I started my first job
outside of university,
which was as a short
term interest rates trader at Citibank,
I wasn't really thinking about inequality
or distribution at all.
I started working full time as a trader
in June of 2008,
which is obviously just before the Lehman crisis,
and a big part of my job and the job of my team was to
look at central bank base
rates, central bank interest rates.
So, for example, in this country,
the Bank of England, in the US,
the Federal Reserve and say, okay, what are they now?
What are they going to be in one years
time, in six months time, in two years time?
So this is kind of what you would call like
a macroeconomic analysis job in a way.
The central bank is supposed to control inflation
basically when the economy is weak, they cut the rates.
When the economy is strong
or when the economy is overheating,
from an inflation perspective,
they increase their rates.
So really what you're doing
is you're looking at the economy.
Is it going to be strong? Is it going to be weak?
That was my job. That was my team’s job.
I started there in June 2008,
which obviously is a few months
before the Lehman crisis.
In October 2008, the crisis sort of slowly bubbles.
In October it explodes.
Lehman goes under.
There's this massive economic collapse.
I guess some people who watch the channel now
might be too young to remember that!
There was this huge economic collapse.
Tonnes and tonnes of people lost their jobs.
It was an economic disaster.
And central banks all across the world,
including in the US, here in the UK,
Europe, Australia,
they all suddenly slashed their interest rates
down to zero.
This was like a really extreme measure at the time.
So we're doing this video in the beginning of 2025.
We had zero interest rates quite recently,
but at the time in 2008, zero interest rates,
they were like totally new.
Except for in Japan,
which they’d been happening for a while.
Like before the crisis, central banks
would move interest rates from like 5.5% to 5.25%.
It was really that kind of like
delicate fine tuning.
And then suddenly in 2008, you have,
oh my God, this is such a disaster.
They're being cut from like 5.5% to 0%.
Well, technically 0.5%, but this...
this kind of thing across the world,
effectively from 5.5% or 4.5%
down to 0% in a matter of,
you know, a couple of months,
massive, massive aggressive cuts.
So our job then as interest rate traders,
from the perspective of predicting
is to look at the economy and say, okay,
well how long are these rates going to stay at 0% then?
When are they going to come back up?
How quickly will they come back up?
What level will they go back up to?
And at the time,
because the interest rates
had been cut so aggressively,
and most of these
traders are aware of the basic economic theory,
probably worth covering what economists think here.
So this response, which happened in 2008,
basically the exact same response
we had in Covid, right, slash
the interest rates, pushed the interest rates down.
This is a very classic modern economic response, right?
This is how modern economists
want to manage the economy.
It's all about interest rate management.
There's an economic weakness.
You reduce the interest rates
and the economic theory is quite simple right.
Interest rates are lower.
You're not making any money for saving.
You can borrow cheaply. It's the same for businesses.
There's no point saving money. You can borrow cheaply.
Go out and spend.
Go out and spend money.
Borrow money, invest, build up your business.
Borrow and spend, it’s free, super cheap to borrow. And
bear in mind, right before
2008, we would cut the rate from 5.5% to 5.25% and
expect that to make like a significant difference, right.
So we believed and, economies still do believe,
that these small interest rate
changes make a big difference to the economy.
And during 2008, we had these massive changes.
And the general economic consensus on
that was and still is,
these stimulate the economy,
but it takes a bit of time,
takes generally
they like to say 18 months, a year
and a half, takes that sort of time
for these interest rate movements
to affect, influence the economy.
So when we had these massive,
massive interest rate cuts,
everybody was saying like,
oh my God, like, this might be too much.
We're going to see like a massive economic bounce back.
You know, you might see a spike in inflation.
People were even talking about hyper inflation.
And speaking
now in 2025,
I think you have to point out that a lot of this
narrative was quite similar
to the narrative during Covid,
which is when you have these massive,
massive movements in interest rates.
They're so economically stimulative
that we are going to see like a massive bounce back.
And, you know, people now
might not remember the media during the 2008 crisis,
but they'll probably remember
media saying during Covid,
we're going to have a roaring ‘20s.
There's going to be all this pent up demand.
In a lot of ways, it was quite similar.
People were saying these massive moves in interest
rates will cause massive economic stimulus.
And basically
when you're a trader,
you can just look at the markets, right.
And the markets will say,
we think interest rates next year will be x, right.
So interest rates
went down to like 0.5% here in the UK.
Pretty much the same in the US, Europe.
And you can say what would they be next year?
What will they be in two years time?
And everybody was like,
well we're gonna have such a big bounce back
that these interest rates are going
to come massively up.
I was really young, I was only 21...
well I turned 22, during the Lehman crisis,
very young,
naive, inexperienced trader,
fresh out of university studying economics.
So I just...
you just... you kind of accept it, right.
I was busy, you know,
trying to make money in other ways.
There was a lot of sort of kind of easy money
to be made at that time in my area.
And I just kind of accepted,
I wasn't really getting too involved in, you know,
looking at these economic predictions
and like most 22 year olds
fresh out of economics university,
I thought, well, yeah, they’re probably right.
They probably know they're talking about.
And I expected, like everybody else, rapid recovery,
rapid bounce back in interest rates.
Obviously, we know now that didn't happen.
So I sat through 2009
and the interest rates didn't go up.
And people were kind of saying,
well, you know, it takes 18 months.
So, you know, this was a particularly bad crisis.
Maybe it's going to take a little bit longer,
give it a bit more time.
So we get to the end of 2009
and the narrative is kind of unchanged.
Okay, we were wrong, rates haven't gone up yet,
but next year rates will definitely go up.
Obviously again, we know now
we sat through the whole of 2010
and rate stayed 0% all across the world.
And you know, I'm getting a bit older,
getting a bit more experienced by the end of 2010.
I would have just turned 24
and I've got a couple of years
experience as a trader now.
We get into the beginning of 2011
and a lot of people don't remember this,
but there was a kind of mini inflation crisis in 2011
that was quite similar in a lot of ways,
although less extreme
than the inflation crisis we had just after Covid,
which was inflation shot up,
it was much higher than the 2% target,
I think, going up in this country to nearly 6%.
I don't think ever quite hit 6%.
It was driven primarily by energy and food,
similarly to Covid.
So we had this inflation
crisis coming in in the beginning of 2011,
and then people were like,
well, this is really going to be it now, you know,
we not only have
we got all this money flooding in and governments
are running a massive deficit, similarly to Covid.
We had this quantitative easing programs
which are designed to push
even more money into the economy.
So you've got zero interest rates, quantitative easing,
massive government deficits,
just like Covid,
all this money
getting pushed in, so much money getting pushed in
and now you're starting to see inflation go.
And everybody at the beginning of 2011 was like,
well now it's really, really going to happen.
And by then I was 24 and I'd witnessed,
you know, two and a half years,
three years really of like really,
really bad
economic predictions by not just the traders, like,
this is pretty much a broad economic consensus.
You’re always going to get a few people who disagree.
But most traders, most economists
said the same thing throughout.
You know,
they didn't predict the 2008 financial crisis.
There was this famous moment
when did you know the Queen visited LSE,
did you hear about this?
The Queen visited LSE
and, just on some sort of visit,
and she asked one of the professor,
so why didn't you predict the economic crisis then?
Yeah, 2008 crisis comes,
you know, some sort of lone voices called it,
but in general, the economic establishment
hadn't predicted it.
Definitely nothing of that scale.
2009 big recovery didn't happen.
2010 big recovery didn't happen.
We’re sitting at the beginning of 2011
and everybody's like,
now we're going to have a massive recovery.
And I had started to become
like very cynical, basically.
I was making a half million
pound a year
in my early 20s,
and people around me are obviously making millions.
And you see them just consistently wrong.
You start to get to know these guys. And I was lucky.
Like, I worked with some really smart people.
But if you...
the majority of the people
on the trading floor, to be honest,
these are just basically guys from rich families.
And I think if you come from a rich family,
it's kind of the norm to end up at an elite university
and get a job like something on the trading floor.
So you know, you sit there two and a half years,
you start to realise, like, actually
most of the guys making these calls, the economists,
the traders, and they're consistently wrong.
They've been wrong here for like three years. And,
you know, my job was
to be a trader,
so if you can out predict
these guys you can make a lot of money.
So I'm not going to pretend
that my motivation was at all altruistic.
It was like,
you know, here I am, top degree from a top university
on one of the biggest trading floors in the world.
And you start realising,
these guys around me, they just wrong.
They just wrong. They're wrong every year.
And you start realising, well,
I'm in as good a situation as anybody
to figure out why these guys are wrong, basically.
You know,
I've got the elite degree just like everybody else.
You know, I'm in the best place.
These are the top paid economists.
These are the top paid traders.
And they're wrong.
So it was actually really exciting,
this exciting realisation
that you're here
on the cutting edge of like a really important thing,
like economics and everybody's wrong.
So we need to figure out why they're wrong.
Because if we can, we can make a ton of money.
So I started to think a lot about, okay,
well what's the theory?
And I'll explain the theory to you,
which is low interest rates get people spending
because it's cheap to borrow money.
There's no point saving money.
So people should be spending
and all the economic theory says
that people should be spending,
people should be spending, people should be spending.
And yet there I was, early 2011,
and people were not spending.
So there's...
what you can do then, and what I was able to do is,
you can kind of boil down
this really important economic problem of
why is the economy like consistently sh*t?
To a much more objective answerable
question of why aren't people spending money?
And I spent a lot of time
thinking about that simple question of,
why aren't people spending money?
And, you know, I was young, I was 24.
You don't know that much when you’re 24.
I just went and started asking people,
and I think this is where I had quite a big advantage
over a lot of other economists, a lot of other traders,
because I come from a poor background,
I was just a lot closer to just ordinary people.
And, you know,
if you ask ordinary people, and I did
and I think this is a really useful thing to do,
if you ask them, why don't you spend more money?
You know, the answer
then was exactly the same
as what the answer now would be.
The vast majority of people just said, well,
I don't spend any money
because I don't have any more money.
Most people were basically,
you know, money in, money out, you know,
very often money in was less than money out.
You know, they were struggling to spend money.
And I think this is where my experience was different
from a lot of economists and a lot of traders,
because if you were to ask people
from rich families that,
they can't say that
and they wouldn't say
they that, it wouldn’t makes sense to say that.
Most people from rich families,
they're not constrained by their income.
Their income is more than their expenditure.
They save every month.
So what I was seeing was, I think, the correct answer
to the very simple question,
why aren't people spending money,
which is the core question of why is the economy weak,
which was that people didn't have any money.
And that sat in my head for a bit.
And at the time I was working with, I had hired,
a junior trader, an Italian guy.
He’s in the book, so I can't use his real name.
In the book he’s called Titzy.
Really smart kid, Italian kid,
went to Bocconi which is basically the Italian LSE,
and I sort of like, I poke this question around at him.
Okay, well why why maybe people don't have any money.
And he would say,
and we would discuss the fact
that it's kind of impossible
for nobody to have any money.
And we've done videos on this channel
about what is money, this kind of thing.
Money is basically a spreadsheet.
There's winners and losers.
It has to balance out. It has to add up.
That is the way our current monetary system works.
It doesn't make sense to say, like,
nobody has any money.
And furthermore, beyond that,
like other than money, there exists real wealth.
You know, we covered it on part one, What is Wealth?
And, you know,
the wealth wasn't disappearing, you know.
The houses are still here, you know,
the resources are still here,
the businesses are still here,
the buildings are still here.
And that's what most of wealth is.
So, you know, the wealth is not disappearing.
Somebody has to have the money.
And yet when you ask people,
why don't they spend money?
They're like, well, I don't have any money.
And this kind of didn't make any sense.
And that was bouncing around in my head, early 2011.
And then I got called into a meeting.
So I was still a junior traded then, but I used to...
the previous manager had allowed me to come
to like the meeting
of all the senior managers to bring the sandwiches.
So I was able to go to these like quite senior
economist meetings,
and a really good Citibank economist...
I'm sometimes quite mean about economists,
but there are good ones.
And I thought this guy was a good economist.
He showed us all these slides
going through the fiscal situation,
the financial position
of a lot of major world governments.
So you probably remember maybe some people don't.
In 2011,
after this meeting,
there was a crisis of the financial position
of major European governments,
and it was centered on
Italy, Greece, Spain,
Portugal, Ireland,
were the ones who were central in it.
Before that crisis blew up, this guy kind of spotted
oh this could blow up.
And he said, well,
if you look at all of these countries,
they're spending more than they make every year.
They're having to sell their assets,
they're going into debt.
And it wasn't just those countries
that were central in that 2011 crisis.
The situation in the UK was not much better.
Situation of the US, not much better.
Situation in Japan, not much better. So
what you have here is basically governments
also can't spend because they don’t have any more money
and they're running their wealth down.
And that really reminded me of
when my friend said, we don't have any more money.
You know, I didn't...
I didn't just accept that face value.
I kind of dug into a little bit
where I could
and what I kind of found was the big,
the big problem for my friends and their families was
the kids couldn't
see how they would ever be able to afford a property.
And what's important about that
is so, I'm 38 now, In 2011, I was in my mid 20s.
Our parents generation, you know,
even my parents, I come from quite a poor background.
They all own property.
You know,
I went to grammar school,
so I didn't know like the poorest people.
But, you know,
most of my parents generation, they own property.
They own property. And yet my generation
could in many cases never afford to own property.
So what you are seeing
there is the families,
ordinary families
going over time
from being property owning to not property owning.
And I think once you understand that,
it doesn't make any sense to really ask the question of
why don't you spend more money?
Because what you recognise
then is these guys, their wealth
trajectory over
time is going down to zero,
which means the family as a whole
spending more than their income.
And if you're already spending more than your income,
you can't long term spend more.
And then I went into this meeting about governments.
And it's basically the same.
Families spending more on their income,
losing their assets, going into debt.
Governments losing their income...
spending more than their income,
losing assets, going into debt.
And the thing...
you might think
I came out of that meeting thinking like,
oh my God, like, this is a disaster,
Western countries are going to collapse.
But what was really in
my head was the kind of systemic impossibility of this.
It's not possible
for everyone to spend more than their income.
It's not possible.
As a society. Spending and income has to be the same.
You can only consume what you produce.
This is, this is the way that it is.
And it's not possible for everybody to go into debt.
And we've done videos on this, videos on this,
but and you can go look at them.
But if one group goes into debt,
some group must be accumulating
credit, like this has to balance out.
And it's not possible
for everybody to lose their assets.
Not unless there's been an earthquake,
which they hadn't been.
You know, the assets that existed. Right.
So I was just sitting there and I was thinking,
people aren't spending
because they're losing their assets.
Which means they’re actually spending more
than they can possibly spend.
Governments aren't spending
because they're losing their assets,
which means that they're spending more
than they can possibly spend in the long run.
It just doesn't balance.
It's not possible. Where are they?
It was as if everything was like being taken by aliens,
you know, as if all of the assets.
And then obviously
I'm sitting there on the Citibank trading floor
as somebody who had been paid nearly £500,000
the previous two years surrounded by millionaires.
And then you just suddenly realise like,
oh my God, like
we are the balance or the balance is us, like and
and not just us.
Because of course, you know,
whilst we were rich people,
the people whose money we moving
are even richer people.
And you start realising,
oh, and you know, at that time, similarly to now,
the stock market was ripping to all time highs
and you were starting to see like house prices
starting to move
and the gold price was starting to go
and you starting to...
and I suddenly realised, like
the reason that families are losing their homes
and the reason that governments are going
bankrupt is because the wealth
that used to be being held
by ordinary families and by governments
is being transferred to the rich and the super rich.
And once I realised that,
I realised immediately
that is a problem which would worsen over time,
because if families and governments
can't afford to run a balanced budget
when they own their own properties,
when they have some wealth,
well, they definitely can't afford
to run a balanced budget
when they don't own the property
and when they don't have wealth,
because now they've lost that passive income.
They need to pay to rent those things.
And if the rich can afford to outcompete the middle
at this lower level of wealth,
well, now they're richer.
They've got more passive income,
they can out compete them even quicker.
So you can see very quickly this, this core problem.
And this is the really core problem, which is...
should be spoken about a million times
more than it is,
which is as inequality gets bigger,
the passive income that
the rich receive will get bigger.
The passive income that the poor spend will get bigger,
and the rate of increase of inequality
will increase over time.
And this will just,
not only will this get worse over time,
it will accelerate in a kind of what
a mathematician would call an exponential fashion. And,
you know, this was all going through my head,
like sitting there on the trading desk.
And of course, I've thought about it
a lot more now, so I can kind of explain it clearly.
What hit me there as a trader was
this gets worse forever.
This gets worse and worse and worse
and worse forever and ever and ever.
And at that time,
the beginning of 2011,
as I explained a little bit earlier,
everybody was like,
this is the year that the recovery really happens.
This is the year that the rates really go.
And I was sitting there
early 2011 saying with everybody saying, this is it,
this is the recovery, this is the recovery.
And I had just become almost certain
that the economy would collapse forever.
And this might sound callous,
and I think it's written very well in the book.
I realised,
oh my God, I could make so much f**king money here.
because everyone is wrong and not only that,
they probably won't figure it out for a long time.
They'll be wrong next year
and they’ll be wrong
the year after, and they’ll be wrong the year after.
Because at the time I'd been to LSE, right.
And I,
you know, and I was
after LSE you go into trading
and are surrounded by economists
and the kids that come in on the grad scheme,
they're all of the top graduates
from all of the top economics
uni’s across the world, right.
So you're very plugged in to what economists are saying
and what economists are thinking.
You get all of these emails from economists,
you all these economics calls.
So I knew what the economists were thinking.
Nobody was talking about inequality.
Nobody was talking about inequality at that time.
And I was like, this is why they've been wrong.
This is why, this is why they're consistently wrong.
And I mean, it made sense
because if they are consistently wrong,
which I think was obvious even in 2011,
but should be even more obvious now, it’s
because they're missing a big thing.
And I've been to universities,
I knew that they weren't looking at this thing
and it had just become...
the penny had dropped for me.
This was it, this is the big thing.
They're going to miss it.
They're not going to catch it.
And I put this massive trade on that rates
and stay zero.
I basically made a tonne of money
that year basically betting
that the economy would be a disaster.
And obviously that was one year, 2011.
So you, you’re not...
I was quite confident in that.
I was confident enough to bet a lot on it,
but I wasn't immediately
like 100% certain I was right.
And you can never be 100% certain.
But then you go into the next year
and the same thing happens the next year.
You're like, well,
everybody’s saying there’s going to be recovery,
and you're saying there’s not going to be a recovery
because the inequality is getting worse.
And then you start to,
you start to think about other things.
You start, for example, I start to think, okay, well,
if there is a big increase in wealth inequality
that is underlying
the reason that markets are wrong on interest rates
and also the reason why economists
are wrong in their predictions,
maybe the market's wrong on other things.
So I started to think, well,
what would it mean for asset prices more broadly
if inequality would increase?
Well that's quite an easy question right.
Because we know
ordinary people
tend to spend money on goods and services,
rich people tend to spend money buying assets.
So if inequality increases, you would expect to see
asset prices rising while
goods,
services, wages,
what we call CPI inflation
because CPI doesn't look at assets,
sort of dicks around at the bottom.
And at this time...
and then I was like okay,
well the asset prices are going to go,
stock market is going to go.
And that again
people...
the economy was so weak in 2011,
we had this big sovereign debt crisis
and we had more austerity.
The economy was so weak.
Everyone was like, stock market is going to be s**t.
But I was like, no,
if I'm right on this,
stock markets will go, because the economy being s**t
if the...
if the economy is s**t because governments are in debt
well who are they in debt to?
That again itself is a manifestation of inequality, right.
So I said, stock prices will go up. And then they did.
And I said,
well you'll get asset price inflation combined with
disinflation for the poor. And it did.
And what you start seeing is this,
this understanding of inequality,
it seems to explain all of the incorrect predictions.
And then you start being able
to predict everything correctly.
And I think that is the big giveaway.
I think when you understand...
you know,
I think it would be easy to turn around and say,
oh, you're just mad. You know, you're just pessimistic.
If I'm pessimistic, why do the bets keep being right?
You know, if this is just pessimism,
why do the bets keep being right?
And, you know, I consistently made money betting on
the economy staying weak.
Markets continue to predict
interest rate normalisation way beyond that.
2012, 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019.
Rates in this country stayed zero,
and there would be a few times
you would see rates pop up and the predictions pop up.
And I would just go back in and bet,
because I knew you can't,
if you don't fix this fundamental problem,
you're not going be able to fix the economy.
And this simple way of understanding it, which is that
the growth in wealth inequality,
not income inequality, wealth inequality
is being missed.
And you start being able to
predict everything correctly.
This one simple idea
that inequality is at the center,
that it is driving living standards
down, has enabled me to correctly predict
the weak recovery from 2008.
The cost of living crisis during Covid.
Stock price rally in the mid 2010s.
Stock price rally after Covid.
Collapse in living standards.
The collapse of central political parties.
The rise of the far right.
Like I'm not Mystic Meg here. The theories right?
The theory is right
and it's not being looked at.
And if we don't take action on it,
it will get worse and worse and worse and worse.
So that's it, I think that is why
inequality is the core central problem.
I would encourage people to care about it
because if you don't take action on it,
it means living standards
getting worse and worse and worse.
And we will talk in our next video
about how do we fix it.
So thank you very much.
Thanks for watching.
Support the channel. Support the Patreon.
Send the videos to your family,
to your mum, to your friends.
Let's stop things being terrible.
Thank you. Take care.