Okay guys welcome back to Gary’s Economics.
Today
we are going to do a final channel
update before I go on holiday.
Okay I'm talking to you today on the 25th of June.
We won't put this video out until much later.
In the middle of the start
of a beautiful London heatwave.
I am about to
fly off to Japan in a few days to finally do
this long cycle I've wanted to do for ages.
so I thought it'd be a nice time
to just look back a little bit on what has been
a mad year for me and for the channel
and for the world and talk a little bit
about what we've achieved
and what we're going to do in the future.
So the first thing to say is,
of course, that this year has been basically
just a massive, massive year for growth on the channel.
At the moment I'm shooting this, we are
about 275,000 subs on YouTube.
A year ago that was something like 80,000.
We've had massive growth on Instagram, on TikTok.
We've started to really cut through
quite a lot, basically.
And that's
thanks to a lot of your support sharing the videos.
Thanks to a lot of hard work
from the team that we've put together.
And yes, something to be proud of,
in terms of how we're affecting
the conversation.
You know, my aim
with this
channel has always been basically
to build the bridge between
inequality and the economy.
I think that
almost everybody agrees
that high levels of inequality are a bad thing,
but I think people have
believed or been kind of fooled
into believing for a long time that
high levels of inequality
are kind of
a necessary sacrifice,
kind of the price you pay for a good economy
in a capitalist society.
But those of you who know my history will know
I made a lot of money basically
betting that high inequality
will destroy the economy in the long term.
And what I really want to do
is get people to see
the things that are happening
in the real economy, in their real lives.
Increased difficulty with
buying houses,
in many cases, just paying the rent, buying food
and connect them
with the really rapidly
growing inequality we're seeing in society.
I think that if we can get people
to recognise that
the reason that they or their kids
or their grandkids are struggling
economically is because of growing inequality,
and that problem will get worse and worse,
that we can start to take action on it. And,
we definitely have been making progress on that.
This year, I brought in for the first time
a couple of professionals.
Professional videographer,
professional channel manager
to help me manage the growth of the channel
during the book release. And,
in order to do that,
we went and got some funding from like a big
charitable foundation here in London.
They do a lot of work on inequality.
That's why they funded us.
And, they've been sort of surveying people,
and they've found there's been a massive increase in
people who think that the reason
the economy is bad is because of
growing inequality, basically. And,
you know, when I heard that,
I was really proud because that's
partly, I think because of this channel.
And I think that's partly
because of the work that we do here.
So we're getting out there, we're reaching people,
we're still not reaching enough people.
I think still, most people in the country don't realise
growing inequality is the reason for growing poverty,
for growing difficulties in their lives.
But we are making progress.
I watch a lot of news in the morning
because I want to see what people are being told,
and I watch the most basic commonplace news in the UK.
I watch BBC news and Sky news.
And I was watching
BBC radio five live
while I was eating breakfast the other day and,
they were interviewing a Green candidate.
We mentioned on another video
that the Greens have basically adopted
our policies of a wealth tax.
And I was watching the interviews and
nobody was talking about wealth inequality,
and it was kind of making me think like,
what more do we have to do to really get this issue
really into the discussion
so that mainstream politicians have to talk about it.
So it has to be mentioned.
And exactly when I,
was thinking
that I was eating my porridge, there was a caller,
a lady called Helen from Burnley called in and,
she basically said, you know,
are you guys aware of how much money
has being given out
during Covid, the government deficit,
since Covid is £700 billion
and are you aware of where that money's ended up?
Whether it's ended up with the richest people,
whether it's increased inequality?
Because what I'm seeing is
a massive increase in the wealth
of billionaires and millionaires.
And, I don't think people are talking about it.
People aren’t doing anything about it. And,
it was immediately obvious
because nobody else really talks about these issues
and because of the language
she was using that she got that information
from this channel. And,
you know, I know that's a one off instance,
but it was quite emotional for me to see that we’re
starting to cut through, we’re stating
to affect the conversation.
And I think that's,
that's something we can all be proud of.
It's part of the conversation now.
But at the same time, realistically,
it's not a central enough part.
I think we're starting to make cuts
throughs with people on the street,
but we're seeing a lot of other problems coming in.
The rhetoric that the problems are primarily
caused by immigration
is growing and growing and growing.
Partly because of the, you know, the resurgence
in the return of Nigel Farage.
His voice is way, way, way louder than mine.
And,
because this inequality problem is not being fixed, it
inevitable that the economic problems
and the living standards
problems will keep getting worse
and people will become very dissatisfied
with the incoming Labour government.
They'll become very dissatisfied with the status quo.
They’ll want change,
and they'll be looking for an alternative. And,
at this point in time,
when you look at the loudness of ‘the
problem is immigration’ versus
the loudness of ‘the problem is inequality’,
it's really hard to see them not winning.
And, I want to be really clear when I say this.
You know, I'm not saying that immigration doesn't
cause economic problems for certain groups of people,
you know. In fact, I think it probably does.
I think the problem you have here
is that it is going to drown out this narrative.
And if we don't win this narrative, then
the economy will continue to collapse, basically.
That's the problem on one side.
On the other side,
we have an incoming Labour government,
who are advised by a group of mainstream economists
and journalists
who are super, super resistant to taxation.
There was a tweet by a guy, what was his name?
Dan Neidle recently, which said,
if taxing wealth is so easy, why doesn't anybody do it?
And he showed that, you know, across the world,
wealth taxation is quite low.
And, I thought that was quite funny because, you know,
what we have at the moment is a situation
where basically across the Western world,
living standards are falling.
And it's pretty clear that what is being done
across the Western world is
a kind of a unanimous shared economic opinion
being driven by these
relatively well-paid economists.
And it's not working. It's not working.
And we need to do something different.
But unfortunately, I think what we have
is a lot of relatively well-paid
economists and academics and politicians
who have decent salaries
and decent houses and mortgages to pay
that just don't want to pay any more tax, basically.
And even though I'm quite explicit,
I'm not trying to tax them, I'm
trying to tax the very rich.
I think they're just very instinctively conservative,
very instinctively protective.
I continue to believe that
we're not going to get change
delivered to us from well-paid people,
from the richest people in society.
You know, I would like this sort of...
this well-paid middle class
who are not the sort of asset, super rich
to support us,
because I would like them to realise that
if things keep going
the way they're going, living standards will collapse.
And we'll keep
campaigning them,
we'll keep lobbying the Labour Party,
we’ll keep trying to build support.
But I really don't think we'll win
unless we have ordinary people demanding it.
So I'm going to keep doing it.
And, we're going to keep pushing it
and hopefully we’ll make it.
But for the moment, I'm going on holiday.
For me personally, it's been an absolutely crazy year.
I wrote a whole book, which, came out in March,
The Trading Game.
I've talked about it a lot on the channel.
It was a Sunday Times
number one best seller for two weeks.
It was in the top ten for eight or nine weeks.
I had press
all over the world, loads of press in this country.
It's blown up
this channel massively.
I've been getting recognised in the street
a lot, in the gym, in Lidl, all over the place.
And that's great.
It was always part of the plan
to, sort of, use my face and use my name.
But it's been a lot, basically. It's been a lot.
I think people who only watch the videos
probably don't realise that I'm also
doing a ton of interviews
for all different press all over the world,
and speaking to people
about how we can sort of grow this movement,
and also like
thinking all the time about
what are the ways that we can communicate
to push this message out there.
And, you know, you write a book,
I was published by Penguin, you know,
you get a massive amount of support,
like I had basically a full time
publicist working with me.
She was amazing.
She has to be like,
take a lot of the credit for
the growth of this channel.
But at the end of the day, she's trying to sell books.
She's not trying to push a political message,
you know, and,
I obviously say,
you know,
I want to try to push this
political message,
but I'm always thinking,
how can we use this publicity and to help grow
these ideas?
And, it's a lot of work.
It’s been a lot of work creatively.
I'm always thinking about new ways
we can push things creatively. And,
it's just been hard basically, it's exhausting.
I'm not the kind of person who
loves being recognised in the street.
I don't want to tell people
not to say hi to me in the street
because everyone's really, really nice
and I really appreciate everybody's support.
But it's just weird. It's just I'm no used to it.
I'll get recognised like seven, eight times a day now,
and it's just a bit scary.
And, you know, like,
weird things happen,
like Mail on Sunday did a massive, like,
two page hit piece on me.
I've got friends from Citibank forwarding
mails from, like,
FT reporters asking if there's any dirt,
any dirt on Gary Stevenson
which is stressful and stuff.
You have to sort of,
it’s new for me, stuff you have to deal with.
But really more than anything,
it's just stressful sort of seeing...
Seeing how difficult it's
going to be to win this fight.
I think we've got a long way to go
before we get accepted by these sort of
well-paid, fancy posh
economists who don't like the idea of more taxes.
We've had the big boost from the book now.
I need to think about
how can we keep growing it, as well as
how can we keep making content?
And, yeah,
basically the last month or two,
I've been pretty exhausted, and,
I've decided to take a bit of time off.
Go back to Japan, where I lived for two years,
do this big cycle I want to do.
Just basically tear away
and try and sort of refresh myself creatively,
which means that we're pre-recording loads.
I don't think this will go out
until maybe the end of July, maybe even into August,
but we're trying to pre-record loads
so that we don't leave a big gap.
But we might end up doing a gap.
Depends sort of what I need personally.
But I've been thinking about what we're going to do
when we come back.
How we are going to manage the channel.
This year we managed to get, as I've said,
a little bit of external funding on the channel,
and that's basically paid
the wages of my videographer,
my manager, and we’ve got another guy doing subtitling.
We had somebody help us
with just the branding of the channel a little bit.
But it's tricky,
external funding is tricky because we had,
obviously we had the election called early,
and they didn’t want me to do any political videos.
So, I basically just funded some videos myself.
And also the funding will run out at some point
and we sort of have to decide what to do.
At the moment,
the channel is making just kind of roughly enough
from YouTube revenue
to pay for the staff that we've got.
But I think going forward,
if it's going to be really a thing,
I'm probably going to need more support,
a bit more creative support,
a bit more help
by structuring the videos,
managing the videos, managing the YouTube.
I look at
how much we’ve grown
because we’ve had a publicist from Penguin,
and I do think if we had some real
PR support on the channel, it could be really bigger.
So,
I've been thinking for a while about whether we should
basically open up for donations
so that we can hire more staff, and,
I think I'm going to do that.
So what I'm planning at the moment is to
start a not for profit company
so that anyone who donates, can know
for sure that the money is not going to me
and basically open a Patreon,
see if we get some money in,
and then maybe just build up a little pot of cash
so that I can get the support that I need.
I know that with people that say, well,
you're a millionaire, Gary you should fund it, but,
I'm a millionaire that spends most of my time
working for free on a YouTube channel.
So, I don't really
want to start funding it myself as well,
because, I'm already working for free.
I've worked on it for free for a long time, and,
I don’t think it’s going to work basically,
if we're going to have to make it as big as we need,
we're going to need staff.
And I think if we're going to really, really grow,
we're going to need more people. And,
I'm not going to be able to keep funding it myself.
I have funded up till now.
But if it's going to go,
we're going to need a bit more money.
So I think I'm going to open a Patreon.
I'm not going to say to anybody, you need to donate.
You need to donate.
I'm going to open it,
see what we get,
and if we get enough money,
we can hopefully use that to make a few more videos,
mix up a little bit the creative output,
make some longer videos,
get some stuff with animations in.
But yeah, I think that's what we're going to have to do
because it's just basically
getting too big for me to manage it.
I want to be able to like, totally split
the finances off.
Really what I want to get is the finances separate.
So I can just focus on the creative side
and not have to worry about having to fund it as well.
So we'll do that.
I'll try and get that sorted,
hopefully before I’m back.
But first and foremost,
I'm going to take a little break, go and chill out.
Try and come back with some good,
creative stuff because,
one video
a week on top of all of these mental interviews
is quite a lot.
And sometimes I feel a little bit creatively burnt out.
But yeah, I'm not going to stop.
I think the way that this channel
is going to go,
I'm probably always going to have to
take bits of time out to just escape the pressure
and the constant creative churn,
because it's hard to do something
good, new, creative once a week.
But, I'll keep doing it.
I'll keep doing that at a pace that works for me.
We'll open for funding, but we won't paywall
any of the content.
We'll just see what we get
and whether that means we can grow
more quickly and get
get more staff and get more support.
If you do choose to donate,
we'll really appreciate that.
But for now,
thank you very much for all of your support,
whether that's in the last 2 or 3 months,
whether that's in the last 3 or 4 years.
Thanks for your supporting on the channel.
I really, truly believe if we don't manage
to get some action on this rapidly
growing inequality, that it will have
a devastating impact on ordinary people.
But I think we can. I think we can do it.
I think if you see the growth of this channel
this year, it shows that demand is there.
I'll do my best to try to get the strategy right.
If we get a bit of funding,
then I'll try and get some experts in who are not
economists trying to run a YouTube channel on the side.
But we'll keep growing.
We're going to get opportunities here and
people are supporting it,
and, I'll keep fighting for it
if you keep fighting for it,
but maybe not for the next couple of months.
Have a good summer. And,
good luck.
Thank you.