Okay, welcome back to Gary's economics.
Today, we are going to explain why the rich get richer.
All right. So I was talking the other day
to a good friend of mine,
a Dutch guy who I studied economics with back at Oxford
when I was doing my Master's in ‘17 to ’19.
And when I was at Oxford, I was very adamant,
very adamant that the
economy would get worse and worse for ordinary people.
Living standards would fall
because inequality was increasing and increasing.
Now, this is not a popular idea
in modern university, academic economics.
And this guy sort of was quite skeptical at the time,
but it's obviously been five or six years since then.
And he and I
and you have seen
inequality massively increase
and living standards massively decrease.
And he's kind of started to be convinced
that I'm correct, which
if you stick with my channel for long enough
and keep seeing my predictions
be right, hopefully you will be too.
So he messaged me the other day, and he was like, look,
I think you're right.
Inequality is just destroying the economy.
I think it's important,
we need to do something about it.
But he asked me, why is it that suddenly now
in the last
twenty years, ten years,
especially the last five years,
why is inequality increasing now?
What is actually causing the increase in inequality?
And I thought that was a really interesting question
and something that was worth
discussing and explaining on the channel.
So I think the first thing you need to know
in order to answer that question
is that for the vast majority of human history,
at least in the last 2000 years,
human societies have been extremely unequal
and living standards have been, in most cases,
very, very low.
It was only really after the Second World War
that inequality decreased significantly
in parts of the world,
here in the UK, in Western Europe,
North America, places like Japan.
But of course in the rest of the world,
inequality stayed very high
and living standards stayed very low.
But if you go back and look before World War Two,
basically most of history is
extremely unequal societies.
So I think in order to answer the question,
why is inequality rising now?
You first need to understand that
really it is the last 70 years that are the exception.
What we have had is an exceptional period
only in certain places, which is that
Western Europe, North America,
Japan, Australia, a few other places
have had historically
very equal,
low inequality societies
for 70 years and very high living standards.
That's not normal.
That didn't exist
almost ever basically. It was a specific period.
So the reason that I mention that is
it's not actually something
unusual that is happening now,
that inequality is becoming very large.
This is actually the norm.
So I think if we look at human history,
we kind of have to accept that human societies
tend towards very high levels of inequality.
And we have a few examples
in the last 70 years of places
where that didn't happen.
So let's discuss why it happens,
why the inequality grows
in the context of this basically always happens.
And what I said to my friend was really,
really it’s very simple.
So you can look at it in the very specific case,
which is in our societies that we live in now.
What happens is you go to work,
you get paid your 30, 40 grand a year.
You spend almost all of it on
rent, mortgage,
food, bills,
and it goes towards the owners of the properties,
the owners of the debt, the owners of the
production, of the things that you need,
which is essentially rich people.
So you go to work, you make 40 grand,
you give it all to rich people.
They use that to buy the rest of the assets.
It's a relatively simple dynamic.
I've spoken about it a lot on the channel.
But this is the specific case.
I think what this is,
is a specific example
of basically a more general concept,
which is when power is unequally distributed,
people who have a lot of power,
which in our society basically means rich people
can use that power to dispossess the less powerful.
So in our society,
that means rich people use your salary,
which you've paid to them, they give it to their
kids, their kids buy your house.
Your kids don't have a house.
But this can manifest differently in different ways.
This is simply
a specific case of the general rule
that when power is unequal,
the powerful can dispossessed the weak.
And this leads very naturally
to an accumulation of power. I'm powerful. You're not.
I use that power to take your stuff. And
you can see this happen.
If you look throughout
sort of the history of medieval Europe.
What you saw was, for a period
it was lots of small states.
And then when certain kingdoms became powerful,
they used that power to take the kingdoms around them.
It's another example of this, you know,
this is why human history tends
towards high levels of inequality,
because once you have inequality,
then the rich can use their power
to dispossess the weak. And that's all of history.
That is all of history.
That is what happens in human societies.
If you look at the history of human societies,
human societies have always been very unequal,
except for one period in time,
70 years after the Second World War,
when a lot of societies
suddenly became much more equal.
Why was that?
I think the best clue, I always remember
there's a song by the Beatles.
I'm a big fan of the Beatles,
first time I’ve mentioned that on the channel,
called Taxman.
Yeah, one of the opening lines of the song
is written from the perspective of the Taxman,
which says, one for you, 19 for Me.
And this is because the Beatles, at the
peak of their success, were paying
95% top income tax rate in the UK.
Now, I'm not advocating for a 95% top income tax rate.
The top inheritance tax rate at the time was 90%
during that period up until the eighties specifically,
we had in Western Europe and also in America,
which has a reputation as a low tax society,
up until the eighties we had extremely high tax rates
on the very rich
and that basically prevented
the rich from rapidly accumulating
wealth of the rest of their countries.
That is the exception. That is the exception.
If you have systems that prevent the rich
and the powerful from taking the wealth and power
of the poor, then you can prevent it.
If you don't have those system, you can't prevent it.
So the reason that inequality is increasing
is that
the rich are very powerful
and they can
use the income that they get from you
to take the rest of the stuff.
And this is always the way it has been
and it's always the way it will be.
But I don't want to be excessively fatalistic here
because I see people in the comments
all the time saying it was always like that.
It was always like that.
Listen, we had 70 years when it was not like that.
We had 70 years
when inequality was unusually low
in a lot of countries, especially, you know,
most of the countries of Western Europe,
and that was 70 years in which
postmen and cleaners and hairdressers
could buy houses and go on holidays
and raise families and afford space.
This is not the norm.
But we had that because we had
very high rates of tax on wealthier people.
Listen, you need that.
You need to have structures in place in your economy
that prevent the rich from taking all of the wealth.
If you don't have that, history teaches us
the rich get all of the wealth.
And once the rich have all of the wealth,
not just history, but the present world shows us
ordinary people end up with very poor
living conditions.
If you go to countries that are very unequal,
if you go to...
I mean, it's most of the world, to be honest.
You go to a places like India, South Africa,
you know, almost anywhere in Latin America,
very unequal societies
lead to very poor living standards.
This is the norm.
We prevented it before.
We prevented it by levying
very high tax rates on the very, very rich. So,
you know, I know I see
people in the comments all the time
accusing me of being a communist
because I want high tax rates on the rich.
Listen, I'm a trader in my heart of hearts.
I made a lot of money betting on this.
I'm still betting on it now.
My firm belief
is that if you don't tax rich people,
living standards collapse for ordinary people.
It's happening now. It will continue to happen.
We can reverse it, but we need to tax the rich.
And I'm not talking about you, Dave,
in the comments, who's an accountant making £60 grand.
I'm talking about families with £10 million,
£100 million in assets.
If you don't tax them,
they'll take everything
that includes all of your assets,
your kids will be poor, your grandkids will be poor.
You won’t own anything.
You need to protect yourself
from the people who are taking your assets,
that is the rich.
We're fighting against it. Support the channel.
Educate yourself,
educate your friends, educate your family.
If enough people say no, we can change it
just like we changed after World War Two.
But it needs enough people
to step forward and push back.
I'm pushing. I hope you’ll push too.
Thank you very much.