It's like suddenly saying,
okay, I have this 45 year old
son who's not doing very well,
and I'm going to protect him. Yeah. Yeah.
We have in the news today.
Today is what is it
called, freedom Day, Liberation today.
Today is the day that
today is the day
that Donald Trump is trying to impose a lot of tariffs.
So I know you talk a lot in your work
about how poor countries become rich.
It's a really interesting topic
because really not a lot of poor
countries have successfully become rich in the last
70 years.
And Korea
is probably like
one of the outstanding examples of one that has done.
And correct me if I'm wrong,
but from my understanding of your work,
you speak a lot
about how actually
a lot of the countries which did become rich,
not just Korea,
but also including the United States in its history
and the United Kingdom,
use things like tariffs and things like protectionism.
So I guess I couldn't really have you on today.
I don't know if Trump's tariff day without asking you
what you think about tax as a concept.
What do you think about Trump's tariffs plans.
Where do you think they will
they improve living standards for Americans?
Yeah.
Well,
first of all, tariffs, like all other policy tools,
can be used for good, useful, bad purposes, you know.
So, you know, there's no tool that is,
universally, good or universally bad.
Yeah.
So, it all depends on why are you using it,
how you are using it. Yeah.
So the most, successful use of, tariff is,
based on this idea of infant industry protection.
Yeah.
So that idea is, basically that the governments or,
economically backward nations
need to protect and nurture the industries,
through tariffs,
but also other means like, subsidies and so on,
so that they can grow up
and compete with, superior foreign firms eventually.
But why they develop, they need to be protected
and, you know, the hint is in the name.
I mean, it's, based on the idea of, child rearing.
Yeah.
I mean, in the same way that,
you could send your kids, to work at the age of 5 or
6, as.
Many people do.
Yeah.
And that, today, many, countries are still doing,
many poor countries
and that that will, in the short run,
save you money because,
you don't have to, people, the kids, the,
education, food,
you know, accommodation and, he will,
support himself, you know, but this will mean that,
this guy can never become,
I don't know, nuclear physicist.
Do it. Economy. Economy.
Yeah. That's right.
God forbid.
Yeah. The architect. Yeah.
He cannot become a high productivity person.
If he doesn't go to school, go to eventually,
hopefully university. Yeah.
So you need to attack,
send the kid to school until it, kind of grows up.
Yeah.
And then that, push it into the, other labor market.
And, yeah,
country after country has,
succeeded with this, scheme and, Britain and
indeed the 18th and early 19th century was,
still not the leading, technological,
nation.
In Europe, because at the time, Belgium,
the Netherlands, parts of Italy were ahead of Britain
in terms of technology.
Britain used, protective measures to grow
is domestic industries in the 19th century and until,
in the Second World War, the US had very high tariffs,
you know, 40, 50%.
So Trump tariff is nothing compared to that,
because that at the time the US was, basically
struggling against,
British and other European competition. Yeah.
And this is idea, which was actually formalized,
by the first finance minister called the
they call it,
Treasury secretary in the country
of the United States
of America,
Alexander Hamilton, the guy on the $10 bill,
the guy who's, life has been made into a hip
hop musical. Yeah.
So that, this idea has, enabled,
many nations, later, Germany, Sweden,
France, that,
Japan, Korea, Taiwan all use this idea to develop.
This particular. Exact.
Young industries.
Well, what Trump is doing is it's not that exactly.
Yeah, yeah.
So it's, like, that, something is saying,
okay, I have this that, 45 year old
son was not doing very well.
And I'm going to protect him.
Yeah, yeah. Okay.
This is that that, nonsensical.
Yeah, yeah.
Also,
you know, he seems to think that, by using tariff,
you can, make other, countries,
come and invest in the US.
And, I mean, yeah, it's sad
that something that has happened
many, many times in the past,
many developing countries put up high tide before, but,
kind of, that, was, partly
to encourage the domestic producers, but also that,
to motivate,
foreign companies to come and set up, factories.
So, for example, Brazil had a very high protection
against 14 car imports there in the 1960s and 70s.
So fiat for
these guys, came and, built cars in Brazil.
Yeah, yeah.
So that, that this is known as, tariff jumping.
So that Trump's hope is that, if I set up this tariff
wall, Korean companies, Japanese companies,
German companies are going to come and produce
their electric cars and semiconductors.
It. Yeah, some of it is going to happen.
But the trouble is that,
this is, not going to be one year.
You know, if,
for, Well, was this making America great?
Yeah, yeah.
And of course, it will raise the cost, so.
Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. So
first of all, you cannot
kind of rebuild, this, industries
by simply having one factory here, one factory
there because, you know, in order to have, really,
high productivity, you need,
not just the factory making the final product, but,
a whole kind of, industrial ecosystem as,
some economists call it.
So you need the, workers with the right skills
infrastructure that is, suited to the industry,
even university, departments, doing
research in the area that you are, specializing in.
So on this,
you have this, that tissue, but, support system.
Yeah. You are not going to achieve high productivity.
Yeah.
But secondly, that the most,
something that most people don't even realize
is that the US financial system
is now so parasitic
that, is not going to that,
Allow that, Mr.
Trump's plan to work
because,
you know, the idea is that when you give protection,
your domestic companies will not only have, protection
from foreign competition,
but they also have extra resources, you know,
because that that, they can charge, more.
Yeah.
And the hope is that they'll use that resource
to invest in raising productivity,
which is what happened in Japan. Korea.
Yeah.
Now, the US, financial system.
Is actually going to drain this extra resource
from these companies. Yeah.
And to make that, income inequality even worse.
Yeah. Yeah.
So yeah, because, in the last 25 years,
the American, the top American corporations
have, given away something like 90
to 95% of their profits, to shareholders.
Yeah, through dividends and more importantly,
stock buybacks. Yeah, yeah.
So you can buy extra resources to these companies.
Are they going to invest. No.
Their shareholders will say to more stock buybacks.
Yeah. Yeah.
We want
you think it's going to lead to higher inequality.
Yeah. Exactly. Yeah.
On top of that
you will have but until you kind of build
at least some, additional industrial base,
you're going to have serious inflation problem.
Yeah. Yeah.
I think it's.
Just, this is a politically unsustainable.
It's going to be it's
going to make life harder for poor people.
Yeah. Exactly.
Yeah.
So I think, increasing inequality.
And, you know, seriously,
I mean, you cannot rebuild,
an industrial base that had been eroded
for the last 40 years within 2 or 3 years. Yeah.
Yeah, it will take at least, a couple of decades.
Yeah.
And this is very, very broad
tariff on almost everything. Exactly. Yeah.
Let's try it. Yeah.
It seems unwise.
Yeah.
If, tariffs are going to work, it has to be targeted.
Do you want to develop automobile industry?
Yes. Protect automobile industry.
But then and then you.
Can make sure you have the workers.
Exactly. Yeah. You have.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah.
There's no plan like that. Yeah. So.
So we don't think we're going
to see an improvement in living standards.
No no no. No neither do I.
Yeah. It's hopefully won't be that bad, but, Yeah.
Pessimistic.
Yeah, I'm very pessimistic.
But, you know,
one good thing about that
Trump is that he has no ideology.
If it doesn't work, he will change his mind that,
Yeah,
I do want well,
I said this on the channel
before,
it's very hard to guess from what Trump says,
what Trump actually is going to do.
That's it.
So, we we hope he'll go back on this
because I think it would be bad
for everyone, including Americans, I suspect.
Yeah. Yeah.