[Chris] LBC News, time 6:31. It's Chris Golds
with you here,
live across the UK this Thursday evening.
We're on
DAB digital radio, on your smart speaker,
and on Global Player, of course.
The FTSE 100 has ended the penultimate
day of trading this week in the red,
down 41 points at 6,526. We'll find out
where it opens with
Lisa Aziz at about eight o'clock tomorrow
morning. She is, of course, live on
breakfast from six.
Now, if you've been on social media over
the last 24/48 hours or so, you will
have seen this story, but
maybe you've been slightly confused by
it. I know I have.
It's market regulators in the US that
are gonna review this rally in shares
of the struggling retailer
GameStop, following an internet campaign.
Stocks have risen over
1,700% in the past couple of weeks,
mostly driven by users of the social
media platform Reddit.
They were trying to show how easy it is
to manipulate the system.
Confused? Well, let's try and break it
down for you here on LBC News. I'd like
to say I'm joined by
Gary Stevenson, who joins us now. He's an
ex-City trader and is now an economist.
Evening to you, Gary.
[Gary] Hi, Chris.
[Chris] So what has gone on here? What sparked
it? Why GameStop? What's going on? Give
us the detail.
[Gary] Okay, so first, to give you a little
bit of background. The US is obviously
going through a very similar massive COVID
epidemic, like we are. A lot of people
lost their jobs, a lot of people lost
incomes,
a lot of people are sitting at home,
unable to work, and the government's been
sending out stimulus cheques to support
these people.
Now, at the same time, the US stock
market has been on an absolute surge.
It's nearly doubled in the last nine
months, and some stocks like Tesla have
gone up nearly six times.
Other things like Bitcoin absolutely
exploding. So we've got a load of people
sitting at home,
they can't work, they're not making any
money. At the same time, the richest
people in the country, like Jeff Bezos,
the value of their companies are
doubling. And this is on the back of ten
years of stock markets exploding in that
country.
So people at home are starting to think,
"Listen, I'm not happy with this. Work
isn't working for me,
I'm not making any money and the super-
rich are just getting super-rich on the
stock markets," and they want to get
involved.
So they're surging onto the internet, and
they're going through this website,
Reddit,
which is a social media site, essentially
it's a message board site. There's an
area on there called WallStreetBets,
that's where people go to
talk about how to make money on the
markets, what stocks to buy, this kind of
thing.
And some people came up with the idea
about GameStop. So what you need to
understand about GameStop
is there's a big hedge fund, well a few
hedge funds, that decided that this was a
weak
company. They decided to try and push the
stock price down by short selling it.
So you need to know a little bit about
short selling, alright? So, to short sell
a stock,
normally if you think a stock price is
going to go up, you buy it. But how do
you make money if a stock price is gonna
go down?
Well, the way you do it is you borrow the
stock, for example for a week, for
someone who has it, and then you sell it,
hoping to buy it back later at a lower
price.
Now, these hedge funds had shorted a lot
of this stock, and some people on Reddit
figured it out. So they said, "Look, if
we all go together and we buy loads and
loads of this stock, we can push the
price up massively.
We'll refuse to lend out any of the stock
to the short sellers, and then the short
sellers will have to buy the stock back
when their loans of their stock run out.
That means we can push the price up, and
then the hedge funds will have to buy at
a massively higher price, and we'll all
make loads of money."
Now, this is a thing which is relatively
well known historically in financial
markets. It's called a short squeeze. You
push the price up so that all the shorts
lose loads of money and they have to buy
the higher prices.
There was a massive short squeeze in the
gold market, for example, in the '80s.
Sometimes it's called cornering the
market.
They've even been guys who done this
with sort of food markets, like wheat.
"We're gonna buy all the wheat, and
the people who need them, we're gonna
charge exorbitant prices."
So, basically, amazingly, this horde of
sort of unrelated people who were sitting
at home trading on the internet
managed to push GameStop up 1,500% in
about two weeks, which was phenomenal.
That caused this one hedge fund, I think
it's Melvin is the name, to almost go
bankrupt. They lost about, I think, 30%
of their assets under value.
I mean, it really is a phenomenal story.
But I think what this tells you,
people are starting to to this
situation, where the way we deal with
crisis is to bail out the stock markets
but not to bail out ordinary people, and
people want to get involved.
But I mean, the way it's played out has
been really phenomenal. My big concern
now is, and I think I would like to tell
people listening at home,
really be careful before you get involved
in things like this, because it is
inevitable, in my opinion,
I think most market professionals would
agree, that this stock will collapse back
down at some point.
And some people are gonna make a lot
of money on this. You know, there's
someone on this Reddit website who claims
to have turned
$50,000 into $47 million. [Chris] Yeah
[Gary] If you get involved now, that's not
gonna be you. And at some point, this is
gonna collapse
and some people are gonna be holding
it. So, I would just really note of
caution to people listening: don't rush
in and get involved in this, now, my
strong recommendation.
[Chris] Do you think this is gonna spark
some sort of trend?
[Gary] But it's already a trend! I mean, look
at Bitcoin, look at Tesla, look at... I
mean,
the thing is, you need to understand what
is happening with regards to the
coronavirus crisis. Governments all over
the world...
[Chris] But Tesla's stock's not going up
because lots of people are chatting about
it on Reddit, they're going up because...
[Gary] They are, they are. I've been on this
website, these guys love Tesla, Elon
Musk. [Chris] Is that really the reason
behind Tesla's, not, exposure
? [Gary] I mean, listen,
I'm not an expert exactly on Tesla stock.
[Chris] But it's a stock we talk about a lot
isn't it? [Gary] Yeah, I mean, it's very,
very expensive compared to other car
makers, and there is a huge... like, I go
on this, I've been on this,
you know, I trade markets and I look at
this website. They love Tesla, they love
Elon Musk. Oh, you know, not all of them,
but
if Elon Musk tweets something, that will
move... you know, [Chris] Yeah [Gary]
these guys, they love that guy. And
the fact is, you know, governments have
printed lots of money. That's how they've
dealt with this crisis,
and that means there's a lot of money
spilling about in the system, and largely
it's ended up with richer people here.
And if you give a lot of money to a lot
of rich people, they're gonna buy
stocks. And I think what's relevant to
the UK, they're gonna buy houses as
well.
And, you know, we're starting to see, in
the middle of the worst economic crisis
in our lifetimes, house prices are going
up at record pace. , so
I think... go ahead...
[Chris] Yeah, sorry, what do you think is
going to happen to GameStop themselves?
[Gary] I mean, the company... the hedge funds
which looked at this company, they
analysed it to be a weak company.
I mean, I tell you one thing, they've
definitely got a lot of free advertising
and publicity over the last few days,
which will
probably support the company. But if we
assume, and I think it is likely, that
this stock price will simply rise and
fall, that doesn't actually really
benefit the company themselves.
It's purely a game between people who
hold the stock, the short sellers, and
this army on Reddit, essentially.
You know, the company gets some free
advertising, but it was judged by many
hedge funds to be a weak stock. It's
trying to
compete with a massive giant like Amazon.
But realistically, presuming the stock
falls back down, it doesn't really change
the outlook for the company itself.
[Chris] Do you think we'll see a move away from
stock markets and how they work and how
massive, well, you know, part that they
play in their countries' economies,
or is this the model that is gonna be
around for a while?
[Gary] Well, I mean, already there's such a
divergence between countries' economies
and the stock market. I mean,
just look at what's happened since 2008.
You know, the UK stock market's up, I
think, two or three times in that time.
The US is up even more.
Stock markets just seem to go up and up,
and the reason for this is, and this is
another thing that these guys on Reddit
love to talk about, is
whenever there's a strong economy, stock
markets go up. But whenever there's a
weak economy,
central banks print billions of dollars
and that pushes stock markets up. So it
creates a situation where it feels like
stock markets can only go up,
whether it's a strong economy or a weak
economy. And what that means is, whether
workers and ordinary families do well or
badly,
the rich always do well.
So, if that's the situation, and if we
look at the last twelve years, that seems
to be the situation, you can kind of
understand why now ordinary people are
surging in to buy these stocks.
[Chris] Well, fascinating talking to you. I
think you've made some sense of all those
memes and various different videos I've
seen online, so thank you very much for
joining us here on LBC News.
That's Gary Stevenson, an ex-City trader
and an economist. This is LBC News, the
headlines are next.