[Gary] My name is Gary Stevenson, former trader and
people's economist. This is Gary's Economics.
Now today we're going to do something a little
bit different. Since I started doing this channel
I've spoken a lot about how I made a lot of
money in the City, and I've also spoken about
how I came from a poor background. We've had
a lot of messages from people who want to
know more about the background where I grew
up, if I really am from that kind of background.
So recently my parents told me that they're
selling their house and they're moving to south
coast somewhere, so I figured I would bring
you to the house I grew up in and show you
what my life was like growing up.
So here's the house I grew up in.
[Gary's mum] Hi Gary!
[Gary] Hey, how's it going? Go in, shall we?
[Gary] Okay so this is my old bedroom. It's pretty
different now. Like, growing up I used to
share this with my older brother, so
there was like a bunk bed in this corner
and I was in the bottom bunk here.
I could look outta this window.
Yeah, you can see it's not massive.
I used to keep all of my stuff in like
a couple of drawers that just went under
the bed. There was a computer here
my brother used to learn to program, which
someone from church gave us for free,
and he's a programmer now. But yeah,
I grew up here just sleeping under there.
You can see there's a railway track
just back here. There's a train going past.
I've spoken in a couple of my videos
about how my dad used to wake up
really early, like 5-5:30am, and he would
go down to Seven Kings station and
he would get the train into work every
morning and it would go past here.
And my mum would wake us up. We'd
look out and try and wave to my dad,
see if we could see him in a train,
like super early in the morning.
That's like one of my earliest memories
growing up. But yeah, this is my bedroom
it's where I grew up. I shared it with my brother.
And let's go down to the front room I think.
Okay so this is the front room.
This is the biggest room in the house,
the nicest room. You can see the
sun coming in from the windows.
Growing up it was me, both my
parents, and my brother and my sister,
so it was often pretty crowded in here.
But I had a little Mega Drive,
I'd play Sonic the Hedgehog down here.
Now, when I was 16 I was expelled
from school, and I remember at that time
I would wake up in the morning and
there would be no one in the house.
My parents would be at work and
my brother and my sister be at school. So
that was the time when I would spend
the most time, basically, in this room.
You know, we didn't like have a desk
really in the house to study, so we
used to get a little plank of wood
and I'd put it on the floor here
and I would lie down here and
I would do all my maths homework
and my French homework for GCSEs.
That's when I spent a lot of time in this
room, and obviously that time was like...
having been expelled from school,
I was like very... it meant a lot to me
that I did well in them exams, so I spent
a lot of time lying down on this floor
studying, and I did well.
What did I get? 8 A*s and 3 As.
Study hard for your exams, guys.
Yeah, that's the front room, and I think
we just show the bathroom and
the garden quickly. Yeah, we'll do that.
[Gary] Okay so this is the bathroom. I wanted
to show the bathroom because I've got
a couple of memories of this bathroom
growing up. One thing I remember is
my first ever day interning at Citibank.
When I was 20 years old, I had to get
into the office at 7am. It was in December,
so that meant leaving here at 6am.
And I remember now, we got one of
these showers here. You get this like little
stick-on thing from Argos and you put it
on the taps and then you like
you use this little shower head.
You hold it, you sit in the bath.
I remember like waking up at like
5am and sitting in this like bathtub
which was very cold on a December
morning, and showering myself up before
getting the train into Canary Wharf
for my first day at Citibank.
And I also remember the day after
I got expelled, when I was 16,
waking up and my brother and sister
were at school. I think maybe my brother was
already working then and my parents
were at work. And yeah, waking up
the only person in the house and coming
down and sitting in this bathtub
with this handheld shower.
And showering and watching
the water go down the drain.
And just watching the water go down
and thinking, yeah, that's gonna
be your life if you don't do something
about it. So yeah, that's why I was
studying so much in that front room.
That's the bathroom. Yeah, so...
my mum says you've gotta go to the garden.
Yeah, so we'll go quickly to the garden.
Just watch your footing around here.
[Gary] So this is the garden. We do have a little bit of a
garden, even though, as I think you're about to see,
there are trains going past right here. This is
the main line in, out from Essex into London.
Yeah, my mum want to show the hydrangeas she's
been working at them hard. She's gonna lose them
soon when she moves out. But yeah, we didn't spend
much time here. The sun is on the other side.
But yeah, I could see out from
the bedroom into here.
Yeah, it wasn't too bad. We've got some trees out
here in this... That's basically it. One other thing,
what was I supposed to show you? Yeah, my little
clay painting I made when I was 12. Little clay
portrait of the house. So that's it. Yeah, so look it's
not a big house but it meant a lot to me.
Yeah, this is where I grew up. It was small,
it was crowded with five people, but it was...
it was where I lived. So yeah, that's it. We're
gonna show you a little bit outside the front I think yeah.
[Gary] So this is the outside of the house. I just
wanted to show a few things that have changed
basically since I was a kid. So we used to have
like a kind of abandoned factory here at the end
that we would climb over the gates and play in.
You can see now it's like a massive block of flats.
That really like overlooks the street. Yeah,
I've got nothing against that but I guess it's
a bit strange for me, like, just being here when it
didn't used to be there. Big great block of flats.
Yeah, I was talking to my mate the other day who
used to live down there, said he doesn't like coming
down anymore, just because it sort of
makes him feel strange to see like
this massive block of flats where we used to be
able to see the sky. I suppose there's another one
over there. Can you see the one there? That's new as
well. That used to be a swimming pool. We used to go
for, I think, like one pound as kids, go swimming
in the swimming pool. That's a block of flats too.
So there's no swimming pool now. I think
these guys are getting a loft conversion.
There's another block of flats over there which I
think is just out of shot, and beyond that there's
I think a 40-storey block of flats, which
is massive. There was nothing like that in
Ilford when I was a kid growing up. So yeah, my
dad was saying it's just filling the place up.
Yeah, I know people need houses, I'm not
complaining against it, but just saying...
Yeah, this place has changed since I was a kid.
A lot more flats, a lot more crowded, but still
it's a nice street, in a way. I enjoyed growing up here.
We're gonna show a few things on the street.
[Gary] So this street, like, it don't connect to no other streets,
so there's not a lot of traffic and the kids used
to play out on the road. My mum says they still
do. I used to know everyone. Aron, one of my
best friends, used to live here. Lee Jones lived
over there. He wasn't one of my best friends.
Andrew and John Parker lived here, they were
good guys. I used to go round their house to
play Mega Drive before I had the Mega Drive.
Not just that, they were my mates as well, obviously,
in case they're watching. And Bradley used to
live there, and there was another Bradley with his
brother Justin and their little brother Ricardo
used to live up there. Yeah, like, all the kids would be out
in the street all the time playing. And it's
a Wednesday today, so there's nobody playing,
but I guess on a sunny day like this they still do.
Let's take it to the end of the street where we used to hang out.
It's funny, like, when I was a kid the street
seemed like so long, you know what I mean?
This is where Anthony Silverstone used to
live. He was like my absolute idol growing up.
Very funny, very sporty guy. And then this
was Kelly, his next-door neighbour.
[Crew] I've got a question, where did Tyrone live?
[Gary] Tyrone was like in the middle. We ain't talking
about Tyrone, man. Tyrone was trouble.
Still is, probably. This was the Jattinder family,
don't know their surname. They come out and we
used to play football down here. So we're gonna
show... see, this new sign. I don't know if you
can see this "no ball game" sign. I don't know when
they added that, but you see down here at the end,
there's this telegraph pole and this lamp pole.
And obviously it's made for playing football.
We used to play football here all the time. These
houses weren't there, it was like a kind of, like a garden,
like, warehouse or something. Yeah, we used to
play football. It always used to go over into this
man's fence. They put this... this is new, this
fence. We used to kick the ball over all the time
and we had to go all the way around to climb over.
And I remember one kid came down from a couple
streets down and he just jumped straight
over that wall, like, kicked off it and jumped
over it when we was about 15 and we was like...
blew our minds. But yeah, we used to
play football down here all the time.
There's a "no ball game" sign here now, but I'm
guessing people probably still do play football.
We'll show you the bridge. Yeah, okay, so this is the
bridge. This goes over the railway and connects
my street to the rest of Ilford, which
is on the north side of this railway.
[Gary] So my primary school, my grammar school, my
comprehensive school, they're all on the other
side of this, so I started crossing this every
single day from when I was four or five years old.
I remember crossing it with my brother.
As you can see, it's a very long bridge.
To be honest, it was quite dangerous
growing up. My dad was saying
that even now he won't cross it in the night-time.
Anthony got beaten up one time on
this bridge and had to go to hospital. I remember
one time two guys tried to mug me just here.
I remember just listing to them all the names
of the people that I knew, hoping that we knew
someone, because I live literally just here.
Eventually they decided not to mug me. So I guess we did...
But yeah, I crossed this and back every day, and
it was dangerous and it was scary, but
if anything happened I just used to run away.
So that's how it is. I had a bright future, I'm
not losing it to fight someone on this bridge.
But yeah, this iron bridge, so well known in Ilford.
[Gary] This is where I come from. If you come from a place
like this, and, you know, it doesn't have to be in
London, it could be in Manchester or Birmingham
or Newcastle, or, you know, Northern Ireland, Wales,
it could be in another country, right. If you come
from a place like this, you're not going to hear
many voices like yours or like mine talking about
economics. What you are gonna hear is voices
paid for by billionaires, telling you you shouldn't
tax billionaires. Now look, I don't get paid to do
this. YouTube doesn't pay me to do this.
The reason I do this is because I worked in the
City, and my job was to analyse the economy. And the
result of my analysis was: if we don't do anything,
people like me and the people here, and from
places like here, are gonna struggle, and
their kids' lives will be even harder than their
lives, and their lives will get worse over time.
That's what will happen if we don't do anything
about wealth inequality. But the newspapers, which
are very often owned by billionaires, and the
politicians, who often are billionaires themselves,
are not gonna say that. But I'm gonna
say that, because I want to make things better.
So look, there's a voice here that is representing
your interests in economics. And if you want to
make things better for ordinary people, then
it's important that voice gets heard. So check
out my website, check out my videos, share this
voice, and let's let people know that the way
things go with the economy might be good for
the billionaires and millionaires who talk on TV,
but it's not good for ordinary people. Let's spread a
different message about how we can make the
world better for ordinary people, like the people that
live here and the people who live where you live.
And we're gonna start that by talking
about the tax system, in our next video,
about what's happened to changes in the tax
system, raising national insurance payments,
which is ordinary tax on people like you, while the
billionaires don't have to pay anything. So yeah,
check out my next video on tax
and share this video. Thank you.
[Gary] Is that good? [Crew] Yeah, perfect.
[Gary's mum] Hi! I don't know if you can see the
likeness, he's short like me.
[Gary] You can't... we can't put that in can we!
[Gary's mum] I'll do that again.
[Gary] No, that's probably worked fine, to be honest.
[Gary's mum] Yeah. I'm your mother. I've been around a
bit longer than he has. That's kind of important,
isn't it? I'm really proud of you, Gary.
[Gary] That's nice, we'll put that bit instead of the short bit.
[Gary] Okay, thanks. [Gary's mum] No, put the short bit in as well!
[Gary] OK, it's enough, right? It's enough. Okay, good work.