The richest in our society are making
billions off of COVID-19.
That is gonna keep our economy in a
crisis for decades. I know,
because I made millions as a trader in
the City, betting the same thing would
happen after the 2008 crash.
So my name is Gary Stevenson. In 2011, I
was Citibank's most profitable trader
globally, and I made that money by
betting that
after 2008 crisis, there would be no
powerful economic recovery,
because economists don't understand the
importance of inequality.
Alright, so there's been a lot of talk
in the news about how poorer people have
been most affected by coronavirus.
But what I think has not been understood
is how much money richer people have
made.
Now, this can be easily understood if you
understand the flows of money in society.
So normally, richer people spend a lot of
money.
Now, that's important because it drives
wages and it drives jobs for ordinary
workers.
They need that money because ordinary
workers have to pay rent, bills,
mortgages, and that money flows back up
to the owners of properties and the
owners of mortgages, who are the rich. So
in normal times, the money flows in a circle.
Rich people spend a lot, ordinary people
have to pay their rent, their mortgages,
their bills.
Now, when COVID happened, suddenly rich
people massively cut their spending,
quite simply because a lot of things they
like to spend on — holidays, hospitality
— they couldn't spend anymore.
Now, that causes a big problem in this
circle. Suddenly money is not flowing
around,
it's just flowing in one way. And if that
keeps happening,
very quickly ordinary people run outta
money and they can't pay their bills and
they can't pay their rent, they can't pay
their mortgages.
So obviously government had to do
something. They came in with furlough
schemes and other support schemes to
support people who had lost their
jobs.
The problem is they didn't take
money from the same place it was coming
before. Rather than taxing the rich
to help struggling workers, they simply
printed the money at the Bank of England.
What that means is money's still not
flowing around in a circle, now it's
flowing in a line.
The Bank of England prints new money,
they lend it to the government, building
up the government debt.
They give it to ordinary workers,
ordinary workers give it to richer
people when they pay their bills,
and richer people are just keeping the
money. It's going from the Bank of
England and the government to the very
rich.
The amount of money that has been
printed is enormous. It's £450 billion,
which is more than £6,000 for every man,
woman and child in the country.
There's been talk about more austerity,
more taxes on ordinary people.
Now, if that happens, that's gonna increase
inequality even further. But what I wanna
talk about is that massive
increase of money that has been built up
in the bank accounts of richer people.
What is gonna happen with that money?
Now listen, I've been poor and I've been
rich.
I know how ordinary people spend their
money and I know how rich people spend
their money.
Now, richer people, if you give them a
massive amount of money, they're gonna
use that to buy stocks, they're gonna
use that to buy property,
and that's gonna push up the price of
those things. That means that right now,
just as millions of ordinary people are
losing their jobs, richer people are
gonna get a massive income from
increase in the prices of the properties
and the stocks that they own.
It's important to understand how this is
gonna affect ordinary families.
You know, back in 2008 we made the same
mistake. We tried to fix an economic
crisis by pouring money into the economy,
and it all ended up with richer people.
What happened after that? Stock prices
trebled, quadrupled.
House prices in London doubled. What's it
gonna mean for ordinary families if
house prices double again?
It's gonna mean that for millions of
families in this country, they will never
ever be able to own property, no matter
how hard they work, no matter what job
they get.
It is gonna end social mobility in
this country. It is gonna end the
ability of ordinary families to access
housing.
I was working in Canary Wharf in 2008.
I saw the economists and the traders
predict who'd get a massive, rapid
recovery because of all the money getting
poured in,
but it didn't happen. That recovery was
only for the owners of stocks, the owners
of property.
For ordinary people, there was no
recovery, because the inequality was
never dealt with.
If we do the same thing now again, we
will have 20, 30 years of economic
weakness for ordinary people.
This problem is not gonna fix itself.
Inequality will only get worse and worse.
It will grow like a cancer in our
economy. Listen,
I don't wanna live in a country where
ordinary people
can't have access to good quality
housing, to financial security.
I don't wanna live in a country where,
if you're born poor, you will live your
whole life poor and you will die poor,
and there's nothing you can do about it.
We've got a tax system in this country
which is very good at taxing ordinary
workers.
If you work, you're gonna pay your
income tax. But the richest people in
this country
often get their income through different
forms — trusts, inheritances, capital
gains.
These are all taxed in different methods
and are very easy to legally avoid.
Under that current tax system, it is
inevitable that the very richest will
get richer and richer,
house prices will get less and less
affordable, ordinary people get squeezed,
and the economy will never recover.
I don't wanna stand in front of you
and make pessimistic predictions, but
I've been betting on this for ten years
and I've been right for ten years.
If we don't fix inequality, we're not
gonna have an economic recovery.
We need to reform the tax system so that
it doesn't just tax the income of
working people,
but also taxes the wealth of the super-
rich.
I grew up here in East London. I came
from a poor family and I went to work
down there in Canary Wharf.
I know how difficult it is for kids from
ordinary families to make something of
themselves,
to get property, to get financial
security, and I know how important it is
to people from families like that. And
that's gonna get more difficult now,
if we don't deal with the extra
inequality we're getting from COVID-19.
But it's also an opportunity. The
inequality is becoming more obvious to
everyone,
that unfairness. This is a chance for us
to come together and challenge the
system,
and make sure that the very richest in
society actually contribute,
instead of getting richer every time
there's a crisis.
We need to reform the tax system. We need
to make things fairer.
If we don't do that, the future is gonna
be bleak.