[Ian] And also this story, this one does divide
the room somewhat. A one-off wealth tax
will be the best way to patch up
UK public finances, battered by the
coronavirus crisis. This is according to
the Wealth
Tax Commission. They said the government
should look at a tax on millionaire
couples,
rather than increasing income tax or VAT.
Taxing those households
an extra one percent above a one million
pound threshold
would raise £260 billion over five years.
Let's speak to Gary Stevenson,
himself a millionaire, former trader,
wants the wealthy to pay for COVID. Now,
an inequality...
is that right, an inequality economist?
[Gary] Yes, that's right, yeah.
[Ian] Afternoon, Gary. The only reason I
paused at that — I thought you were
championing inequality for a second.
That would be a curious job to have,
wouldn't it? But you're an economist
looking at issues of inequality,
and I said at the beginning of this,
Gary, or just before the news, this one
divides me somewhat, and I'm sure
lots of people feel the same, because I
can see how persuasive and seductive the
argument is.
You know, if somebody is worth a few
quid, it's a one-off tax, then, you know,
why not?
It's not going to be forever. You could
argue it's in their interest as well,
long-term.
But there's another part of it: I think,
well, if you always go cap in hand to
rich people, you could play that game
every day of the week that there's any
kind of crisis.
[Gary] Yeah, that's the concern. It's
addressed in the report. A lot of the...
some economists at the London School of
Economics and a group of lawyers and tax
accountants have looked at this.
Yeah, they've addressed that in the
report. I think the thing we need to
consider here is there's a massive
increase, as everybody knows, in
government debt due to the covid crisis.
It's coming up to half a trillion pounds
just from this year. Something has to be
done about that. It will have to be
addressed.
At the moment, the very richest in our
society often pay the lowest rates of
tax. You know, it's famous, some
billionaires pay less than their
cleaners...
[Ian] As a rate, yes.
[Gary] Yes, as a rate, yeah. Someone's gonna
have to deal with this, and if it's not
the very richest, who often pay very
little,
then it might have to be hard-working
people like you and I.
[Ian] I mean, in terms of tax
thresholds... I mean, you will know a bit
about this, Gary, you've done well in the
City and you've earned a few quid, and
that's fabulous.
What happens in terms of taxation once
you... what is the top rate of tax you
can pay at that level?
[Gary] Well, I think the top rate of income
tax at the moment is 45%.
[Ian] So that doesn't change between having,
you know, £150,000 or £50,000 to having
two billion.
[Gary] No, well when I was working, there
was temporarily a 50% rate tax.
[Ian] That's right.
[Gary] But I think at the moment, the top
rate is back down to 45%.
[Ian] So it's still 45%, there's nothing
above that.
[Gary] Yeah, but what's important to realise
is that tax gets charged on worked
income. But the very richest people, they
make a lot of their income,
often most of their income in the case of
the richest, in ways that is not through
working. For example, trusts,
inheritances, capital gains.
And these methods of income are taxed
often a lot less, and some of these guys
will be paying less than 20% tax
and they may even be making billions in
income.
[Ian] Yeah.
[Gary] So there comes a question where
you have to ask, why are people who are
earning £50,000, £60,000 a year paying
45%, when the Duke of Westminster's
making nine billion pounds and not paying
anything?
[Ian] Yeah, and in terms of your own situation,
I mean, you've done well, I don't think
you're making nine billion quid, Gary.
But nonetheless, you would be prepared to
pay more?
[Gary] I'll tell you what. At the moment, in
this country we've got a Chancellor whose
father-in-law is a multi-billionaire, and
his wife is estimated to be worth about
half a billion pounds.
If Rishi Sunak pays, I'll pay.
[Ian] But then Rishi Sunak might say, "Well,
okay, that's all very well, but he
shouldn't be judged on his spouse and her
family."
[Gary] Alright, if Rishi Sunak's wife pays.
[Ian] He's a self-made man. Yeah, okay, if
Mrs Sunak pays, pays the big bundle, then
you will as well?
[Ian] How would you... I mean, would you
just have a one-off payment? Do you think
that would work? Or do you think there
should be
an increase in the basic rates of income
tax? Because the smart money always says,
Gary, as you know,
that if you up it to 50%, and I believe
there is evidence for this when Gordon
Brown had his sort of five minutes at the
50% rate,
this is just income tax, that the intake
was actually... the overall tax intake was
slightly less, because people just found
ways to avoid it.
[Gary] You know, I really want to try and
be clear about drawing the line here.
There's a difference here between...
what these guys are doing in this report
is they're talking about taxing wealth.
So it's maybe families that have... they
might have accumulated wealth over
possibly centuries, you know,
£50 million, £100 million. It's about
taxing families that are accumulating
huge amounts of wealth, and their wealth
is just getting bigger and bigger.
They often don't pay income tax because
they don't get their income through
working, like you do, or like I did when
I was working.
So we're not talking about taxing lawyers
and doctors here. We're talking about
taxing extremely wealthy families who are
accumulating wealth over generations
and often don't get their income through
work. So it's not really about what level
of income tax; it's about, do we get the
super, super rich to pay at all? Because
often, right now, they're not paying at
all.
[Ian] So it's a kind of misnomer really,
the idea that
we talk about income tax and we kind of
obsess on that, but actually the real big
bunce comes from elsewhere.
It comes from those funds, those pots,
those investments, it's those kind of
areas.
[Gary] Yeah, it's a choice, in a way, because,
you know, there's a massive debt here,
it's increasingly huge, somebody has to
pay it.
And in a sense, the government has to
choose: do we go to the super-rich, like
for example the Chancellor's wife,
or do we go to people who are working?
[Ian] Yeah.
[Gary] And at the moment, I've worked, and I've
paid a lot of tax.
But a lot of these guys who are a lot
richer than me, many, many, many times
richer than me, and I presume you as
well,
are not paying anything. And it's not
fair, and it's damaging to the economy,
because if you squeeze the middle class,
then there's no spending. You know,
Rishi Sunak's wife is not going to keep
the whole economy alive. We need to tax
the rich as well.
[Ian] Do you think the government response
to that might... apart from ideologically
they would say it's not the right thing
to do, and we can argue that forever,
but do you think the government might
say, "Well, we'd need to set up such a
complicated system in order to find where
all of those
funds and investments lurk," that it would
become impossible?
[Gary] Yeah, I mean, when you consider, as
we've said, that the Chancellor's
father-in-law is a multi-billionaire, the
government might say something like that.
But the work that the economists and the
various people on this panel have done
today is basically saying, "Look, we've
done the work, we've shown you how you
can do it,
we've shown you how it can work." And
there are other economists that
have done similar work, like Gabriel
Zucman.
You know, the economists are putting the
work in to show how you can do it. We
need the government to come on board
and say, "Look, we are committed to
making sure the richest pay as well." And
the economists will work with them. I'll
work with them for free.
Look, if they want to call me up, I'll
work with them, I'll tell them how to do
it.
But we need to know they're on side, and
in theory they're on board with making
sure the super-rich, like Rishi Sunak's
family, like Jacob Rees-Mogg, actually
pay their way,
and it's not just put on the hard-working
people of this country.
[Ian] Good work, Gary, thank you. Gary
Stevenson, former trader, himself a
millionaire, would happily pay more money
if other people were doing it. But is it
down to the rich to fill that void?