I can say for me, I come from an ordinary,
to be honest, quite a poor background,
really.
And when I was a kid, I just wanted to
make money. It's hard being poor, you get
judged for being poor, you know.
I didn't wanna be poor no more, I
wanted to make some money, and, you know,
I thought I was smart and I could do it.
So I went into the City. But the truth
is, because of the kind of background I
come from,
I didn't... what I thought was a lot of
money was not what they was making in the
City.
They was making a lot more money in the
City, you know what I mean.
And I remember, like, my first bonus day,
like, what I was expecting, and for me in
my head, that was like, "Wow."
And then when I went into the room, the
boss man, he was a big guy, I remember he
had this little piece of paper on the
table.
I looked at it and I was like, "Is it
that number?" And he was like, "Yes, that
number."
And I remember I literally said, "Wow,
that's a big number."
Not because... for me, like, the first
thing that that made me... that come to
my head was my dad, basically.
You know my dad worked for the Post
Office for, I think, 35 years. And when I
was a young kid,
he used to start work really early in the
morning. I remember he used to leave home
at like 5:30 or something and my mum
used to wake us up, and the train used to
run right past my bedroom,
and then my dad would look out the window
and we would try and see my dad on the
way in, you know.
And he was up, like, before, you know,
early, before the sun come up, every day,
going in. And he never made a lot of
money, you know.
And we was never, we never really had
that much. But he was up every day, 5am,
5am, going in, going in.
And it's funny, like, I was there in the
room and I should have been super happy,
but the first thing I thought of was my
dad, every day, up 5am, you know what I
mean, going into work.
And then thinking, I was, I think I was
22, and I was making, like, maybe more
than ten times what my dad made in one
year.
And it was just... it was just a madness.
It was a madness.
I went back to my desk and I was just,
like, in shock. And the guy next to me,
these guys thought it was funny. They
thought I was funny, like me coming in
like sort of like a street kid, they
thought it was funny.
The guy next to me was like, "Just go
take a moment, take a moment." And
listen, of course, like, I'm super
grateful. I know what it's like to not
have money. I'm super grateful that I've
got money now and I'm secure.
But it's difficult, like, to be, like,
fully happy when you've grown up and
you've seen how hard some people are
working to make so little, and to
struggle.
And you know that as a 22-year-old, you
can walk into the City and make ten times
that. So yeah, I'm conflicted, because on
the one hand, look, it's mad important
to, like,
I know that there's people from worlds
where that's not a lot of money, because
I've seen both sides of the coin, you
know.
So I know that there's people making that
money, and I think kids from my sort of
background have every right to make what
they're, what those guys are making,
and to get financial security and to get
property. But at the same time, when
people like my dad and my friends' dads
are working so hard and getting so
little,
it's hard not to feel that there's
unfairness there.
Anyone getting involved in that world of
online trading, online foreign exchange
trading, forex betting,
that is a dangerous world, a very, very
dangerous world.
You know, I do some of this online, and I
don't mean that as an endorsement, but
you know, people get dragged into using
trading strategies, they're sitting there
every day, buy buy buy, sell sell sell.
The truth is, the vast majority of people
that do that, they lose money. Basically,
it's gambling. Basically, it is gambling.
It's not really that different to you
going in and doing the slot machines, or
just betting on the sports.
But because it's foreign exchange
trading, people sort of think it's
investing. But the truth is, if you don't
know what you're doing,
if you don't have a really solid handle,
that is gambling. Gambling can ruin lives,
it can ruin families.
So anyone out there doing that, please be
careful. Don't gamble more than you can
afford to lose. Make sure you know what
you're doing. Don't be fooled into
thinking you're a big-shot trader if
you're not.
But at the same time, look, I fully
understand it. I know how difficult it is
to make money from working. I know how
difficult it is to make money from
working.
And then, at the same time, like I say,
I've been, I've studied at Oxford, you
know.
And I see people born into money that
have millions you know, and then I see
people working that can't get anything.
And then people see people like me going
to the City, essentially gambling and
making a lot of money you know. Like,
realistically, we live in a world now
where the only way
to get rich is to be born rich or to
gamble, you know. So people are at home
and they want to gamble. But the truth
is, it's dangerous, it's dangerous.
You can lose, you can lose a lot of
money, and for a lot of people, that's
money that they can't afford to lose. So
I understand it, but the truth is, for
most people who don't have
some sort of advantage, some sort of
special knowledge, it's gambling, it's
dangerous. Be careful.
So I think you need to understand exactly
how I made money in the City, alright?
My job... I started working in 2008, that
was when the big crash happened, alright?
My job was essentially to predict, when
will there be a recovery?
Okay, and in 2008, everyone, all the
economists, thought it would happen next
year, 2009. But that didn't happen,
alright. 2009, everybody said next year,
2010.
That didn't happen, right? In 2010,
everyone was like, "Okay, well, it'll
take one more year, 2011." Alright.
That was mind-blowing to me, right? I
studied at London School of Economics. We
thought everybody understood what was
happening.
Then I went to work in the City with a
bunch of millionaires who get paid six-
figure salaries, sometimes more, to
understand what's gonna happen,
and they're wrong every year. For me,
that was amazing, but also it was
opportunity, because if these guys, the
best paid guys,
if they don't know what's happening, then
it's me, I can do it, I'm as good as
anyone else, right? If I can figure out
why there's no recovery, then I can make,
I can be a millionaire, basically.
So I was obsessed with this idea: why is
there no recovery? Why is there no
recovery?
And I came to the conclusion that all
this money that was getting poured into
the economy, it wasn't going to ordinary
people, it was going to rich people.
Now, unlike most people in that world, I
could see that there's a difference
between what ordinary people do and what
rich people do.
Ordinary people spend their money, rich
people save it. If you give millions to
the richest, all you're going to do is
push up asset prices,
stock prices, house prices. You're not
gonna make the economy recover. Now, if
that's what's happening, then that means
there will be no economic recovery.
When I realised that, it was like a penny
dropping. I went back to the desk, I put
a massive bet on: there will never be an
economic recovery.
By the end of that year, 2011, when I was
24, I was the most profitable trader at
Citibank in the world,
by betting that there would never be an
economic recovery, alright?
You know, and that worked, that's worked
every year since, right? But can you
imagine, like, what kind of
situation that puts me in? One, you are
one of the best traders going, you're
making loads of money, and it's because
you're betting there will never be an
economic recovery.
And then at the end of the year, I get
paid a lot of money, and it's just like,
"Well done, do it again."
But I mean, how many times can you get
paid a load of money for betting the
world's gonna be terrible forever, before
you start thinking,
maybe I've got some sort of obligation
to at least try and tell people that this
economic problem is serious and forever
and not getting better?
You know, I've said it enough times, I
come from an ordinary background. People
like my parents, like my friends, that
the kids I grew up with,
they are the guys that are getting hurt
here. And the future generations are not
gonna have a chance
if we don't do something about this. And
look, I'm not pretending to be an angel.
I'm not Mahatma Gandhi. I made my money.
But I made my money by betting on, and
understanding, that the economy will be
weak forever.
You know, if you knew that your next-door
neighbour's house was gonna burn down,
you've gotta tell them, right?
Well, that is what I'm seeing. This is an
economy that is gonna burn down if we
don't do anything.
And I could sit in one of these
skyscrapers in Canary Wharf and make a
million pounds a year.
But then, you know, the economy will
still burn down. And what am I gonna tell
my kids? I'm gonna say, "Well, I made my
money betting the economy would burn
down."
"Did you tell anyone? Did you try and do
anything about it?" You know what I mean?
Like, listen, I made my money, you know,
I'm not an angel. But at the same time, I
care about this country and the people of
this country and the world,
and what happens to the economy. And if I
made money betting that the economy is
going to break, I feel I at least have an
obligation to try and tell people,
"Listen, this economy is gonna break.
It's breaking. I understand how. I
understand how to fix it."
If nobody listens, then maybe I'll go
back. But I've gotta try.