[Nick Robinson] It's 8:27. Now, millionaires have a critical
role to play in healing our world. Who
said so? Well, a group of millionaires.
You've written a letter
calling on politicians to acknowledge
that tax increases on the wealthy
are, in their words, essential. One of
those who signed is Gary Stevenson,
a former interest rate trader, and he
joins us on the line. Morning to you.
[Gary] Good morning, Nick. [Nick Robinson] It's an unusual
message, this: "I'm rich,
tax me." [Gary] Yes, it is an unusual message, but
I guess this is a pretty
unusual time, and I think it's gonna
be very important.
[Nick Robinson] How would you want governments to tackle
the wealthy?
[Gary] Well, for me, I think one of the most
important things when we deal with
tackling the wealthy
is that we develop a tax system that is
able to tax wealth and not just income.
So we currently have a tax system which
is relatively good at taxing people who
work for their money and earn a lot of
money, such as
footballers, and sometimes bankers, if
they're not trying to dodge it.
But people who have very large amounts
of money and
accumulate their income through things
like capital gains or trusts,
we're very bad at taxing them. That
means we end up with a system
where people who work and people who
earn money
have to pay a lot of tax, whereas
the very richest in our society often
end up paying
nothing, or next to nothing.
[Nick Robinson] So, is this a
question of a wealth tax, as against
just higher rates of income tax, or is it
about finding a way to stop
money being moved from one country to
another, and
always avoiding the tax authorities of
that particular country?
[Gary] To be honest, I think those two questions
have to be considered hand in hand,
because there's no point bringing in a
wealth tax which has
loopholes in it, because if you put
loopholes in your tax system,
then the people who will exploit those
loopholes will be the people with the
best tax accountants,
and those are generally the very richest.
And, you know, our tax system
is littered with loopholes. I remember
when they brought in the second home
stamp duty, an extra 3% for
second home buyers.
Perfectly reasonable tax. There was an
exemption for people who bought seven or
more at once.
I mean, that tells you the tax system we
have now, and the people who pay and the
people who don't.
[Nick Robinson] Now, many of the names you saw in this
letter are relatively well known. Richard
Curtis, for example, the
film director. Christina Johansen, the
philanthropist.
You're not so well known, but clearly
made a lot of money very young,
trading in the City. And having read some
of what you've written,
it feels as if when you watched the
traders around you,
you were rather revolted at the business
that had made you so rich.
[Gary] Well, some of them might be listening here,
so I'll probably be careful what I say.
The truth is, I had a lot of
disagreements culturally with
some people when I worked in the City.
There are some elements of that industry
which can be a little bit unseemly at
times. And definitely
some people who... I won't name names,
but actually,
you know, I learned a lot working in the
City, and some parts of it I really
enjoyed.
The job analysing the economy was
fantastically interesting, and there were
some
really intelligent and interesting
people, and some people who were really,
really good to me when I was there. So I
don't wanna tar all bankers with the
same brush. I think, as you'll find in
every walk of life, you'll find good and
bad people.
But yeah, there were definitely parts of
that industry which
left a bitter taste in my mouth.
[Nick Robinson] Gary
Stevenson, thank you very much for
joining us.