Okay. Welcome back to Gary's Economics.
Today we are going to talk about how to make money.
So this is one of the questions...
Well not just one of the questions, the question,
by a million miles
which I get asked most on the channel.
And I also get asked this question a lot in real life.
So I wanted to address it.
And I got asked this question twice recently in person.
I went to
a friend of mine's 50th birthday party,
and his nephew was there,
and we were standing outside this pub
and he said to me, oh,
you know, you're that guy, I watch your channel.
You know, what do I do?
What do I do?
How do I get rich?
And, I had another friend of mine,
a Japanese guy, come out to my house.
We were cooking dinner,
and he said, I want to ask you, like,
you know, you've got a lot of money.
Can you tell me how to get rich? And,
it's a tricky one, right?
Because I was thinking when this second guy asked me,
if you came to me and said, you know,
how do I get hench?
I would say, go to the gym every day.
If he said to me, you know,
how do I get my English better?
I would say, you know, speak English every day.
If you say, how do I learn Japanese?
I'll show you what textbooks to buy.
but the truth of the matter is what I said to this guy.
He said, can I ask you one question?
I said, yeah, go on. He said, how do I get rich?
I said to him, ask another question,
because the truth is,
this is the one thing
which is almost impossible to safely do
as a young person nowadays.
There's there's basically one really,
really good method for getting rich in today's society.
It’s almost foolproof. Have a rich Dad.
If you failed that one,
try again.
Because,
okay, so obviously people ask me this question
because I'm a rich person.
I've been very open about that.
I talk about this on the channel.
I made my money working as a trader.
I was a very good trader.
I was a very successful trader.
I wasn't a professional trader for a long time.
I worked as a trader from 2008 to 2014.
I made a lot of money,
especially in 2011,
but also a couple of years around that.
If you can get a job as a professional trader,
it's an extremely well-paid job
and you will become a relatively rich person.
Basically, nobody,
not from a rich background, becomes a trader nowadays.
It's almost impossible to get that job.
And I got that job
partially because I was a very good student,
you know, I was a very talented maths student.
I got very good grades.
I got into a very good university,
and I got very good grades at that university.
But even on top of that,
I needed to win like a national card game
to get that job.
And I think that shows you...
this story’s in my book, if you want,
you can read my book, it tells you about this.
It's almost impossible for ordinary people to get that
job nowadays. So
unless you are like a kind of like a extremely,
unbelievably talented mathematician,
in which case, you know,
go and study maths or economics
at Oxford, Cambridge, LSE,
and try and get a job as a trader.
This is just not a route that is open to you.
You know, the trading floor has almost
nobody from a poor, ordinary background,
almost everybody is from a rich background.
So if you come to me from an ordinary background,
say, how do I get rich?
I can't really say to you, do what I did
because it's almost impossible for you to do that.
So then you might say, okay, well,
you know, maybe I can't get a job as a trader, but,
you know, you still trade personally.
And I do still trade personally.
And I've got a very good track record
trading personally.
I have made quite a lot of money trading personally
since I quit trading.
so you might say, well, teach me how to trade.
So for this,
I've mentioned this a couple of times
before on the channel.
I have a couple of times tried to help
friends get involved in trading.
And this happened
particularly at the beginning of Covid.
So I sort of started doing my public work
at the beginning of Covid in 2020.
And one of the big things that I said
when I came out publicly was that
house prices would go up a lot because of Covid,
because rich people accumulated a lot of money
during Covid.
You can go and look at my early videos,
how the rich get rich from Covid 19.
I talk about exactly this.
And some of my friends who were trying to buy
houses, had maybe 50, 60 grand saved up,
came to me saying, listen, I'm worried.
You said house prices would go up.
I don't have a big enough deposit yet.
I can't buy a house. What can I do?
And at that time, at the beginning of Covid,
I was making some really big bets.
In particular,
I had a really big bet that the gold
price would go up, and,
I thought the gold price would go up.
It has come up a lot.
I thought house prices would go up.
They have come up a lot.
And actually like quite a good way
to hedge your exposure to rising house prices
is to buy other assets like gold.
So I said to my friends, okay, well,
you can't buy a house yet,
but what you can do is you can buy gold.
I had a massive trade on that
the gold price would go up,
so I felt quite comfortable recommending to them
to do the same thing that I was doing.
And yeah, it was a good trade recommendation.
Gold price went up. A lot has gone up a lot since.
And the gold price went up about 20%
not long after that recommendation.
And then it came down sort of 5%.
And sort of
when this happened, about nine months later,
both of my friends called me up
and they said, you know, what do we do?
They call me up individually, you know, what do I do?
And I said, well, you know,
it's gone up 20% is down 5%.
So you’re still up a lot of money,
like just don't do anything, just sit.
Wait.
You know,
if you want, you can buy a little bit more on this dip.
and they both said, you know, you don't understand.
Like I'm out. I'm wiped out. I've lost all my money.
And I was confused, how could you have lost money?
It’s up 15% since I told you to buy.
And they both did basically the same thing,
which was they didn't do anything when I said buy it,
because at the time it looked terrible
because the price is really low.
It went up 5% and they thought,
oh damn, I should have bought it.
It went up another 5%.
And they thought, oh man, I really should have bought.
I'm going to buy now.
So straight away they missed the first 10%
goes up another 5% and they make a little bit
more on it.
The okay great I made some money.
They buy a little bit more,
goes up another 5%
and then they both just basically went totally insane
and didn't say anything to me.
They bought a ton more gold.
They bought silver, they bought platinum,
they bought palladium, they bought Bitcoin.
They're buying Tesla.
Not telling me any of this stuff basically
because they’d made a little bit of money
trading on my recommendation.
They basically became sort of convinced
that they themselves are really good traders. And they
did a load of stuff, which I didn't tell them to do.
And they bought loads basically
and then it came down and they lost a ton of money.
So this is why I don't try and teach people
to trade, basically.
You know,
the few times I've given friends
trading recommendations,
most of the time they manage to lose a ton of money
because trading hard.
And you know, I make money as a trader.
And every now and again
I do say my positions on the channel,
but I was a professional trader for six years,
and I've been looking at the economy for 20 years.
And, you know,
I have an extremely good track record
as a professional trader,
an extremely good track record
as a as a personal trader.
I don't think this is
a thing which I can teach you to do,
you know what I mean, you know.
It's a bit like going and asking Usain Bolt,
how can I win the Olympics?
You know, like maybe train for 20 years?
I just don't think it's,
I don't think it would be responsible.
I think it'd be super dangerous.
I know that trading has become
super popular for young men on the internet.
And you see them on Instagram
showing off their Lamborghinis.
I've come out and,
you know, very aggressively said,
I think crypto trading is dangerous
and day trading is dangerous
and FX trading is dangerous.
And for that reason, I get, you know,
young men emailing me all the time
telling me they've lost all their money
FX trading, crypto trading,
and a lot of the time when they send me those emails,
they say, but don't worry, I figured it out now
and for me, I'm going to make money.
And, it's difficult to read those emails.
Listen, trading is gambling.
Trading is gambling.
If you go on...
I trade on IG index,
which is a spread betting platform.
It says there on the front page,
like 75% of accounts lose money. I'm not losing money.
And there's professionals on there like me
that are not losing money.
And there's an old saying,
if you don't know who the idiot is
at the poker table, you’re the idiot.
Listen, professional traders like me,
if you go out, you're trading against me, you know.
And it's dangerous.
It's a dangerous thing for ordinary people to do.
I think we've created this situation
now where we have basically convinced
young people, especially young men, that
the only way to be of
value in society is to make a lot of money
and we've created a situation
where all of the legitimate paths
to getting rich are basically blocked,
and it's almost impossible to become rich nowadays.
Realistically,
for the younger generation,
if you're working, you've already lost.
Basically, it's almost impossible
to get rich through your work.
The only way to get rich nowadays
is to inherit money from your parents.
But often these inheritances are invisible.
So I went to a grammar school
but I also went to a comprehensive school,
and I've got friends from different kinds
of financial backgrounds.
People from poorer families,
it's basically impossible to buy property.
People from richer families, what happens is
the parents will gift them
£100,000, £200,000, maybe £500,000 to buy property.
People from poorer backgrounds
don't realise that that's happened behind the scenes.
So they see other people
from different families buying properties, and they...
people don't tend to go and say, you know,
the reason I bought a property
is because my mum gave me £500,000,
but that is what is happening.
Then people from poorer backgrounds
see these guys buying property
and they think, what are they doing
that I'm doing wrong?
And the thing that you're doing wrong
if you're poor is you had the wrong parents.
You shouldn't have done that.
You should have had the right parents.
This is the world that we live in nowadays.
We live in a world
in which the only way to get rich
is to have rich parents.
And yet we tell young people,
if you are poor, you are a failure. You are a loser.
It is your fault.
And this is just absolutely devastating
for the mental health of young people.
So what I want to say is, listen,
you live in a rigged game.
You and I live in a rigged game.
It is almost impossible to get rich
if your parents are not rich.
So what I want you to do is to accept that.
The game is rigged,
and to stop judging yourself
and other people based on financial outcomes
when financial outcomes are increasingly nothing to do
with how smart you are,
how hard you work, what job you do.
You know this is the world that we live in.
But I think
what obfuscates this a little bit
is the fact that there is social mobility
on like the micro scale.
So like the people who come
from the same financial background as you,
if you work harder than them and get a better job,
you will be able to get slightly better off than them.
But you will never be able to jump up
to the level of somebody whose parents are richer.
So that's what it is. So at the same time,
you know, especially if you're poor,
you do have to work really hard
and you do have to try and study the right subjects.
You do have to try and get the right job,
because increasingly
people are put in this situation where otherwise
you'll become homeless and completely impoverished.
So you have this kind of small scale
competitiveness. But there's no macro competitiveness.
So you're forced to compete
with other people who are poor,
but you have no way of competing
with people who are born richer.
And it's a horrible game. It's a horrible game.
It's a horrible game. So I think we need to.
You need to understand that
this is the world that you've been put in.
They want you to fight each other to be rich, but
it's impossible to be rich,
because the rich are taking everything.
So while you are sort of being convinced
to fight each other and obsess
about being a failure and obsess about making money,
the game is being rigged such that you and the middle
classes are basically being robbed blind,
and the government is being robbed blind.
And
my concerns are one devastating
for the mental health of young people.
But two, it's like really,
really deeply depoliticising.
I think if you can convince
ordinary young people
to focus only on their specific bank balances
whilst the game is rigged,
so that it's very easy for the rich to rob the poor,
then the poor will never unite
and stop that theft basically. So,
this is the world we're living in
and this is the thing
which I worry about a lot at the moment,
which is how do we stop the systemised
robbing of the poor
when the poor have been really trained
to play the game, very individualistic
and to not work together?
And I think, if I want to send one message, it is that
the game is set up in a way that
you are being robbed of your wealth,
and there's very little
you could do as an individual to stop that.
But no matter how much they rob you of your wealth,
they can't rob you of your dignity and
it's not your fault
that you live
in increasingly in poverty,
the game is being set up
such that the majority of this country
increasingly will live in poverty.
But you can realise that
that's not fair on you, as an individual
that is the result of a rotten system,
is the result of a rotten system. And,
I think people can deal with poverty.
And I know poverty is not easy, but, you know,
I grew up in poverty and it was hard.
But what affected me
in many ways, more than the poverty was,
was the judgment. So,
don't judge yourself harshly and don't judge
other people harshly because it's a system
that's broken.
You should be proud of the work that you do,
and you should be proud
of what you do to support yourself
and to support your family
and support the people around you.
Because I think once we managed to shake off
this judgment and this idea that it's our fault,
then we can start
being proud of ourselves and each other
and seeing the game for what it really is,
which is a broken game that we have to fix together.
So
there's only two ways to be rich
in this world that we live in.
Be born rich or change the rules.
and we can only change the rules together.
So I'm going to try to change the rules.
Tax the rich more, tax you less,
move us back into an economy
where ordinary people
like my parents, like your parents,
can achieve financial security
and even wealth by hard work.
But the only way to do that
is to work together to change the system.
So how do you get rich?
You get rich by working together.
I'm going to try and do that, and I hope you join me.
Good luck. Thank you.