Okay.
Welcome back to Garys Economics.
This week
I want to do something a little bit different,
which is to talk about
a discussion
which has been causing a lot of disagreements
here in Garys Economics offices, which is,
largely this kitchen and a WhatsApp group.
Recently we got contacted
by the Labour Party, basically,
which is the first time
we've ever been contacted by the Labour Party.
And, they said,
you know, we've been seeing
what you've been doing on the channel
and we would like to send some MPs
onto the channel to talk to you about,
presumably the economy.
And my initial instinct
when that happens was that
we have to let them on basically,
that was a kind of a,
I think, a moral like a, like an ethical response
because we criticise the government a lot.
Labour have been in government
for coming up to a year now.
We've criticised them a lot, before them
we criticised the Conservatives a lot.
But I felt that since we are criticising
these guys
a lot on the channel,
we kind of have kind of an obligation
to let them come on and defend themselves.
They are literally the party of government
in this country.
I think I might even have said on the channel,
you know, if you want to come on,
we'll have you on,
so I felt like we kind of
have to have them on, really, from a moral perspective.
So I chucked it out there to the team,
we have like a very small team now
we have Jack, here the videographer,
and we have Oscar, who's the channel manager.
And I said, these guys want to come on the channel,
I think we have to have them on.
And we had a little chat about it.
And basically, Oscar thinks we shouldn't have them on.
I think Jack probably thinks we shouldn't
have them either.
So I wanted to basically talk about
what's going on in my head,
what's going on in our discussions
about whether we should have them on.
And basically,
I wanted to put it to you guys,
the viewers, to basically let you guys
have your say about
whether you think we should have them on.
And I wanted to engage you guys in the thought process.
Yeah and just
encourage you to put in the comments what you think.
So I'm going to kind of go through the pros
and the cons as I see them.
So firstly
the pros, I think it's kind of the right thing to do,
to have them on
because as I say, we've been criticising them
and they're the party of government
and we kind of
should give them like a right
to reply to defend themselves.
Other pros,
look, I'll be clear about what I'm doing here.
You know, this is obviously a YouTube channel,
but those of you who've been watching for a long time,
you will probably be aware that,
you know, I'm not just doing this
YouTube channel to make videos.
I want to achieve political change here.
You know, I want to achieve a fairer tax system
which taxes
the very rich more and taxes ordinary working
people less.
I want to stop increasing inequality.
I want to try to stop falling living standards.
You know, and everything, the writing of the book,
it's all about trying to achieve political change.
And i’ll be very clear, like plan A for me,
and I think I've said this on the channel before,
is to try to influence the Labour Party
running up into the next election.
I think that they will fail on the economy.
I think that living standards will continue to decline.
I think that Labour and Keir
Starmer will become increasingly unpopular
because of that,
and I think they will be forced to,
if not replace Keir Starmer, at the very least
do a significant rebrand on economic policy.
And I think they will be forced
to consider a new direction
to consider, at the very least,
a new style of messaging.
But I think they will be forced to listen to new ideas.
And, I think that
if we can keep growing the channel at the kind of pace
we have been growing the channel,
I think that we
can be big enough
and can be powerful enough that we maybe can influence
that changing
economic direction for the party,
which will probably come in two years
time, three years time leading into the election.
That might sound crazy,
but the growth of the channel
is so quick at the moment,
and the growth in support is so quick,
I actually think that that is achievable.
But that obviously means
building some form of connection
with Labour and some form of influence in Labour.
I'll be clear about that.
I'm not trying to sort of
covertly become a member of the Labour Party.
My priority,
my plan is to make this channel so big
that they basically have to talk to us,
whether they like us or not.
I call this the Rupert Murdoch plan.
So Rupert Murdoch,
for those who don't know who he is, is
one of the richest men in the world.
He's an Australian media businessman.
He owns loads of newspapers.
And really,
he kind of indirectly controls
politics in a lot of countries, including the UK,
because he has so much influence
over the public through his newspapers
and his TV channels
that unless prime ministers get his support,
they basically can't win elections.
And I think I'm not wrong in saying,
wasn't he godson to Tony Blair's kid?
I think he...
double check me on that.
But,
you know,
I think one of the reasons Tony Blair was so successful
politically is because he got Rupert
Murdoch's support, basically.
And I think Rupert Murdoch is a great example
of how you don't need to be an MP or even prime
minister directly to completely control
politics, basically.
He is, he was? Yeah, yeah so I'm not wrong on this.
-Tony Blair Godfather to Rupert Murdock’s daughter.
Okay.
Tony Blair Godfather to Rupert Murdock’s daughter.
Okay, so they were close basically.
I think Rupert Murdoch shows you that
if you have a big enough media presence,
you can basically boss the political parties around.
And that's my plan A, basically.
The growth on this channel
is unbelievably quick at the moment.
I don't know whether we'll be able
to keep up that level of speed,
but to be honest, you know,
we're going to try to get some big media hits.
You know,
Diary of a CEO, Question Time, The Rest Is Politics.
Maybe we can keep growing at this pace.
And if we do
yeah then Labour will have to listen to us.
But either way if I don't want to set up
a political party myself,
which, trust me, I don't,
I think our best chance of influencing policy is
via the Labour Party. So,
obviously having them on is
a way to try to develop some sort of relationship.
Which I guess brings us onto the negatives,
because one of the obvious negatives is,
I am very, very critical of Labour
Party policy at the moment.
I think it will fail economically.
And if somebody comes on, I will say that.
And, you know, I'm not going to have them on
and be a soft touch, like I'm going to try to...
I'm going to tell them
that I think their policy will fail,
and I'm going to try to...
if they,
if they're unwilling to listen to that,
then I'll probably have to go for them
quite aggressively.
And there is a risk that we perhaps
sour the relationship with the Labour Party,
which might be problematic down the line. I don't know.
I want to be clear, I keep saying that,
I don't have a background in politics.
My background is in economics,
and I'm not a professional lobbyer.
I really don't know how this works.
My plan for a long time
has been to build
popularity with the public,
and it's only really
now the channel is growing
that I'm even starting to think about, okay,
how are we going to be able to leverage
this into political power down the line?
But yeah, that's one of the risks.
Number one is, you know,
we might potentially sour relations
with the Labour Party,
which might possibly influence
our ability to influence them,
affect our ability to implement them down the line,
which could be a problem.
To be honest,
I think if we get this channel big enough,
I don't think that'll be a problem,
because I think if we're big enough,
they have to listen.
But, you know,
maybe it is,
maybe you guys know more than me
about the Labour Party,
I'm not an expert, I'm not a member.
The second thing is,
it risks people
questioning the political neutrality of me
and the channel.
So I come into this as an economist.
I consider what I'm doing
kind of a single issue campaign.
We need to stop wealth inequality increasing,
that's how we stop poverty from exploding.
I honestly don't consider myself
to be particularly politically factional.
I voted for a number of different political parties
over the course of my life.
But obviously,
if we let the Labour Party
on, there might be people that say,
“Oh, Gary's let the Labour Party on, he's
a Labour Party stooge.
He's on the left.” I think we have to accept we live in
increasingly, extremely
factional times with regard
to politics,
where people who feel that
they're on the right often
hate people who are on the left,
people who feel that they're on the left,
often hate people who are on the right.
And
I
I want to appeal to people
in both camps on either camp.
I honestly believe that
we're not politically factional,
and I want to be able
to remain believably politically non factional.
And that might be a risk if we have Labour on.
I would be bringing Labour on
because they are literally the party in government and
I criticise them a lot.
And I would have had the Conservatives
on when they were in government and,
you know,
I'd be open to having the Conservatives on
now if we had Labour on, but that's a risk
we might be seen as nonpolitical, factional,
we might be seen as, yeah, not politically neutral.
Then after that,
if we have Labour on in order to,
you know, defend and justify
that we are politically neutral, which I think that
we are,
we might need to have
the Conservatives on, we might need to have Reform on.
And some people might say
we should even have the Liberal Democrats on,
and we should even have the Greens on,
and we should the SNP on.
And then it starts to become a situation
where we are giving up
a significant amount of our time
to basically other people when, primarily this is a...
I want this channel to be
an educational channel, an informative channel.
I work hard to put out
informative educational videos
every week that help ordinary people understand
what is happening.
And we only do one video a week.
It takes up a lot of my time.
It takes up a lot of my energy.
It takes up a lot of our resources.
We don't really want to start
giving up a huge amount of basically this space
we've created to a bunch of politicians
who we don't really trust or even really
like necessarily.
So that's the second question.
Is it going to sort of
start us on a slippery slope
of having to give a lot of our time and space,
which we've worked hard to create, to people
that we don't really like,
people that we don't support.
And I don't mean that just Reform
and Conservatives, I include Labour in that,
because there are a lot of people in Labour
that maybe I'm not a massive fan of.
And then the next problem, potential problem
after this is quite simply
that it might just be really boring, it’s
I think a very real risks.
So, I mentioned message
discipline in my video last week.
One of the reasons why MPs are often quite boring
when they go on TV
is because they get told what to say by the party.
That's the way that it works,
party tells them what to say,
they don't have a huge amount of freedom.
And there's a very real risk
that we allow someone on the channel,
he sits here with me at the kitchen table.
He or she obviously, could be a woman.
And it's just really, really boring.
And it's just talking,
just speaking the talking points
they've been told to say.
They're not really thinking about the economy,
they're not really listening.
And it could just be really rubbish
TV, could just be really rubbish video.
That is a risk.
And I take pride in putting out good,
interesting videos on the channel.
People have their opinions on
whether they're good or interesting,
I think we produce good content.
And I've always believed that
it's really important to produce
good, interesting content,
and that is a risk
when we bring them on that it’s just boring,
boring content.
And then
to, you know,
then we're forced to bring on Reform and Conservatives,
and we just get a string of boring videos
and we become Garys Economics, political...
boring political broadcasts,
which is obviously not what we want to be.
And the next risk is just,
you know,
I am obviously not a professional interviewer.
I'm an economist.
We've done interviews on the channel, we've only had...
we've only ever had three guests
on the channel, Matt Zarb-Cousin,
Stephanie Brobbey, and Jimmy the Giant,
all three people that I really like,
I really respect, I really respect their work.
But even so, you know,
people sometimes criticise
those videos and say, “Oh, Gary,
you're not a good interviewer.
You need to give the guest on to speak.”
And I think they're probably right.
I'm not a professional interviewer. It's not my job.
I would have to sort of sit
and think quite long and hard about,
you know, what do I would ask these people?
How do I want to run it?
How are we going to manage it if they're boring
and they don't say anything?
So it's just a lot of stuff for me to think about.
You know,
if I go too soft on them, people might say, “Oh, Gary,
you secretly support Labour.”
If I go too hard on them, people might say, “Oh, Gary,
you hate Labour.
You're on the right.” We might sour our abilities to
influence them down the line.
So yeah, that's basically it really.
We're throwing around a lot of ideas.
I think if I was thinking
purely explicitly about
like what is best for the YouTube channel,
probably I wouldn't have them on.
I think we, I think we've got a cool channel here.
I think we make great videos.
I think we make
we make fun, exciting,
accessible, educational, informative videos.
People like it.
We're growing really quickly, we're popular.
Everybody hates Labour,
I think they’re going to do quite a bad job.
Their brand is weak.
It's kind of toxic.
It's like, purely
from a growing the channel perspective,
it seems like an unnecessary risk.
But at the same time,
I think
and I'm kind of a lone voice in this in our team,
I think it's the right thing to do.
We attack them, we criticise them.
I think it’s the right thing to do.
These guys are literally
the government of this country.
Even if we don't have other parties on.
I think we have a
kind of a duty
to let them come on and defend themselves.
But no decision has been made.
I'm crazy, crazy busy,
and I haven't had a real chance to sit
and think it through.
So I thought we’d
try something different,
which is to just discuss here on camera
in front of you guys
what we're thinking,
what I'm thinking, and ask
you guys for your opinions, basically.
So, what do you think?
Should we have them on? What are the risks?
If we have them on, does that mean
we have to have on the Conservatives,
and Reform, the Liberal Democrats? What do you think?
Or is it a waste of our time
and we should just keep making the videos?
Of course, you know,
I can go back to these guys and say, hey, look,
I want to talk to you.
And I can sort of ask for, look,
if you want to come on the channel,
I need you to come and talk to me about...
are you going to give me what I want?
Are you going to be open to things like
wealth taxes, like a fairer tax system,
like raising tax on wealth and lowering tax on work?
So, you know, that is another option.
We can turn around and say,
“Yeah, we'll have you on the channel,
if you give us what we want, which is,
you know, a little bit more access to your policymakers
telling us how you make your policy.”
Lots of options here.
I have no background in political lobbying.
I'm not really comfortable in this space.
I'm an economist at the end of the day, so be nice.
No decisions have been made,
but let us know what you think.
Yeah, put it in the comments.
We'll be watching, we'll be reading.
And that's all.
Well, I should say
the reason that we're
getting these kind of approaches from Labour
is because the channel is growing
unbelievably quickly, and that is
thanks to you, the viewers.
So I'd like to thank everyone
who watches the channel, shares
the channel, everybody who has bought the book
shared, the book.
The book at the time I'm speaking, the book’s
been five weeks at number one.
This is one of the reasons why we get these approaches.
Yeah, this is something that shows we are
getting a bit of political power,
and if we keep growing, we could get more,
but we haven't yet decided what the best way
is to play it, to approach it.
So let us know your opinions, put them in the comments.
Thanks for your support and keep watching. Thank you.