Okay. Welcome back to Gary's Economics.
Today, we are going to talk about
the changing shape of Great Britain.
I've come down to Waterlooville
because I’m helping my Mum and Dad out with an eye tes,
but bloody hell.
Like, this is definitely not what it was.
I grew up around here.
I used to sit on that cannon as a kid,
and I think a lot these shops, like,
I remember I used to come and get my Pepe
jeans from one of these shops. But look at it.
There's bloody nothing here.
It's crazy.
I want to talk about this.
This phenomenon of the death of the smaller town.
I've been thinking about this for a long time,
so a couple of years ago
in the winter, I went to Colombia for two months
because I wanted to practice my Spanish
and because I hate winter.
So Colombia is a massive country, is about,
I think it's like five or six times bigger than the UK.
It might even be more.
And the population is a lot less than the UK,
just over half the UK. So
it's a big, low population density country.
It's a much poorer country than the UK.
So I was expecting it to be quite rural, right?
There's a lot of space, there's a lot of farmland.
There's not that many people.
I thought it would be like spread out,
you know, it’s a poorer country,
so there might be people, like, working in agriculture.
But I got there,
I flew into Bogotá
and straightaway Bogotá is like a massive city.
Bogotá is like, you know, it's almost as big as London,
it might even be as big as London.
And I was quite surprised, right,
because you have much fewer people in the country,
but they've got a massive city the size of London.
And then after that, I took a bus to Medellín,
which is the second biggest city.
And then again you have another city which is
almost as big as London.
So I was kind of like a little bit blown away by this,
like how can this country, massive country
with a relatively small population, have two cities
the size of London?
And it got me thinking about this quite a lot.
And the more I travelled in Latin America
and in other countries as well,
I started to realise that actually
this is quite commonly the shape
of like a relatively well developed
but very unequal country, which is that
you have a huge amount of farmland,
but it's largely industrialised
and not many people live in that farmland.
And all of the people then basically,
they have no jobs and they need jobs.
So they have to swarm basically
to where the rich people are
because the rich have all the money
and you end up with these sort of,
huge super cities
with a very, very wealthy centre and kind of large area
of essentially very low quality housing.
You could call it a slum around these these big cities.
And this is not unique to Colombia.
This is the situation
in most poorer,
most monarchical countries in the world. And
it basically got me
thinking about what the shape of a country is.
I think in capitalism, your country has to...
the physical shape of your country
has to reflect the wealth distribution of your country.
And if you look at Western European countries,
they have a different shape,
which is they have some big cities,
some smaller cities, and they have some towns,
they have some people living in rural settings.
It's much more diverse
than these extreme unequal countries
where increasingly the people live
in these slums around super cities.
And if you think about it, this makes sense, right?
Because if you have a relatively equal economy,
then every person in that economy is a small scale
wealth holder.
They are a worker and they're also a consumer.
And what that means is basically any
size settlement, is sustainable?
Because as long as you have a group of people there
you have
wealth holders, you have consumers,
and you have workers,
and everybody can work for each other
and everybody can consume each other's work.
So, you know, small cities are sustainable,
towns are sustainable, villages are sustainable
because everybody can work for each other.
But once you have a very unequal society,
then what you have is basically two kinds of people.
You have a very large group
of very poor people who need to work,
and you have a very small group of extremely wealthy
people who have an enormous amount of money to spend.
And what that means then is if you have
a group, a village,
which doesn't include any rich people,
you have a ton of workers and you have no employer,
you have no consumer.
So these small cities basically become,
they basically become non-viable, non sustainable.
And these cities have to essentially disband
and the people need to move towards
not even necessarily the big cities,
but wherever rich people exist.
And I think what we have in this country,
the UK and you also see in the US in places
like the Rust Belt and actually a lot of Europe,
I think what you have
is transitional countries
in the sense that we used to be a country
with a relatively large property owning middle class.
So these people lived in a variety
of different cities, big cities, small cities,
towns, and these places were sustaining.
But now we have moved
and we are continually moving into this more
Colombia type model.
You know, it's common across Latin America,
including the poor countries in Asia,
maybe some Eastern European countries.
We're moving to that very unequal model where
people need to live, where the rich people live.
So they need to move,
they need to move to these super cities.
And
you’re seeing that,
you're seeing the world basically split
into two kinds of places or places
where there are no rich people and places
where there are rich people.
And I think this is often described
by economists in a way
which I think is incorrect as an increasing...
such a classic economist way to describe a problem,
increasing preference towards large cities.
They say, well,
people just like large cities now, so
everybody's moving to large cities.
But I think this doesn't really
fit the model right,
because if you look at a place like
Newcastle, Newcastle is a large city,
Glasgow is a large city.
These are cities where there's
increasing economic deprivation and people are leaving.
Whereas if you look at a place like
Cambridge or Oxford,
these are small cities
and yet these are places
where people are moving to the cities
and where housing is extraordinarily expensive.
If you look at, for example,
the Swiss Alps or the Hamptons,
a popular holiday destination
in the states for wealthy people,
these are not big cities
and they're becoming very expensive.
So actually what you are seeing is people flooding
from the country to wherever rich people are.
And that is what you have to do
when countries become more unequal.
I think we are moving
from the physical shape of an equal country
to the physical shape of an unequal country.
And you also see that in big cities.
So I'm from London, I come from Ilford in East London.
And
this is a place
where people are swarming to this place.
And one of the most common
solutions that is put forward to the housing crisis is
you have to build more houses,
you have to build more houses.
And
I'm from Ilford and people from other,
sort of, more distant suburbs, poorer
suburbs of London
will be very aware that in these places
enormous amounts of housing is being built.
And if you go to the street I grew up on,
the density has increased enormously.
All of the houses have been expanded upwards,
all the houses have been expanded backwards.
There was a factory at the end of the street
which has been knocked down
and replaced with a massive block of flats.
And these
are providing extremely low quality housing
because these cities are increasingly full of extremely
poor people.
And I think
I'm not opposed to building more houses, but I think
unequal economies,
the shape of these countries
is basically enormous slums around the wealthy centers.
And that,
because our economy
is becoming a very unequal economy,
that is what our country wants
to become like from a capitalist perspective.
So if we build more houses
under this situation of high and growing inequality,
we will build that physical slum space.
If you go back to Ilford,
especially the part of Ilford I'm from,
that is what it's becoming.
So I think when I see this video,
what I see is a transitional country.
You know, we used to be a middle class country
and we are becoming a very highly unequal country.
And highly unequal countries
don't have cute little towns for ordinary people.
They have slums for ordinary people.
And if you go to,
you know, if you go to highly unequal countries,
like most of the countries in Latin America, you know,
you go to Mexico City, you'll see the same thing.
People are forced out of the countryside.
The countryside gets,
you know, industrialised from a farming perspective.
Some of it gets kept as playgrounds for the rich
and people swarm to the big cities and
I'm very skeptical that building
will solve the problem.
I lived in Tokyo for two years,
and that is a city with 38 million people
and very unaffordable housing.
I think poverty is the problem.
You know, if you don't get money
in ordinary people's pockets,
then everybody has to live close to the rich people
and there are fewer and fewer rich people
and those people are richer and richer. So
I think unless you fix the wealth distribution,
then this video of emptying out
small towns is the future of this country,
But not just this country,
but also America and also most of Europe.
And I don't want it to go that way.
And one solution is we build more housing in London
and we turn London into the super slum it's becoming.
And another solution is
we get money in people's pockets and allow people
to live where their families have lived in 100...
for hundreds of years
because they can afford to work for each other.
And that's the future
which I'd rather have for this country, for America
and for the rest of Europe. We can do it.
But we can only do it if we deal with inequality.
And the only way to deal with inequality
is to tax the rich.
So we're going to campaign for it, we’re here
every week. Thank you for your support.