Correct implementation on tax policy is a job of
experts and government and and civil service.
It is not the job of ******* YouTubers.
All right, so we'll do one on implementation
of wealth taxes and how to reduce inequality.
And the reason we have to do that is
because we are, like, increasingly doing
really, really, really well on narrative.
We are influencing what the media talk about.
We're influencing the debate on this.
Like, we have a massive presence in the debate now.
Governments are failing, especially the government
here in the UK is really, really unpopular and they
will have to do something or they will
lose really badly in the next election.
And increasingly we are looking like quite well-positioned
to be the way that they might have to turn.
So they might come to us and we
might, we might get something.
And what worries me is there is like a phenomenal
naivety at the moment in the way that people
are talking about wealth taxes, basically.
And basically that people seem to think that
the government can just turn around and say,
"Okay, let's do wealth taxes.
Let's tax the rich now and
things will be fixed." Right?
The truth is, and I've always said this,
I've never tried to hide this, actually
raising taxes on the rich is going to be really,
really hard for a variety of reasons, right?
One of the biggest reasons is obviously
they control a lot of the media narrative.
They can sell lot of scare stories.
"If you tax us, we'll leave." Or they
can do a lot of sort of personally
attacking of me as an individual.
But the truth is there are things they can
do and you need to deal with those things.
Like the truth is they can leave, right?
And I've always said, and I constantly believe,
you know, look at the Abramovich situation,
which shows like here's a rich man who tried to leave.
And we just said, "Okay, well you can leave, but if
you're going to own British assets, we can tax British
assets." And that's always been my comeback to that.
And that is true, but you need make sure
that you have your legal systems in place.
Like people sometimes ask me, you know,
"If you were Chancellor, what would you do?
If you were Prime Minister, what would you do?"
And I always turn around and say, "Listen, goddamn,
like, it's not that easy." The implementation
and the design... the correct implementation
and the correct design of this tax
or these taxes, it has to be so good.
It has be really, really good.
And there's... I think, a sensible government
at this point would be calling me...
Like the sensible thing do is to call me up and
say, "All right, look, we get it, right?
We see..." Like the argument I'm making is correct.
Inequality is increasing really, really quickly.
The rich are rapidly increasing their wealth.
It's squeezing everybody out.
It's destroying the middle class.
It's destroying the government.
It's having and will continue to have like
really destructive effects on living standards.
You need to fix it.
Like 100% you need to fix it.
The only way to really do that is to
aggressively increase taxes on the rich.
The truth is that's ******* hard to do.
So they should be calling me up and
saying, "Listen, okay, we see it.
You, you know, you're right.
We understand now.
Okay, you don't deal with
inequality, you're kind of ****ed.
But the rich are saying they're going to leave.
We don't really... We don't
think it's possible." You know what I mean?
So then you call me up and you say,
"Okay, all right, let's put the *******
work in." We put the ******* work in.
We design this tax so that it's ******* good.
So it's watertight.
You know, you look at things like what China
does. China doesn't allow you to own a
**** ton of Chinese wealth and live overseas.
You ask the question, you realistically discuss
the question, how much can the UK do by itself?
Or realistically, do we need international corporation?
International corporation is achievable.
If you look at when we last significantly reduced
inequality, it was in the aftermath of World
War II, and it was done internationally.
Everybody did it together and it worked.
The truth is, this would be difficult
for the UK, specifically the UK.
I think a massive country like the US
would probably have an easier time, especially
when you consider how many of the billionaires
and the massive companies are based in the US.
I think the US would have an
easier time to do it by itself.
I think a country like the UK could do some things
by themselves, but like why do it by yourself?
This problem is happening everywhere.
We have a mass opportunity to
build something internationally here.
But there's this like real childish naivety,
which is like, okay, fine, just give it like...
The big thing that you see, and this I
think really encapsulates the childish naivety
that I talk about, is people turn around me
and they say, "Okay, I'll show... all right.
Show me the tax policy then.
Show me the tax policy." You know,
listen, I'm here in my kitchen, right?
Which is real, like with a
massive ******* YouTube channel.
Like, I'm pretty much, pretty obviously
the world's biggest campaigner for wealth
taxes and I work ******* hard, right?
Do you think tax policies are
usually made by YouTubers?
Like, tax policy is not you give... We
spoke about this in the tariffs video, right?
Which is that the Trump tariffs had
this similar vibe, which is like some
random intern, like, bashed it together.
Oh, Cambodia.
Yeah, **** Cambodia.
You know what I mean?
Like, what is this idiocracy behavior?
Listen, if you want good tax policy, you need
to pay good ******* tax people and you need to
sit them in a room for a long ******* time and
you need to make sure they design that policy.
Even if I was the ******* smartest guy in the
world, you wouldn't want one ******* guy to design...
This is not *******... Do you remember that Little
Britain, write the theme tune, sing the theme tune?
It's like, you know, like,
alright, you, oh, you're the campaigner.
You ******* make it yourself then.
What have we become as a country. Like, listen,
if you want good tax policy, you need to pay proper
tax experts for their expertise and their time.
And you spend... Listen, you spend two years
designing the tax policy, obviously.
Obviously.
It's idiotic this approach.
Listen, I would be more than happy, more than
******* happy to be involved in making sure
this tax policy is designed well, obviously.
But the way that you do that is you get the tax
experts, you talk to me, you talk to the other
guys, you build a team of proper good tax experts.
You think about the question of how do we
deal with people who leave the country?
Can we still tax them on the UK assets like,
like we did to Abramovich, like China does?
You look at how these issues
were dealt with in the past.
You look at how wealth inequality was reduced
significantly in the 20th century. You
have sensible discussions, but I'm constantly faced
with these like idiotically simplistic discussions
which are totally bad faith, which is like, "Oh, okay.
You've recognised that the ship's going to sink.
Well, why don't you ******* fix the hole your
******* self then, you ******* idiot?" It's
unbelievably childish and it's unbelievably chaotic.
Like, listen, we're supposed to be
adult, grownup, mature countries here.
I have correctly identified a massive problem
in our economy that is going to devastate
living standards if nothing is done about it.
You need to fix that with well-designed tax policy and
well-designed tax policy takes experts and it takes
money and it takes resources and it takes hard work.
So and that is the message.
You know, that is the message.
So listen, we're winning the debate and
it's not just because of me, but that's because
I've been focused on winning the ******* debate.
Okay.
Implementation is going to be hard.
You know, and I emailed... Just this week I emailed
Gabriel Zucman, who is French economist who
I've got a lot of time and a lot of respect for,
he's working on similar things.
And I said to him, "Listen, dear Gabriel,
we're winning the debate here.
Who have we got working on
implementation?" You know what I mean?
Because listen, I can't do
******* everything by myself.
You know what I mean?
Correct implementation on tax policy is a job of
experts and government and civil service.
It is not the job of *******
YouTubers, you know what I mean?
And we need to win the debate and
we need to win implementation.
And, you know, I want to be clear, right?
I know I've campaigned for 2%
on wealth of above 10 million, you know.
That's what I do.
That's what Patriotic Millionaires do.
That would be good.
But like, this is not like I've sat
down and picked the perfect tax policy.
And people sometimes criticise me like,
"Oh, that form of wealth tax is not good.
We need another form of wealth tax." I'm here for that.
Let's have those discussions,
let's build a tax policy, you know?
But this kind of really stupid shutting
down of the debate is, "Oh, you've correctly
identified that our economy's going to be devastated.
Well, why don't you fix it?"
We need to grow up basically.
We need to grow up.
But, you know, the reason I'm here and I've
finally done a video on implementation is because
we're winning the debate and I'm really proud of,
of myself and so should you be, the work you've put
on it and so should everybody watching, because
this... What I think is really interesting
about like our, like, increasing narrative
victory here is people go on TV, so like when
like... It's Neil Kinnock is his name, right?
Is it Neil?
When he went on TV recently and he was like, "2%
wealth tax above 10 million." That is exactly
the wealth tax that I campaigned for, but
he didn't say Gary Stevenson wealth tax.
And he probably didn't hear it from me, right?
Like, and we don't have a massive
presence in the mainstream media.
Like, the way that we do this is we feed it into
the public and it comes up from the public to
the newspapers and to the politicians and, like,
it's... I think this is, I think
it's kind of inspiring to show how much power
the public has if they stick to a message, right?
And if they're very clear on it.
It shows that, like, you know,
a YouTuber, you know, it's not just me, you know.
I mentioned before, Patriotic Millionaires and
all these other guys who do their good work.
We can drive it up.
We can drive it up through the people.
But then, you know, if politicians
turn around and say, "Oh, okay, great.
Let's just..." You know.
We're not going to provide the policy, you know.
And we were speaking this week about, you know,
maybe we could try and get some funding to get
some tax le-... I'll be honest with you,
I'm ******* busy here, you know what I mean?
And it's stressful and I'm doing a lot of work and
I'm really focused on narrative and I think the
work that we do here is really, really, really vital.
So we were thinking about like getting some experts in
to fund tax... to actually work on implementation
and trying to get some money for that.
But the truth is, the honest
truth is, it shouldn't be our job.
It shouldn't be our job and I know like, you
know, I do lot of jobs that shouldn't be my job,
but, I would like to do a shout-out to like
governments, not just here in the UK, right?
Because this is an international problem.
Governments and, real governments that
want fix their ******* problems, you need to work...
you need to fund the policy on tax work on this.
Civil services across the country,
including this country, think tanks.
Listen, I'm working my tits off out here.
Get your best people working on how we do this.
And, you know, I would love to help and,
if the UK Government was to
call me, I'd definitely make time for it.
This is not ******* Gary Stevenson
saves the world, you know?
We need other people helping to design this.
I'm 100% aware and I've always been aware, effectively
implementing tax on the richest people will be hard.
I've never ever, ever said anything else and I know it
was hard and I knew from the start it would be hard.
And I, if I'm honest, I never thought
we'd get as far as we have already come.
But I don't do this because it's easy.
I do this because it's essential.
This is as simple as that.
It's as simple as that.
If you don't want your country to collapse
into poverty, you have to deal with this.
We've got the people, we've got the experts,
get them in a ******* room together, pay them
what they need and get that tax policy *******
sorted and give it the time it needs.
And I would like to see, you know,
this is not a UK specific problem.
I want to see politicians and economists
and civil servants in Germany, in Italy, in
Spain, in France, in Japan, in Australia.
I would say America, but we're not likely get them.
Oh, and Canada, because they always
complain that I don't mention them.
And New Zealand, get a lot of those.
Listen, what I'm looking for is like
ruthless practicality and pragmatism.
How do we effectively get wealth back
from the very rich, or at the very least
stop, them from taking more of our wealth?
Which has an understanding of the fact
that a lot of those rich are domestic,
but a lot of those rich are also overseas.
And how does... And they, they're
immobile, and how do we deal with that?
That is thing that can be dealt with.
It's been dealt with in the
past, it can be dealt with again.
And I will always say when people say it's
not possible, it was done in the 20th century.
It was done in the 20th century, inequality was reduced
massively and we should look at how they did that.
JACK: On international corporation,
there is a minimum corporation tax now that was...
Yeah, I mean, and that's Gabriel Zucman.
I'm pretty sure that's Gabriel
Zucman, and, and... You know, I'm
not the only guy out here, you know.
I'm very visible, I've chosen the YouTube
strategy, but, you know, I mentioned Rebecca
Gowland and Patriotic Millionaires, Gabriel Zucman,
Thomas Pierki, Aaron Advani, and there'll be
1,000 other guys across the world doing this work.
All of you boffins out there, tax experts,
economists, start building these policies.
Start building these policies.
Once we've won this debate and I stop
having to ******* argue it again and again,
I'll come out there and I'll help you
build the policy, but I can't do it myself.
Implementation will be hard, you have to do it.
I'll keep making the videos.
Let's get you boffins to start making the policies.
Listen, we got four years in this
country before the next election.
Labour, you've got four years, but it's going to
take... it's going to take two or three to get this right.
So, start moving.
Thank you very much.
Tax wealth not work.
Send it your friends, send it to your mum.
I'm done for the day.