Welcome back to Gary’s Economics.
Today we're going to talk about the tax burden.
So this is an economic story
which comes up a lot in the news,
which is the idea that at the moment
the tax burden is at an all time historic high.
Now, I'm pretty sure this is
a basically a factual truth.
And it's something that
when it first started to get mentioned, it
kind of confused me a little bit.
And I think it will have confused a lot of people.
The reason it confused me
is because we have two things happening simultaneously,
which kind of appear to be like
paradoxically impossible, which is, number one,
you have the tax burden at an all time high.
And that's true.
You guys will see that,
especially things like council tax
rising really significantly.
And at the same time, we have this situation
where basically all government services seem to be
collapsing simultaneously.
Everything seems to be constantly in crisis,
NHS is in crisis,
Education is in crisis,
especially things like local services are in crisis.
So how can it be possible that on the one hand
taxes are the highest they've ever been
and on the other hand,
government services are like the worst
they've ever been, or they've been in decades.
Taxes pay for government services,
so if taxes are super high,
how can government services be super terrible? And
the reason which is often
given for this
and I think it's really increased
the popularity of the idea,
is basically that government is corrupt.
Government is corrupt, so we’re paying loads of taxes.
Government p*sses the taxes up the wall.
You know,
let's get rid of taxes,
let's get rid of government services.
And I think,
you know, there probably some truth to this.
I think there's probably always
been some degree of government corruption.
Government corruption
may well be higher now than it has been historically.
If you look at some of the things that happened
during COVID,
some of the sort of Conservative Party
scandals, it does look like corruption is increasing.
But I'm not an expert
on the levels of government corruption.
I don't work in government.
But I've been sitting and
thinking about this for a while.
I don't think it's enough to say that
corruption has suddenly increased massively.
And
the more I thought about this,
the more I realised
there is another really obvious factor,
which basically never gets discussed,
which I want to explain to you today,
which explains really well basically why the tax burden
has increased
and probably will continue to increase
despite the fact that government services
are collapsing.
I think the best way to explain
this is to use an example.
Imagine you own completely your own house.
No mortgage, no rent, you own your own house.
Some of you will be in that position.
Most of you won't be in that position.
Now, imagine you are in that position.
How expensive will your life be?
Well, for most people,
their housing cost is their single
biggest expense in their life.
Be that through paying rent or paying mortgage,
if you own your own house outright,
you don't need to pay rent,
you don't need to pay mortgage.
And basically your costs in life are
very low compared to somebody else.
Now, let's imagine
situation changes and suddenly you lose that house,
you completely lose that house,
and now you still need to leave,
but you don't own your house.
Your costs will massively increase
because you have to pay rent for a whole house,
or you have to pay a mortgage on a whole house.
So if you own your house,
your expenditures in life are much lower
than if you don't own your own house.
Now, keep this example in mind
and we're going to start thinking about the government.
So I talk a lot on this channel
about increases in inequality of wealth
and what I say very often is
that there are two groups in society
who are losing their wealth.
That is ordinary working families
like you, unless you’re very rich and the government.
And both of these groups
have lost their wealth significantly.
Now, of course,
if you're an ordinary family,
especially if you're a young person
from from an ordinary family,
it would be very visible to you
that ordinary families are losing their wealth
because you'll be probably struggling to buy a home.
Or you may be in a situation
where you think you can never buy a home
compared to older generations, who could buy property.
But the loss of government
wealth is often a lot less visible because we don't,
you know, we are not the government,
we don't think about what the government owns.
So I went to a talk by famous French
inequality economist Thomas Piketty, of whom
I'm quite a big fan,
a few years ago
when I was at Oxford and he showed us a graph
which I still remember today,
and we're going to show you that graph now,
which basically shows you government wealth holding.
So on this graph
you can see what percentage of the wealth,
the assets in society are owned by the government.
And I think this graph goes back to around about 1970.
So what you can see in this graph
is that all of the countries in this graph,
the wealth holding of governments
has decreased significantly over time.
So that one line at the top is China.
You won't be surprised, the Chinese government
is essentially a communist country.
The government owns a lot of the wealth in the country.
The other countries on the graph
are all Western countries.
So you've got the USA on there, UK in there,
Germany, Japan, I think France is on there.
And the story of the rest of these countries
is basically all the same. They’ve all the...
the wealth holding of the government
has decreasing significantly over time.
And I want you to notice that in the case of both
the UK and the US, that number went below
0% in the early 2010s.
So the aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis.
So what that means is the total wealth
of the UK government,
the US government
and basically every other Western government
is in a pretty similar situation, is now below zero.
So that means these guys have debts
bigger than their assets.
Note that that graph ends in 2014.
The situation during COVID got significantly worse, so
now these graphs will drop down significantly
and what you will see is significant
negative wealth holding for the British government,
for the American government,
basically every Western government.
Now, I want you to remember the story
I told you about you and your house,
because Western governments,
including the British and American governments,
are basically in this situation.
Back sort of 50 years ago,
Western governments had a lot of wealth.
They essentially own their own house.
Now, of course, when we talk about governments,
it's not just housing.
We're talking about governments
owning things like hospitals, like schools.
But of course, in the case of the UK,
the UK government did own also a significant amount
of housing back in the seventies.
Governments have lost this wealth now.
So governments are in the same situation
basically as you would be if you lost your home.
So governments,
you know,
they provide, in the West
a lot of services, education, health care.
They used to provide housing
for the poorest people in the countries
and they were able to do this
because they owned the wealth, they owned hospitals,
they owned schools, they owned housing.
And what we learned from that Piketty graph
that I showed you
is that basically Western governments do not own
any wealth anymore.
And the fact that the number has dropped
below zero,
means that not only do they not own wealth,
they're actually in a significant amount of debt.
So what does that mean?
Governments still need to provide you with health care,
but they don't own the hospital.
Governments still need to provide you with education,
but they don't own the school.
Governments still need to provide
the poorest people in society with housing,
but they don't own the homes.
Now, things like health care and education
are never very cheap to provide anyway.
You need
to pay for doctors, you need to pay for teachers.
But they're a lot cheaper to
provide when you own the buildings.
If you don't own the building,
then you need to pay rent on the building.
If you have a massive amount of debt,
then you need to pay interest on that debt.
So now governments are in situations,
just as you are in,
previously they didn't need to pay that rent,
they didn't need to pay that debt interest,
and now they've got to pay it.
What that means is
if they want to provide you
with the same level of service
that they used to provide you
with 30, 40, 50 years ago,
they simply need more tax money
because they no longer own the assets
and they need to pay rent or interest on those assets.
So I think this is a really important thing
for you to understand,
and it really completely explains the situation
that we are in.
The reason that governments
are having to charge much higher levels of tax
to provide
much worse levels of service is quite simply
because governments are much, much poorer now.
Governments are really poor.
And when governments are rich,
they have what you could call in
modern lingo passive income,
you know, they own the property,
they don't need to pay for the property
and they can use those passive incomes
to provide you with government services.
Governments are no longer rich.
Governments are now very poor.
They need to rent everything they use,
they need to pay interest.
And that means they've taken that money from you.
And despite taking more money from you,
they can't provide services.
That is what happens when you go
from being rich to being poor.
Now, this wouldn't necessarily be a problem
if the assets which the government
has lost, the wealth which the government has lost,
were held by ordinary families.
So, you know, one thing I want you to realise
is this loss in government wealth,
you know, these assets, these hospitals, these schools,
they have not disappeared. They're all still here.
These assets must have gone to somebody.
And if those assets had gone to ordinary people,
it wouldn't necessarily be a problem.
I think the best example to illustrate
that is the council housing, right?
So when council housing was sold off in sort of
the ‘80s and the ’90s,
the people who benefited from that
initially were the people
who lived in the council houses. Council houses
were given to poorer people,
so it benefited the poor people.
Now the government didn't have the homes,
but the people who needed the housing
owned their own homes.
So it wasn't initially a problem
if it was just a transfer of wealth
from the government to the people,
then it wouldn't necessarily matter
because the people would be richer now.
They could pay more taxes or the government wouldn't
need to provide so many services
because you directly would own things
like your own homes.
The problem that we have is that actually in the last,
you know, 30, 40 year period
in which you have seen
governments have massively lost their wealth.
We have also seen a significant loss of wealth
in ordinary families.
And I think this is
something I talk about a lot on the channel,
but it is most visible in two things.
Number one, the massively decreased
home ownership rates for young people.
You know, here in this country
and in the US, ordinary families,
their wealth tends to be in housing.
So if younger people are not getting housing,
it's a sign that families are losing their wealth.
And number two, the massively increased debt levels
for ordinary families,
especially families who manage to get a mortgage.
So I think this creates a kind of
interesting and confusing paradox, right.
Which is
how can it be possible
that government has lost its wealth
and ordinary families who lost their wealth?
Now the government gave, for example,
the council housing to ordinary families.
Now you have a situation where
both ordinary families and governments
are struggling to get housing.
And I think this reveals
the core of the problem,
which is something I talk about a lot on this channel,
which is that wealth,
which transferred initially from the government
to ordinary families,
has over time ended up being held by the very rich.
And you know, this happens to...
If you want to understand the mechanism of this,
you should watch the video we put a couple of weeks
ago called How You Lose Your House,
which is ordinary people
got this wealth from the government.
They use that wealth to support their lives,
to support their retirements,
to pay for end of life care.
And they ended up selling that wealth to the rich.
The end situation is
we end up in a place where both the government
and ordinary families have very little wealth.
Now, this is.
it’s kind of a disastrous situation, right.
Because we've already learned
the government is struggling to provide basic services
now because government is poor.
What does it mean
if on top of that, ordinary families are poor?
Well, that means ordinary families
can't afford housing,
which means they really need housing.
But the government who used to have housing
doesn't have housing either,
so they can't provide you with housing.
It also means that
people are living lives of greater poverty.
They will live in worse conditions,
they will even worse housing.
They will eat worse diets, they will have more stress.
They will probably face more crime,
which means they'll need more health care.
But the government can't provide more health care
because the government has no assets. So I think this
really realises, makes real the problem
that I talk about on this channel.
So people who’ve watched for a long time will know
I'm very, very worried
about growing inequality of wealth.
And I think
people have become
used to the idea that inequality is a social problem.
They’re used to, kind
of, people on the left
arguing that we need less inequality
because it's unfair. It's not good for society.
My worry is deeper than that.
My worry
is that when you have very high levels of inequality,
what it means is
you can't get
basic essential needs like housing and health care
and education.
You know,
in our economy we have a distribution of resources.
If both governments
and ordinary families are losing their wealth,
that wealth is going to the super rich.
And we've seen a ton of statistics
which show us that the super rich have enormously
increased their wealth in the last three years,
we had the biggest ever one year rise of wealth
by superrich in the first year of COVID.
If we give all of the resources to the rich,
if we bankrupt both ordinary families
and the government,
the consequence is
your family can't get a house,
your family can't get health care,
your family can't get
education, and the government
won't be able to provide them
because they are also poor.
So I think once you recognise that that is the problem,
that governments have lost their wealth
and therefore they can't provide services,
the only option that they appear to feel
they have is to tax the middle class
who are also losing their assets.
You realise that
the fundamental question here
and the only real way to solve this problem
is to get the assets back, basically.
And that doesn't necessarily mean
increasing the size of government.
It could mean transferring assets back
from the very rich
to the middle class, to the working classes.
And the fundamental question is
how do you get those assets back?
And I think if you want to address that question,
how do you get the assets back?
It is very helpful to consider yourself
from the position of a wealthy person.
So consider you all like,
a rich person, but not a super rich person.
So say you've got a net worth of £5 million,
which is of course a lot, but
the very rich have much, much more than that.
If you have a net worth of £5
million, lets assume you’re able
to make 5% a year on that £5 million,
you might make a bit less.
5% of £5 million is £250,000 a year.
Lets assume you make a bit less. £200,000 a year.
This is passive income, you
get this on top of your work,
you don't do any work to get it.
You're making £200,000 a year.
How much money would you spend?
Imagine you suddenly had a passive income of £200,000
a year.
You know, the ordinary person
probably spends £20,000 to £30,000 a year.
I suspect you probably raised your spending
to £60,000 a year, maybe £70,000 a year,
which would massively improve your lifestyle.
And you still have another £130,000
a year passive income,
which you could use to buy more assets.
Now, in a strong economy
that is growing rapidly,
you might be able to use this money
to create more assets.
But we don't live in a strong economy
that's growing rapidly, we haven't for some time.
You're probably going to use this money to buy
existing assets,
probably from the middle class,
probably from the government.
But the big problem you have here,
you will never sell your assets, will you?
If you have £5 million in assets,
you've got £160,000
a year passive income,
which you use to grow your assets.
You will never, ever sell your assets.
So if we exist in an economy
which is not really growing,
the rich will never sell their assets.
Not only that, they will continue to buy more assets.
You can see that it is already
and will become increasingly impossible
for the government or for you as an ordinary family
to ever get any of your assets back.
So, you know, this is the situation we are in.
Government is taxing you a lot
to pay for sh*tty services
because government's bankrupt
and you can't afford to pay those taxes
because ordinary families are bankrupt
and all of that wealth is gone
to the rich who are going to use it
to buy the rest of the wealth,
making you even more bankrupt.
And this essentially is the reason why
what I always campaign
for is significantly higher taxes on the very rich,
because I don't see any other way of you
getting your assets back.
And I want to talk a little bit
about how this could work,
how we could make this society better.
I think the only way
you get wealth flowing in the other direction,
you tax very rich people much, much more.
You use that money
to significantly reduce taxes on working people.
Your taxes are less.
So you start to be able to accumulate a bit of money.
Rich people's taxes are much, much more
so they need to sell their assets
in order to pay for the taxes.
You've got more money.
The rich need to sell assets.
You ordinary working families
can start to buy those assets back from the rich.
So the reason I support higher taxation on the rich
is because, number one,
it's the only way to reduce your taxes.
And number two,
it's the only way for you, ordinary families,
to get your assets back.
The point I want to make here is, you know,
when I talk about taxes,
we're in an interesting place here in society where,
you know, understandably,
the middle class is getting quite heavily taxed,
largely because the rich pay very low taxes.
And if you haven't watched,
I would encourage you to watch our video
Who Pays Tax?
Because the very rich often pay
very, very low rates of tax.
And that has led to a situation where ordinary people
and particularly slightly
higher earning people, middle class
people are very opposed to tax.
And yet tax is essentially
the only way that they will ever get richer.
So ordinary people have been
put in a situation
where for very understandable reasons,
they oppose the only possible policy measure
which could save them from poverty.
And I think,
you know, this is supported by ideas
like tax is wasted, like tax is corrupt,
like tax goes to a corrupt government.
Taxing the rich can be used to lower your taxes
and that is the only way that you can get your assets
back from wealthy people.
If we don't tax them,
they will continue to never sell any assets
have enormous amounts of passive income
which they and their kids will use to outcompete
you and your kids for the assets
which you currently own
and in the end your family will own nothing.
So listen, tax for me is...
it's not about increasing the size of government.
It's not about more levels of government spending.
Tax for me is about defending ordinary families
from the growing power and wealth of the rich.
It's about getting wealth
back into the hands of ordinary people,
and it's about making life better,
or at the very least stopping life from getting worse.
So to conclude,
I would like to make the clear point that the only way
to reduce the tax burden
for you, for ordinary families like you,
is to increase taxes.
But to increase taxes on the rich.
We're going to campaign for it. We're here every week.
Tell your friends. Tell your mum. Thank you.