Okay, welcome back to Gary's Economics.
Today's video is going to be about mental health.
Okay, so when I decide to do these videos, I've
got a really long Google Doc which has a list of all
the subjects that I want to do a video about, and
I've had one on that list about mental health and the
relationship between mental health and the economy,
and economy and mental health for a long, long time.
And one of my friends is always
telling me I need to make that video, but
I've put it off for a long time.
Largely because, firstly, I don't like to
do videos on subjects that are not directly
related to the economy, and I like to try and
stay in my lane and be super economy-focused.
And secondly, because, it felt a little bit,
perhaps a bit personal, a bit indulgent.
Anyone who's read my book will know that I've
had problems with mental health in the past, and
perhaps I was a little bit unwilling to be one
of those typical guys on YouTube that starts talking
about his own mental health in his videos.
But I've decided to do it this week for a couple of reasons.
The first one is, the last few months
since I got back from being away,
I've been doing a lot of videos about
explaining why we need wealth taxes, how can you
convince your friends that we need wealth taxes.
And obviously, really, this whole channel is
me trying to persuade you and, me trying to
persuade the public that we need wealth taxes.
And the longer I've been doing that, especially
the last couple of weeks, where you put out
your arguments for wealth taxes and you see
people coming back with their arguments
why we shouldn't,
the more I start to feel that in a way
we're not really arguing about the economy at all.
I think we're putting out this
idea into the world, there's massive
economic problems, we need to fix things.
And, often what we get back I
think is kind of an emotional response.
And I think the emotional response we get back
when we send this message, "The economy is collapsing,"
is a pretty understandable emotional response, which
is that people are scared and people are worried, and
they don't want the situation to be what I'm saying
it is, which is that the situation is really bad.
It's getting worse.
The way to deal with it is to work together
to fight against the richest and most powerful
people in society, because that's scary.
And I think really, a lot of what I've been
doing the last few months, these few years, trying to
convince people we need wealth taxes in the economy,
a lot of the problem we are having is actually about
mental health and people who are scared
about what's happening in the economy.
And people who, because they are scared, are
looking for simple solutions and are
unwilling to engage with what we are saying.
So wanted talk bit about that.
I wanted to talk about my relationship with that,
because this is something that I went through
when I first realised these things were happening.
The second reason why I wanted to do it is because
I myself have been having a little bit of a difficult
time, especially the last, say, month or so, mental
health-wise, motivation-wise, and I thought that meant
it was a good time to talk about mental health, what
it means to the economy, what it means for this
channel, and what it means about how we fix things.
And thirdly, I've been re-reading one of my
favorite books recently, which is this book here.
Not being paid by Camus.
He's dead.
This is, The Plague by Albert Camus.
Camus is a French-Algerian author who wrote
this really beautiful book about what it means to live
in a collapsing society and what that,
what that does to us and our mental health.
So yeah, we're going to talk about mental health
today and how that affects the economy.
All right, so the first point I want to make, which
is that the crisis of mental health which we're
living in, in this country, in the US, across
the world, and the crisis of the economy are super
related in a way that should be really, really
obvious, but for some reason is often ignored.
So I went on Question Time this year,
I think it was maybe in March, and
the subject of mental health came up.
There's lots of statistics showing
that, especially for young people, like
mental health is really deteriorating.
Lots of people are stressed.
Lots of people are depressed.
And we were asked, the panel, you know, "Why do you
think people are stressed and depressed?" And,
one of the ladies on the panel said she thinks it's
because of mobile phones and social media.
And you know, perhaps that is a part to
play in it, but it was very frustrating for
me because we live here in a society where
it is increasingly impossible to do like simple things
like buy a house and have security for a family,
be able to get like a decent living environment.
To get that you need work all the hours God sends.
You need to get a really competitive degree, and
I think it should be really, really obvious that
a big part of the reason why people, especially
young people, are having mental health problems,
is because it's increasingly impossible just be
able to afford the basics of life for most people.
So I think we'll put up a little clip of me
trying to convince the people on Question Time
that mental health is, is not just because
of phones and it's not just because of individual
problems, but is related to societal problems.
I think we need to talk about the unbelievably
hostile circumstances young people face
with regards to their economic futures.
More and more and more young
people growing up in poverty.
But even aside from that, we've got
people with jobs in London who are homeless.
So that means if you're a young person, you
know that even if you get an ordinary job,
it's not going to be enough to buy a home.
It's not going to be enough to have a family.
So, so just doing the right thing,
working and getting job is, it doesn't
even guarantee you can feed your kids.
You know, we have to look at this and then
obviously, if you're a young person, you're
thinking, "Well, if I don't get the best grades
and I don't get into the best university, then
I'm not even going to be able to have a family."
You know, what kind of world have we made here?
You know, we need to look at it...
We always look at the individual.
This person has a mental health problem.
It doesn't come out of nowhere.
These people don't just suddenly get sick.
My dad worked for the post office and he had a
family and he bought a house and he has a retirement.
He has a pension.
Kids can't get that.
Unless they make millions of pounds,
they can't even have a family.
It's ridiculous, you know.
It's not just a problem for
individuals, it's a societal problem.
We need make sure young people have economic
opportunity. It's super, super, super
frustrating when people treat mental health
problems as if they're like a broken leg.
Like, you ****** up, you jumped
off a building, you broke your leg.
Now you have a problem.
These things are to do with society.
If you create a society where people have security,
where people can get good quality secure work, and
that secure work will be able to provide them with
the basics they need to support a family and to
support a family with dignity, then a lot of people
will be relatively happy and calm and relaxed.
If you create society like we live in now... I live
in a city where people work full-time jobs and are
homeless because they can't afford to pay rent, you
know, nevermind being able to do things like support
a family with dignity, get financial security.
People will feel insecure because
they genuinely are insecure.
And I think it's really, really important
that we start viewing mental health problems,
especially when they exist in societies where
the economic conditions are deteriorating
really quickly, as being related to the economy.
So, mental health and
the economy are not unrelated.
If you create an economy where people can live well,
a lot of people will feel secure because they are secure.
If you create an economy where it's very,
very difficult to get security, people will
feel insecure because they will be insecure.
And this relates very much to my own
personal story and, the story of my book.
So, some of you might not have read
my book so, or know my personal story.
So I made most of my money in 2011 by betting that
basically the... the economic crisis would last forever.
That was just after the 2008 crisis.
And what I bet on was that the economy and
living standards for ordinary people would get
worse and worse and worse and worse and worse.
And I bet on that again,
at the beginning of COVID 2020.
So I'm somebody who has been very aware for a
long time that living standards were going to fall.
And a big part of the story of my book,
especially the last section of my book,
is very explicitly about
depression and mental health.
And that was me sort of trying to deal with
this recent awareness that I had at
a very young age, in 2011 I was 24, that living
standards were going to get worse forever and
that, there would be big explosions in poverty in
my country, in your country, in the Western world.
And you'd get people who'd read the book
asking me, you know, "So, how did you make your
money?" "Oh, I made my money betting society would
collapse." And then they'd say, "But how did you fall
into depression when you made so much money?" And I
think it would be like super interesting really that,
that so many people sort of failed to recognise
that, knowing that the society you're in is
collapsing and is going to collapse would have
an effect on an individual's mental health.
The, the little quote at
the front of the book, I've got couple.
One of them is from the Japanese film director, Akira
Kurosawa, saying, "In mad world, only the mad are
sane." and this is basically about the...
What I wanted in this was to point out the fact
that the book is partially about me going mad, but
is it a mad thing to do, to go mad when you know
you're in a society that is about to collapse?
Yeah, that's really what I wanted to talk
about in this video because I think it's
super relevant to our work, trying to persuade
people they need to take action on inequality.
This question of what does it do to the individual when
they realise they are in a society that is collapsing?
The way that this crisis is often represented
in the media or from politicians is kind of as what
we call a recession, which means a couple of bad years.
One bad year, two bad years, maybe if you're
really unlucky, three bad years, and then
things will start getting better again.
But the reality is unless you're in the top 10%,
really this just gets worse and worse
and worse and worse and worse for you.
So, my plan was like, well, listen, this is like
really big political opportunity because the
political status quo works really, really badly
for like 90% of the population, and that means
we have a really good chance here to unite 90% of
the population to push for something different.
Like in a democracy, if you have a status quo,
which is going to impoverish the kids and grandkids
of 90% of the population, all you need to do is
show them the truth that this is going to happen,
and you'll be able to motivate them to demand
something different from their politicians.
And I think the problem with that plan
is really a problem of mental health.
And I'll explain why.
So this concept that what we were actually in
economically was a structural crisis of growing
inequality, that the bottom 90% was having their
wealth kind of aggressively out by the
top 1%, that is something that I realised in 2011
when I was working as a trader.
At the time, my job was basically to predict
and bet on the future strength of like nations.
So the UK, the US, Europe, these kinds of things.
And it's a funny job in a way because
if you think that the economy is going to be really
bad and the economy turns out to be really bad,
then you make money betting on terrible things.
But that is your job, so it's this kind of strange
job which is slightly dehumanised in a way.
Like if you think a bad thing's going to
happen, your job is to bet that bad thing is
going to happen, and you're kind of encouraged
to think abstractly, step outside the box.
And, if you get it right, you make a
ton of money and nobody really questions like
whether it's the right or the wrong thing to do.
And it felt like a very natural thing
to do for somebody who studied economics.
So, I did economics undergrad at London School of
Economics, and then went into an economic analysis job.
Your job is to look at economies, analyze economies,
make predictions, bet on those predictions.
So when I first put this bet on, I didn't really on
any conscious level think, "What does it mean to bet
on a collapsing economy?" Like I was a young person,
this was my job, I was trying to make money.
I put the bet on.
And it wasn't really until the end of
the year... That year, so this was 2011.
At the end of the year when I got paid on the year,
that I started to really think about, "What does that
mean?" And to be honest, what you see in the sort of
latter part of my book is a long period of me having
this, what you might call, like cognitive dissonance,
which is one part of my brain knows... Well, I
think the first thing say is, when you first put the
bet on, you don't know for sure that you're right.
It's kind of, you're confident, you're confident enough
to bet on it, but you're not sure it's going to happen.
Then at the end of 2011, I was Citibank's
most profitable trader in the year that year,
based on betting society would collapse.
And you get paid a ton of money.
And I think that's probably where like part
of you starts thinking, "Is that like, okay?
Like, should that be the way the world
works?" Like, should you just be paid
a ton of money if the world's going to collapse?
Should you do anything about the economy collapsing?
But I think this is really the big question,
which was, you know, my plan is to show people the
economy is collapsing and hope they will take action.
But when I myself realised the economy was
collapsing, it was a long time before I took action.
And it started a sort of battle in myself where
first of all, you just kind of...
You don't want to accept it.
You don't want to... Because I think if you
were to accept it, it would demand action from you.
So for me as somebody who had made millions
of pounds betting on society collapsing,
I think there's a pretty obvious moral case to
make to somebody like that, that is like, "Well,
maybe you should stop the economy from collapsing."
But obviously to do that, I would have had to quit
my job, and I was making an enormous amount of money.
That would be scary.
Like, I worked really, really hard to get that job.
I came from a poor background, so walking away
from like such a well-paid job was a big thing.
But also like, what do you do?
Like, how can you actually stop this?
And you have these arguments towards the latter
part of the book, where I'm sort of arguing with other
guys at Citibank, my colleagues saying, "Maybe we
should do something." There's one specific discussion
with, a guy who in the book is called Arthur,
where I say to him, like, "Do you think we should
do something about the collapsing economy?" And,
he thinks I mean like, "Do you think we should put
a trade on?" He just keeps saying, "But you already
put the trade on." And I keep saying, "Should we
do something?" And he just doesn't understand it.
And I think what you kind of see here
is basically when you confront somebody
who is working really hard, leads a stressful
life, has worked hard to get the job that they're
in, or is struggling to put food on the table,
anybody, you say, "Hey, society is collapsing.
Let's stop it," I think a very, very normal
emotional human response is to say like, "**** you.
I'm busy.
I'm stressed.
Don't come and tell me we need
save the world, because not my job.
That's the job of the politicians.
Other people should be doing that." And I think a
lot of the pushback that we get, that I get
is basically from people who are kind of struggling
emotionally with the same thing I struggled
emotionally with for a long time, which was, "Oh, ****,
the society we live in is collapsing.
What the **** do we do?" And I think this kind of
debate which I had in my head or in my heart or
in my body sort of in 2011, 2012, and I didn't
finally quit that job till 2014, is to some degree
the argument that we're having in society now.
Because it was pretty clear to me by 2012 that
what was going to happen was living standards would
keep falling basically forever until we stop them.
But I don't think that became really obvious in wider
society, until maybe the last couple of years.
I think you did start to see this
understanding grow more and more and more.
I think that's part of the reason why Brexit happened.
I think that's part of the reason why Trump
got elected both the first time and the second time.
Now we're sort of moving into this space where
it becomes more and more obvious to everyone
that society is collapsing forever, the economy is
collapsing forever, and people as individuals need to
basically decide, "Okay, what do I do with that?
How do I deal with that?" And
this is where Camus comes in.
So I think this book, this book... Camus,
a French Algerian author, he lived in France
during the Nazi occupation of France, and he saw
the rise of the Nazis in the mid-20th Century.
And the book is about an epidemic
of plague in a city in Algeria.
It's a metaphor for, for fascism and for
the Nazis and the growth of Nazism in Europe.
But what he talks about is when you live
in the society that starts to collapse,
what do people... how do people react
to that, and how should people react to that?
And in the book, what you see is, basically
most people just kind of freak the
**** out and kind of lose their minds.
And I'm not going to criticise that response at all
because, that's basically what happened to me.
I had basically a breakdown
when I realised society was collapsing.
I realised it a long time before everybody else.
I've had about 14 years to come to terms with it now.
And you see some people become extremely religious.
Some people become extremely angry.
Some people become violent.
Some people become greedy.
A lot of people become hedonistic.
And I think it's super, super
understandable, this is a reaction.
And when I put my message out there into the
world on the videos saying, "Listen, if we
don't take action, society is going to collapse,"
a lot of the responses I get back
are basically... And, you know, people say, "Oh,
the pro- but the actual solution is Bitcoin.
What you actually need to do is to print money.
You know, the problem is actually immigrants.
The problem is actually foreigners." What
I really hear is a lot of people saying,
"Listen, I'm ******* stressed enough as it is.
Don't you dare tell me that this is my problem and
I need to fix it." The best example of that
was I gave a speech at like a really fancy,
advertising company once, and I was on a panel.
And I did this thing that I do where
I say, "Listen, actually we have this
fundamental problem with inequality.
It's going to get worse and worse.
If we don't take action, society will collapse."
And, um... a lady went up after me and
I think by all accounts, she's a very nice lady.
And what she said was, "Listen, the economy
is part of God's plan and it's like nature.
It's like the changing of the seasons.
Sometimes it gets better and sometimes it gets
worse." And, this was very frustrating for
me in this room full of rich people because
if these people can persuade themselves
that inequality is part of God's plan,
that sometimes it gets better and sometimes it gets
worse, that is a very, very good way of convincing
themselves that they don't need to take action.
And I think a lot of what we are seeing at the
moment is people starting to realise their society
is collapsing and desperately trying to find a
story to tell themselves, "I'm going to be okay.
I don't need to take action.
I don't need to be responsible for fixing this."
So, the truth is, what we are selling here
on this channel is the truth, but it's not
the most promising choice, right?
Because what we are saying is
we have a society-wide economic problem.
The problem is being caused by the very rich.
The people who are supposed be fixing it,
the politicians, the economists, are kind of
incompetent, kind of a little bit bought.
They're not going to fix it.
The job and the responsibility falls on you, ordinary
people, to unite together to educate one another
so that you can push back and fight against the
richest and most powerful people in society.
I think we have to accept that especially in the
very individualistic societies we live in here in
the UK, US, that is not the most appealing message.
And we're not the only guys selling a message
about, "How do you fix this?" There are a
lot of other messages online that's saying
there are other ways to fix your poverty.
I'm going to show you one now from a Instagram
account I've been really enjoying lately.
Listen to this.
Slaves worked all the hours they were awake
for their entire lives.
I think, like, if they can do it, so can I.
You know, Aldous Huxley once said that a
really efficient totalitarian state would
be one with slaves who do not have to be
coerced because they love their servitude.
The reason I wanted show you that is because
as we move further and further and further into this
collapsing economy, and more and more people lose
their minds, people are going to look for ways to get
out of this that they think can protect themselves.
And I think one thing that is super
interesting about this is one of the other
big solutions that people being sold is if you
just work harder, if you work really, really,
really, really, really, really hard, maybe you
will survive the collapse of your whole economy.
And I think it's... it's really appealing
in this post-Thatcher/Reagan world.
There was a quote which, Jack, my
cameraman, told me from Margaret Thatcher.
She said, "Economics are the method.
The object is to change the soul."
And I think that maybe 50 or 60 years ago, we might
have lived in countries where people understood
that the best way to protect your interests
from the rich is to work together.
But as we've moved into very sort of individualistic
mindset, people have been increasingly convinced
that the best way to protect yourself from
the rich is to work really, really, really,
really, really, really, really, really
hard and to compete with other poor people.
If you do that, if everybody does that, if
everybody works really, really, really, really hard to
be the best and lowest paid and hardest working slave,
all you will do is push wages down incredibly quickly
and impoverish yourself and everyone around you.
The only way to fix this is
to find ways to work together.
Okay, so what do you do if you're in that situation,
if you're in a society that is collapsing?
The rich are taking everything.
The 90% are being killed.
The only real way to stop it is to try and unite
that 90% somehow, or as many of it as you can.
But you live in this
phenomenally individualistic society.
Okay, so I'll talk about what I did.
And the truth is, you know, I kind of had
a mental breakdown basically, and this is
the story of the latter part of the book.
I think it's quite beautifully written
personally, but you can read it if you're interested.
And I tried really, really hard to
convince myself that this was not my problem.
There's a side character in my book who,
I wanted to include more, but I didn't have space.
There's a guy called... In the book, he's called Hong.
Really, really nice guy, maybe not the best trader.
But he did this amazing thing, which
is he used to take like 30 sick days a year.
And another guy who I used to work with
called Billy had a little book where
he used to record all of his sick days.
That was on top of his 25 holiday days.
And, nobody got really pissed about
this because he was such a nice guy, and,
he had managed to do this thing in his work
where he had kind of emotionally detached himself
from his work, and he wasn't making the most
money as a trader, but he was a really nice guy.
He was doing his job pretty well, and
he had managed to be emotionally detached.
And I used to sit on my desk on Citibank
trading floor, and I used look at this guy.
In the book, he's called Hong.
This is the scene I wanted to include in the book.
And I used to say to myself, "Why
can't you just be more like Hong?
Why can't you not give a **** about being the best
trader, not give a **** about the world collapsing?
Just get paid your half a million pound
a year and live a ******* good life."
And I tried and I tried and I tried for a long
time, to ignore this sort of, I guess, this
social responsibility to try and fix things.
And then when I tried speak to traders
around me, you know, "Should we do things?"
They just sort of laughed, you know.
Because obviously there's no... You can't pick
up the phone and speak to David Cameron and say,
"The economy's collapsing." And they
said, "It's impossible to do anything." And,
I told myself it was impossible to do anything.
And the truth is, you know, I made this realisation
in 2011. I didn't quit 'til 2014.
I tried really, really, really, really hard
to not do anything about the collapsing economy.
But eventually, the truth is, my body kind
of made the decision for me, and, I got more
and more depressed, and I got more and more sick.
And I didn't really get better until I chose to
quit that job and try and ******* do something.
So personally, I think, and I think this is
the message that Camus comes across in his book,
in a society that is collapsing,
the only way to be healthy and to be calm is
to try to do something to stop that collapse.
But the truth is, even when I did quit in
2014, I didn't work very aggressively, at
fixing the collapsing economy for a long time.
This YouTube channel was started in 2020.
So I haven't spoken much about the
period between me quitting my job in 2014
and me starting this YouTube channel in 2020.
And people who read my book, I kind of wanted
give the impression that I never really wanted
to work for charity and it was kind of like
a game I was using get out of the bank.
But the truth is, that whole period, 2014 - 2020,
I was working in trying to find ways
to stop the economy from collapsing.
And the first thing I did, which I think is
kind of the logical thing to do if your plan is
try and do something about growing inequality,
is I went and I researched the political Left.
It's a common, conspiracy that I'm some sort of
leftist, some massive leftist, some massive communist.
But the truth is, I was never on the political
Left and, I never voted for Labour,
at the point of leaving my job.
But because I thought the problem
was inequality, I assumed the political
Left would be the right place to go.
And I started research the political Left
and I volunteered at some think tanks.
And, you know, I met some great people
who I do still talk to today.
But I was actually like often very,
very frustrated at, number one,
there was almost nobody working on inequality.
And number two, there were a lot of sort of very
posh, well-meaning people who didn't seem super, super,
like really actively concerned and aggressive
about working really hard try and fix inequality.
And I think this is another sort of mental health
wall you can hit when you try to fix things, which...
And we see this a lot, which is people watch our
videos, they become convinced like I was convinced,
and they're like, "Oh my God, I want to do something.
I want to help." But they, similarly to
me in that period of time, they don't know where
to go, they don't know where to use their energy,
they don't know how to actually take action.
So, this is a kind of next step from a mental health
perspective, which is you've realised what's
happening, you've had your freak-out, you've gone
mental for a bit, you've managed to calm yourself down.
You're like, "Now I want to help," and
you can't actually find a place to help.
So, I think with regards to this, I'm always...
We have this discussion quite a lot on
the channel, where we, we talk about like
should we get people to send letters to their
MPs or should we give them like calls to action?
Should we arrange like a march?
Should we arrange like rally?
And I've always been on the side of, I don't want to
arrange these kind of big grandstand events.
What I want to... Because we're not...
I don't want people to give everything, get
super excited, and then burn themself out
because we haven't built those structures.
So what I would say is if you do want to help
and you're in that sort of space, recognise it's
a long-term battle, recognise it's not all on you.
We are not able to give jobs and work
to everybody who wants to support.
What we would ask you to do is always
watch and understand the videos, share the
videos, share the message, get good at explaining
in a simple way that the reason the economy is
getting worse is because of growing inequality,
and just build that message, build that message.
If you're an ordinary person,
that's all we would ask of you.
If you are somebody who is in some position
of power, like you... you are on the political
Left or you are on the political Right, I
think you should be asking yourself, how can
you create spaces for other people to get
involved so that they can support this message?
But the final big realisation that I made in that
period when I was trying to figure out ways to fix it
was basically that the fire engines are not coming.
So, there are these institutions in society that are
supposed to protect us from economic collapse,
which are most obviously the politicians, but also
the academic economists, institutions like central
banks, which are full of economists that are supposed
protect your country's economy, things
like the civil service, things like the media.
These guys are all supposed to
realise there is an economic collapse.
And the big thing that I realised after leaving
the bank is that basically these institutions are all
kind of broken and not able to recognise that basically
what is happening is being caused by inequality.
And that was kind of the second
big shocking realisation for me.
And it's also another big shocking realisation,
I think for... to give to ordinary people.
The truth is, the institutions that are supposed
to protect your economy are not functioning.
They're unable to realise
that inequality is the core problem.
That's another thing we just need to sit and
take a long breath and think about, because
that means that if you are just a regular person,
the responsibility to protect your family and
your kids' and your grandkids' future falls upon you.
And that is another thing which is going to freak
people out from a mental health perspective.
But I think the way to deal with it
is to understand it, to accept it, and to find
some way that you can contribute fixing things.
Take it easy.
Don't work too hard.
Support us.
If you are able to get yourself into a
position of power, we really, really need to
get this idea better understood amongst people
like politicians, economic academics,
economists, the media, civil servants.
We need these think tanks.
We need these people to understand better.
If you do not deal with growing
inequality, your society will collapse.
And if you are working in one of those spaces or are able
to work in one of those spaces, please try your best to
spread that message so that people can understand it.
So that brings us to where we are now basically.
The message that I want to send across is that
the reality of the situation is really, really bad.
That is a massive opportunity because it is going to
damage 90% of families in my country and your country.
If we can unite those families, we can
definitely create change politically.
But it is a massive blow to tell people that
that is going to happen, and we need to find ways
to support each other to get people to understand
what's happening and not freak the **** out.
And that's true for me as
well, and it's true for you.
Listen, I've known for 14 years now
that our economy was going to collapse, and,
the truth is like for the last three years
I've known we had a real opportunity, a really
big opportunity to build something big here.
I'm really proud of what we've built.
I have probably pushed myself a bit too hard.
I took six, seven weeks off earlier this
year, and I came back, and I was really
sort of gunning for it, ready to sort of
go and hold the politicians to account.
And, I've been meeting people at think tanks.
I've been speaking to politicians and celebrities
and trying to build... trying to build a bigger
social media infrastructure for these sort of ideas.
But for the last few weeks, I've been really
struggling a little bit just to make videos, just
to sort of find the creativity to make good videos.
It's a funny thing for me because my background is
maths and economics, and, I'm always really, really,
really confident with the economics understanding.
I'm really confident at trading.
But this YouTube and also the book,
it's not just about understanding the economy.
A huge part of it is this kind of creative
job of how do you package it, how do you make
it compelling, how do you draw people in?
And it's really, it's that kind of creative
energy that I've been struggling a little bit
with recently, and it's, it's the first time
that's ever really happened to me, to be honest.
When I wrote the book, it was kind of amazing,
I could just... it took a long time for
me to figure out the shape of it, but once
I had that, it just really flowed through.
And for the last sort of two, three years, I've taken
these big breaks, but I've felt really, really
confident about the creative product we've been making.
And especially the first half of this year,
I thought the videos were amazing, and I really
wanted come back and really hit the ground running
with videos, but I'm honestly just starting
to feel like I'm a little bit running on empty.
And that, and that's been difficult for me.
But I think I've got my
plan for what I'm going to do.
I'm going to mix up videos a bit.
You might find this surprising.
I hate talking to camera, and if
you look at the older videos we used to do,
I used to do a lot of videos where I would talk
to, my mate Simran used to stand over here, and,
I found those videos way, way easier to make.
I think I might need to basically
reduce a little bit my shoot days, and
only do some to camera and do some off camera.
I think I'm going to have to do that
basically in order to slow things down.
It's disappointing for me because,
I really feel like we're sort of, we're
really getting close to building something.
But I can only carry as much as I can carry, and,
basically I need you guys to do a little bit more.
I need especially... If you are somebody
who has influence in one of those spaces,
the political left, the political right,
government, politicians, media, civil servants,
academia, I really need you guys to start
carrying it a bit more and push it a bit more.
Because I don't think I'm going to be able to keep
pushing it as much as I have been the last few years.
But I'm not going to take a break.
We're going to keep shooting at least
for another couple of months.
Look, the strategy is simple.
If we've got enough people, we don't need
individuals to throw themselves at the barricades.
We don't need individuals to burn themselves out.
Understand the message, spread it, bring people in.
But we also need to build models of
strength that aren't just about individualism,
people being the best, people being richest.
Because the problem is here is really quite simple.
If we can find enough people in this country,
in your country, who are willing to be unselfish
enough that they don't prioritise just their
interests, but they work together to build and
spread a simple message, then their financial
interests will be protected in the long run.
If we are a country that is too selfish, that it
cannot find enough people to protect their collective
interests, then most people will be bankrupted.
So it's kind of this beautiful irony in
a way, which is if people are so
blinded by their selfish material interests,
then they will be materially bankrupted.
But if enough people can stand together to work
together to protect their joint material interests,
then their material interests will be protected.
So it's a battle in a sense
for the soul of the country.
I know which side I'm going to fight on.
I hope you fight too.
You know, I've mentioned Margaret Thatcher in this
video, and she said once, "There is, no such thing
as society." I think what she meant by that was
it is the job of all of us to simply protect ourselves.
The problem is we are in a competition for
resources here, and if we deal with this
in a series of one-on-one battles,
then basically the rich will take everything.
So if we live in a society of individuals
where nobody helps each other, where nobody protects
each other, then who protects the poor from the rich?
So that's it basically.
My video on mental health.
I think it's difficult to be mentally well
when you're in society that's falling apart,
especially a society that tells us
our individual responsibilities are only to
ourselves, but makes it almost impossible
for us protect ourselves individually.
I think the way for us to stay
mentally healthy is... is to fight back,
but to fight back in a way that is balanced.
Don't burn yourself out.
Support each other.
You're going to need each other.
All right, that's it for this week.
We're going to do some more,
off-camera stuff I think.
I've got a couple of good ones coming up.
One about how to build a wealth tax in
terms of implementation, and one about
why you need to forget about money.
Yeah, we're going to try some
new sort of video styles out.
Let us know what you think when you see them.
That's it.
Thanks for your support.
Tax wealth, not work.
Thank you.