Okay.
Welcome back to
Garys Economics.
Today, we are going to
do something different
and we're going to have
a guest on the channel,
an economist for
the very first time.
One of my
favorite economists
working today.
I very often get
asked on this channel,
where else can we go to
learn about economics?
What other stuff
can we read?
How can we learn more?
And there are a
lot of economists who
I like working today.
There's obviously a
couple of French guys
working on inequality-
Piketty and Zucman.
But the person who I
always recommend, because
I think he is the best at
writing about economics in
a way that is accessible
and relatable for
ordinary people is today's
guest on the channel.
So I'd like to
welcome Ha-Joon Chang.
Thank you.
Thank you very much
for coming.
I think I'll just
introduce briefly
how we met and how
I got to know you.
So, I quit banking
in 2014, and when I
came back, I was sort
of looking about how can
I change the economy.
And I didn't really
know much about
the work getting done in
economics today, and I got
invited to a small, what
can I say, lecture series
that you were doing?
Yeah.
When was it?
Was it 2015, perhaps?
'15, '16, I forget.
2015,
I was invited to a
lecture series which you
gave to a smaller
audience, and I was lucky
to watch a few lectures
you gave about how, I
think it was How Poor
Countries Become Rich.
And I was very impressed
at the time about
basically how you
seemed to have thought
the problems through
and delivered answers
rather than kind of
relying on rigidly
mathematical models.
That's kind of you.
And I was very
impressed at basically
how you were just able
to communicate ideas
in a way that ordinary
people would understand.
So, was very impressed,
and I'm very happy
to have you as the first
guest on the channel.
Thanks.
Yeah, actually those
lectures
have been made into this
lecture series called
Economics For People
and available on INET
website, The Institute
for New Economic Thinking.
Yes.
I sometimes get people
tweet photos of me
asking you a question,
saying, "Oh, here's-"
That's right, you
asked some sharp questions.
Yeah.
Looking, looking
younger and fresher,
less jaded by politics.
Yeah, yeah.
So would you be able to
introduce yourself a
little to the audience,
talk a little bit about
why you chose to
study economics,
when you started, why
you chose to move
to the UK to study,
because I know this is
not where you're from
originally.
That's right.
Yeah, yeah.
I'm Ha-Joon Chang.
I'm a professor at
SOAS, University of
London, at the moment.
I used to teach in
Cambridge for over three
decades.
I've moved to SOAS recently.
Yes, I was born in
South Korea in 1963.
That was right at
the beginning of the
country's so-called
economic miracle.
And, you know, really
that was
where I grew up and when
I grew up that I wanted to
study economics, because,
you know, at the time,
South Korea was
growing at like 10%,
12%, sometimes at 15.
This is when you were
sort of in your teens?
That's... Yeah,
that's right,
In the
'60s and '70s, yeah.
And yeah, I mean, the
people's living
standards were rising
really rapidly and, you
know, the new buildings
going new towns
are forming.
Yeah, so there were a lot
of good things
going on then because, you know, at
that level of
income, you know, the
South Korea's income,
per, per capita income,
you know, for example, in
the, the ni- early
1970s when I was a primary
school student was
like, $400, yeah?
Yeah, so I think...
It was a very
poor country-
Yeah.
which meant that this economic growth
really was
literally a matter of
life and death, you know.
Yeah.
Because that in that, at that
level of development, if
your economy grows at
5% rather than
the 1%, it means that
you eat one
more bowl of rice
Was it still like a very
agricultural economy-
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
at that time.
but you know,
like 60... 50-60% of
people were in
the countryside,
engaged in farming.
But also because
the country was
industrialising rapidly
literally millions
of people were arriving
in Seoul, the
capital city, and
Busan, Ulsan, these industrial cities
in the Southeast
to find jobs
in factories, yeah?
But the life was very
hard for the workers,
you know, because
this was a time when
these workers are working
13, 14 hours a day,
six and a half days a week.
In factories, in cities?
Ye- yeah.
Exactly, yeah.
And some factories refused
to serve soup in the
canteen so that they
don't have to give extra toilet break
No, no.
this was a very,
very harsh time.
Yeah.
But, you know, things were
improving.
On the other hand, you
know, you had
these workers you
know, being
worked to death, and you know,
slums springing
up in urban
areas, and then the-
Okay.
property developers
mobilising
these thugs to beat people up
to clear illegal
settlements.
So you've got this
rapidly urbanising and,
like, growth is high,
incomes are growing,
but living standards are
still really poor for a
lot of people, That's right.
the cities are growing
in sort of slum fashion.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And then there
were a lot of tension
because, you
know, the country was
between 1961 and
'87 ruled by a
military dictatorship.
Even though this military government,
was able to
engineer this rapid
economic development
into the very brutal-
yeah.
And as I grew up,
I just, I wanted to
understand what's going on
around me.
And you, you're, you
were growing up in, like,
a middle-class family?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
In Seoul?
That's right, yeah.
My father was a high
ranking civil servant,
in the Ministry
of Finance, and yeah.
I mean, okay, I mean,
we were not rich, but,
well off, yeah?
I guess by the standards
of a career which was
quite poor at the time.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
So, when I was a kid,
our house was the only
house in the neighborhood
with a TV, you know?
Okay.
So people went to...
came to our
house to watch
a football matches,
a boxing match.
So
you were witnessing, I
guess, it sounds like
a period of really
rapid economic change
and economic growth, and,
like, that interested
you and excited you.
That's right, yeah.
So there were
a lot of positive
things happening,
but also a lot of
negative things, yeah?
I mean this exploitation of
workers, you know?
Yeah.
Political
repression, you know?
It's interesting to hear
you talk about the, like,
the rapidly growing cities
and the rapidly growing
slums because obviously
at the moment, we have
a government that is
obsessed with growth,
and they want to build,
they want to build,
they want to build.
And, I come from,
like, a very poor
part of East London.
Yeah.
And I'm seeing, you
know, I'm sure it's not
the same, but I'm seeing
this, like, rapid growth
of these poorer
outer London suburbs,
and basically
turning into slums.
Yeah.
I was saying before,
the Daily Mail went
to my house last week.
And I think they
wanted to do, like,
the house I grew up in,
and they wanted to do
a story like, "Oh, you
know, Gary said he was
poor, but he's actually
not." And the story
they actually wrote was,
"Oh my God, this place
is a slum." They
couldn't believe it.
so it's interesting to see
You know, And I often
worry that this like,
this rapid, like,
move for growth
will lead to the
slumification of London.
Yeah, yeah.
No, I mean, of
course, I mean,
it was worse in Korea
at the time because
the general living
standard was lower.
But yeah, I mean, if you
expand too fast
these builders are
not going to build
houses of good standard.
Yeah, and of course,
we're only a few years
out from the Grenfell
disaster, you know?
Exactly.
I sometimes worry that
this, "Let's slash the
red tape," sometimes
feels shocking to me.
Yeah.
I mean, the housing
problem has to be
solved by, you know, the
regulation and the
more equal distribution
of assets, I mean,
you cannot solve it by building
more houses.
It seems a bit
naive to me.
But let's get back to,
you're a child in Korea.
It was my fault.
You're interested in
economics, and you decide
that you, you moved to, in
the UK when you were 18?
No, no, no, no.
Actually, I went
to university in Korea.
Okay.
In Seoul?
Yeah.
So we studied
economics, and, yeah, some
professors were different,
but most of the professors
were just teaching
this equilibrium
models, you know?
The similar models to
what I would have learned.
Exactly.
Mathematically less
sophisticated,
but the same idea.
Yeah.
Okay.
So just these
are like basically
very mathematically,
mathematically complex,
mathematical equilibrium
models, not so much
stuff on the history of
economic thought, perhaps?
Yeah.
We had a course
in the history of
economic thought.
And you don't
mind me asking,
what
years would you have
been studying in Korea?
Yeah.
So I entered
university in 1982.
Okay.
And graduated in 1986,
and came to England in
the summer of '86
to start my master's.
Okay, just
before was born.
Exactly, yeah, yeah.
I'm old, yeah.
So well, I, yeah,
entered the university,
most of the professors
were, you know,
teaching this abstract...
In Seoul?
Yeah, Seoul
National University.
And many of my friends couldn't take
it seriously, you know, because, there's this
huge upheaval
going on outside the
classrooms, you know?
Economic development,
export success,
political
repression, you know?
Yeah.
In 1980, the second
military government
committed
this massacre in
actually my father's
hometown killing
thousands of people
who are protesting against
the
coup d'etat and, you know?
So, a lot of us got interested in
finding out whether there's another
way of thinking
about economics.
So you went
into university.
And you got very
interested in economics,
and you were kind of
almost amused by
your university
basically doing maths.
That's right.
And there's not much
discussion of, there's
all of this crazy stuff
happening, you know?
Exactly.
This is, you know, one
of the great modern
economic miracles, right?
at this period of
Korean economic growth.
Yeah.
So you kind, you
kind of thought...
I mean, I had a
similar thing, really.
Like you sort of, you,
I think sometimes people
are really amazed when I
tell them, we don't talk
about the housing crisis.
That's right, yeah.
And we don't, we don't
talk about the cost
of living crisis.
Uh-uh.
What we do is maths.
Yeah.
And I did my undergrad
in the mid-2000s.
Yeah.
And I did my post-grad
2017 to '19.
Yeah, and while you were doing
this, there's
one of the biggest financial crises in the
history of capitalism.
Yeah.
And many professors-
I'm kind of
surprised to hear
that even, you know,
this is 30 years earlier
in Korea.
You were also doing
this very, very
heavily mathematised
form of study.
That's right, yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, so I just wanted to study something
different, and I
found out that there
were a few universities in
England and the United
States where you could
study non-Neoclassical
economics, Marxist economics,
development economics,
So, just to make clear,
we're talking, you didn't
want to do just this
kind of very specific
heavily mathematised.
That's what you mean when
you say Neoclassical?
Yeah, yeah, I mean already Neoclassical
economics was very
heavily mathematised.
So Neoclassical is
basically like the...
at the moment at elite
universities there's
kind of one... there's
basically there's one-
Exactly, yeah.
one kind of economics that
you're taught almost, from
my perspective, almost
as if it's like physics,
like a physical science.
That's right, yeah.
So this is a particular
approach to economics
which assumes that the
world is made up of
this selfish rational
individuals, and they,
you know, try to
get ahead and compete with
each other, and that's
what generates wealth and-
And in particular,
what I often talk
about on this channel
is that these models,
these kind of large-scale
heavily mathematical
models, they tend to
use what they call
representative agency.
Which means
that rather than
talking about, we have
whatever 60 million people
in the UK or 40 million
people in Korea, you
just look at the average.
You say let's look at
one guy, the average guy,
the representative guy.
Which of course means
there is no inequality.
Exactly, by definition,
There's no equality
in distribution.
And you were studying
the... that was the
same thing you would
have been studying.
Yeah, exactly, and
yeah,
still laughing
when I remember that
incident you know,
these models
that really came on
stream in a major way
in the 1980s,
because yeah,
before it was more
of a general equilibrium
and that, that kind of
stuff and, yeah, it,
in my early days in
Cambridge, someone
was, giving a...
a seminar using this
representative
agent model.
Yeah.
He also added this
assumption that
this agent is
non-infinitely lived.
Okay, well, I'm
glad to hear it.
We are like looking at this guy
and one of us
asked, "What does that
mean, 'non-infinitely
lived'?" And
another guy said, "Well,
I guess it means that
we all die in the end."
Yeah.
You know what mean?
There's no sense of realism there.
I mean, just whatever makes it
mathematically neat. Yeah.
I wondered, so-
You say
moved to Cambridge in '86?
Exactly, yeah.
To do your post
grad, masters?
That's right, masters
and PhD, and then I
studied with
Professor Bob
Rowthorn who was a famous
Marxist economist.
Okay.
Yeah, although, I mean,
he did lots
of other things and,
he didn't insist that, I
follow his approach,
so my approach is a bit different from
him, but I really thank
him for, kind of showing
me different types of
economics and, you know,
teaching me
how to kind of reconcile
them if I have to and...
So you chose to go to
Cambridge because you
thought that Cambridge
was teaching like a more
like diverse range of-
That's right,
ways of looking
at economics?
Yeah, that, at
that time Cambridge was of
course at the bastion of
Keynesian economics.
Okay.
Can you just
quickly describe what
that means to our viewers
who might not know.
Yeah, Keynesian economics
is economics that
was kind of invented
by the early 20th century
British economist
John Maynard Keynes,
who... well like you, made a lot of money in
the financial market.
He's one of a few
economists who actually
makes money in
the financial market
because surprisingly
many economists that
when they invest
in financial market
they fail.
Not so surprising to me.
But he was rooted in, so
I think
one of the best
economists of all time.
Yeah, exactly.
And he lived through
The Great Depression.
That's right, yeah.
So his argument was look,
you cannot treat
the economy
as a household, yeah?
Yeah.
That is the
mistake that the
current Labour Government
is making, yeah?
We've maxed out
our credit card, you know,
we cannot spend more.
Of course you can, but
the point is that...
He's basically saying,
if you tax people,
like tax working people
more and you don't... the
government stops spending,
you'll basically cause
this kind of economic
depression which is that
there's not
enough spending,
businesses will fail.
Then more people
will lose their jobs.
And, well
yeah, this is-
Yeah, so his point was
you know,
that your income is
my spending, you know.
My spending is
your income, yeah.
Although we're kind of
in this weird situation
in the UK now where we
have a government that
seems to want to spend
but is kind of not
able to spend and we'll
discuss more on this.
But, so basically
I think the point
you're making is at
universities, especially
elite universities,
economics is kind of
taught like there's this
one way of doing things.
Exactly.
Which you're
calling Neoclassical,
neoliberal, which is this
very highly mathematised,
rational individuals, we
look at the averages, but
there are other ways of
thinking about things like
Keynesianism, Marxist
economics.
And you wanted to,
I guess, study a wider
variety so that's why
you went to Cambridge.
Absolutely, yeah.
Cambridge was, you
know Neoclassical
economics was not
so dominant until the
1950s and '60s, but from the '70s it started
really pushing out
other schools because
they are more kind of,
accepting of
the status quo.
They don't
ask awkward
questions, yeah?
So it was that really becoming
dominant, but there
was still in the '80s
a few places here and there where
Neoclassical economics
was not dominant.
Cambridge was one
of those places.
Is Cambridge still
like that now?
No.
Okay.
Because when I... so
I went to London School
of Economics, 2005 to
2008, and really to be
honest, I was not, I was
not even really aware that
there were other ways-
Exactly, yeah.
No, no, that's how
it is, these
days and, you know.
Yeah.
So I deliberately
wanted
to come to Cambridge.
Luckily I got accepted,
but you know, when
I told people that
I want to study in
England, I mean, a
lot of people in Korea-
Your friends and-
just couldn't understand
it because
you know, we had no
historic relationship with
England, so studying
abroad meant 90%
going to the US and
maybe 5% to
Germany, 5% to France.
Hardly anyone came to England,
And yeah, I mean, moreover
people thought wanting to study
anything other than Neoclassical was
career suicide, yeah?
I mean, career hadn't even
begun, but you know.
Yeah.
So.
So have you got
any advice to... We
sometimes get messages
from young people who
are studying economics
or are interested in
studying economics.
Sometimes we even get
messages from people who
are really interested in
the ideas that we talk
about on this channel,
we talk a lot about
inequality, and they
say, "Where can I learn
about these things,
where should I study?
is it gonna be a
problem if, for me, for
like career advancement?"
What advice would
you give to young people
who are interested in
studying economics
and actually learning
about the economy?
Yeah, I mean, it's getting more and
more difficult to study
economics in a kind of
pluralistic way that
accepts different
theoretical approaches and
try to learn the best
from all of them,
because most
universities will teach you a very,
very narrow curriculum
completely dominated
by mathematics, yeah?
Yeah.
So basically a lot of
people want to study
economics because
they want to understand
inequality, you know,
cost of living crisis,
financial crisis
and then they go to the
university and they
don't learn any of those,
and then they do maths
for three years
and they graduate,
you know?
Maybe you could speak a
little bit, because you
were teaching at Cambridge
for quite a long
time, right?
As you've been teaching
at SOAS so you've been
an economics professor and
teacher at universities
for a number of years.
Yeah.
My experience of
studying economics is
when I did my undergrad
I was at LSE, it's a
very elite university.
So lots of
wealthy students.
The truth is
for me, I found the
majority of students
there on the undergrad,
to be honest,
I think they were not, and
I include myself in this.
We were not really that
interested in the economy,
really.
We were there
because we thought,
I think rightly to some
degree, that economics,
especially at an elite
university like LSE, was
a way to get a well-paid
job.
It is, yeah.
So how...
What... Is that what you
were seeing when you were
at Cambridge as well?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
But you know, I mean
there are different
people, so the...
Yeah, even in
Cambridge,
I would say, you know,
30% of the students were
quite interested in the
real world problems.
And Cambridges-
It's funny that, it's
quite a small minority
but that's the
same, I think at LSE
was probably
slightly less.
Yeah, to be fair,
Cambridge
still offers a slightly
more diverse
curriculum than
LSE.
It used to be
actually very
real world oriented and
diverse and so until
about 2005, yeah?
And then
does a major curricular
reform that made it
very mathematical and...
Yeah, so that another
story, but,
so... But the problem
is that even for those
30%, 35%, I mean-
That's just the nature
of the study, the ma- the
The ability to think
about the economy is
beaten out of them, yeah?
I think, yeah,
I think your
gestures are correct.
So for me, okay, so I
well, when I did
my undergrad I was not
interested in economics.
Really.
Other than its ability
to get me a good job.
And that was almost
everyone at LSE
was like that.
But then I went back to do
a master's, at Oxford,
'17 to '19, and what's interesting about
that is the master's is
not really like necessary
to get a good job.
That's true.
If have a good undergrad.
So then that means
that some of the people
who did the master's
a much bigger
percentage of them
were kind of interested in
economics.
But of course they've all
had this experience of,
you go to do your
undergrad and maybe you go
in quite naively thinking,
"I'm gonna learn
about the economy."
But the actual experience
is you have to do a lot
of very, very difficult,
essentially algebra exams.
Algebra and calculus
exams, and, you
know, it's just like
complicated maths.
And then those exams
are really hard.
So then you,
you don't... Unless
you're like super smart,
you don't really have-
Time to do anything else.
Yeah, you, you don't have
time to step back and be
like, "Well, you know,
does it make sense that we
don't look at the... have
any wealth distribution
in the model?" You don't
really ha- you know,
you need to be, and also
if you were to think,
ask those questions,
who do you ask them to?
You know, I was at Oxford.
Oxford had one guy who
looked at inequality.
Was his name
Tony Atkinson?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
And he died
1 year before I entered.
Yeah, so I applied
with the hope...
He was a yeah,
very influential
economist in the field
of inequality study.
I think Piketty was
quite an influence.
Yeah, yeah.
So by the time I got
there, there was not
even anybody to speak
to about inequality.
And then, and, you know,
you have to, you have
to study really hard.
And, you know, I didn't
really care about my
grades in master's
but, you know, it does
whip it out of you,
because if you, if you,
you have to do so much
maths and it's difficult.
Yeah.
And there's... and
it kind of whips out
anyone who actually
wants to ask these
big questions, it's
like, well, everyone
else is doing 100
hours a week of maths.
And you're sitting around
asking stupid questions.
That's right, yeah.
Yeah, so I think it
does kind of whip,
and I thought it was
really, really sad.
Like, I thought the
smartest kids on that
Oxford post-grad course
they all dropped
out of economics.
Because it was like, well,
the guys were curious.
It was so clear there is
no space here for people
who are curious
about the economy.
Yeah.
This conversation
reminds me of what
the radical Keynesian
economist,
Joan Robinson said.
I mean, Robinson was
one of the few...
Was she at Cambridge?
... Yeah,
female economist, yeah,
was a big name in
the Keynesian economics.
I mean, she should have
got greater
recognition, but she was very left-wing
and asked a lot of
awkward questions, and
yeah, therefore she was pushed back.
But she once famously said that, "I
had to learn to think
because I wasn't all that
good at math," you know?
Yeah.
I think it, I
think it, yeah.
Sometimes, maths
becomes substitution
for thinking, yeah?
Yeah, well, I think,
no, I think that's
a really good point.
I think that's a
really good point.
The obsession,
it's insane, Because you
know, especially for
that Oxford post-grad.
You know, it's very
difficult to get
into, Oxford's a very
prestigious university.
These are really, really
smart kids, and the
reality of it is we
spent two years locked
in tiny windowless rooms
inverting matrices.
That's right.
It's insane.
It really, really is
insane, but I think this,
I want to make this
point to our viewers.
because the point I often
make is, you know, at
the end of the day, these
are the guys who are
controlling the economy,
making the decisions
about the economy and-
It's quite worrying,
isn't it, yeah?
Well, the other point
that I make is, and this
something I wanted to
ask you about, was so
when I did my undergrad,
I think LSE is
probably the worst for
this, but I don't think
it's unusual at all.
The vast majority of the
students wanted to be
traders.
Or at the very least
to work in finance.
And the vast majority
of the students with the
best grades did go on
to become traders.
Does that mirror
with what you've seen
as a professor watching
students go through?
Yeah.
I mean, you cannot
blame them, you know,
they've... No, I did it myself.
That's right.
Going into trading,
I mean, you will be
making five,
ten times what
you could be making in
any other uh, possible
uh, profession
The civil service
or whatever.
So that is natural, yeah?
But, you
know, the trouble is
when you train people in
this particular way,
basically maths, and
then put them in
charge of the economies,
a bit like
training people
in, say, biochemistry
and then make them
medical doctors, yeah?
Yeah, so it's related, yeah?
So you have to
understand the principles
of biochemistry and so
in order to understand
human body and so on,
but you need clinical
experiences, yeah?
You should have
actually looked at
actual patients
to know how to
diagnose them as well.
Yes, this is, this is the,
the big thing that
I feel is missing.
And to be honest, it's
why I was impressed
when I went to your
lecture series.
Which is, I think that
from my personal
experience, first of
all, these guys who
study economics to high
level, they're smart guys.
They're very good-
Of course, yeah.
To be honest, they're
very good at maths.
Yeah.
But I think there's really
a lack of being able
to, or even in a sense
thinking that it's a thing
you should do, step back
and look at what you're
doing in a, in a sort
of big picture sense.
Yeah.
I always remember when
I was at Oxford, we had
one lecture, and
there was a discussion
of like the aftermath
to the 2008 crisis.
Which the recovery was
much weaker than everybody
predicted, and they were
saying, "We don't know
why." And I put my hand
up and I asked this guy-
"Okay, well, why do
you think it was?"
And he said, and
I think this is
one of the funniest
things I've ever heard.
He said, "We're not sure
why, but we think it was
because of an exogenous
shock to consumption
savings preferences."
Which is, oh, this me,
I have to explain this
to the audience, right?
Exogenous
is a technical term in
economics modeling which
means something outside
of the model has changed.
So I've asked him, "Why
do you think..." You
know, this is a real
thing that happened in the
real world.
"Why do you think the
recovery was so weak?"
And he said, without
like a hint of irony, "We
think something outside
the model changed."
And that is crazy.
It's a cr- but I think
it shows exactly when you
make a guy do so, do so
much maths in the model
they forget that the model
is not the real world.
And when you reach the
point that you start
explaining things in
the real world by using
technical terms, saying
something outside the
model has changed, I
think this captures
like exactly what has
gone wrong.
And the maddest thing
is, nobody in the hall
even laughs, you know?
They just think, they're
just like, they...
I think this form of
like very, very intense
forcing people to do maths
is almost like
a brainwashing.
That's right, yeah, yeah.
No, I mean, first
of all, you know, that
what this guy was
implicitly saying
was "Suddenly people
didn't want to spend."
Yeah, which is the
whole answer, yeah.
Why, yeah?
Yeah.
Some I don't know,
alien overlord that...
Yeah, came in and
changed the world.
Yeah.
That's right, came and
changed people.
I mean, that's
so stupid.
But secondly, even
if that is the
case, then why are you
not putting that
into your model, yeah?
Yeah, it's-
So it's that,
like, you know,
I mean, unfortunately,
this is now
kind of verging
on becoming a
theology, you know.
I mean-
Yeah, yeah, I saw.
I don't know
if you realise.
I know you're not
on social media.
There is a clip
of you kind of going
viral on social media.
Oh, yeah, yeah,
Are you aware of this?
Well, yeah, my son,
who's...
who's working in the
the Royal Institution.
He's a biologist.
But even he saw it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
People keep sending it
to me, yeah, of you
basically saying like...
And I think it's a
really good point and I
think it's totally true.
Like it or not, economics has become
a bit like Catholic
theology in medieval
Europe.
It has, basically
become the language
of the rulers.
So, if you don't
speak economics, you
cannot participate
in any debate.
Unless you're able to
speak in this language,
use these terms, you're
basically not allowed
to have an opinion.
And it kind of locks...
To be honest, like,
it locks poor people
out of the
conversation.
Yeah, absolutely.
This... I mean,
this scary parallel
with Catholic theology
in medieval Europe
Yeah.
So, theology at
the time was justifying
whatever is going
on in the world.
Yeah?
Yeah.
You know, famine and
exploitation.
You know, the
abuse of power.
Whatever, it's all in God's will, yeah?
Today, whatever is
going wrong in
the world is
justified by economics.
Yeah, must be-
This must be what is
best for the economy.
Exactly, yeah.
Yeah.
Best of all possible
worlds, yeah?
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
And
to make it worse-
they, they use that
term a lot in economi-
well, they use, "The
first best optimal."
Yeah, exactly.
Have you, have you read
Candide by Voltaire?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, so there's a
book, it influenced
me a lot in my book,
where he talks about-
this, It's
by Voltaire.
Hundreds of years ago.
He says that
back in the day
they justified everything
by saying, "If it wasn't
supposed to be like this-"
That's right.
"... God wouldn't have
made it like this."
Yeah, exactly.
"This must be the best
of all possible worlds or
God would've made
it differently."
Yeah.
And economics
uses sometimes
similar language.
They say like, "The first
best optimal outcome."
"If it wasn't supposed to
be like this, the economy
wouldn't have made this."
Absolutely.
But what I want to...
The point which I make a
lot on this channel is if
you reach high levels in
this debate about how we
should run the economy,
how we should manage the
economy, so if you become
a prestigious academic
or if you become a
high level politician, or
if you become, working
in the central bank,
or even high level media,
you're quite rich
by that point.
Yeah.
And then what you have
is a group of rich people
basically refusing to
allow poor people into
the conversation because
they're saying, "Sorry,
you can't speak the
maths," saying, "We think
nothing should change"
as a way of justifying
a system which,
from where I'm standing,
appears to make the
rich richer every year.
Yeah.
And is, is... It's
crushing living standards.
Yeah, we have to remember,
you know, during the, the
medieval times, the
Vatican did not allow the
Bible to be translated
into vernacular languages.
It all had to be in Latin.
So most people
couldn't read Latin.
And therefore, they had to just
take the
priest's word
for... I mean, the...
Yeah, the face
value, yeah?
This is basically why
the Daily Mail has
run four stories on me
in four consecutive
days, because...
You are dangerous.
What I'm trying to do on
this channel, and I think
it's also a lot of what
you're trying to do,
in the work that you do,
but also your books, which
are very accessible to
ordinary people is, you're
trying to explain what's
happening to ordinary
people in a language
they can understand.
And well, I talk about
it a lot on this channel,
what I think is happening
is that the distribution
is changing.
The wealth distribution is
changing in front of us.
Ordinary people
are getting poorer.
The rich and the very
rich are getting richer.
And I think if
people... You know, I
said it a lot on this
channel, what I see
my mission as is really
quite simply getting
people to understand
what is happening.
Absolutely, yeah.
Because if people
understood what is
happening and also what's
goIng to happen, so in my
opinion, and don't know
how much of our videos
you've watched, I think
this crisis of wealth
inequality will get worse.
I think it's, it's
really going to...
It's already decimated
the working classes
in the West.
I think it's starting to
decimate the middle class.
You're seeing how it's
basically impoverishing
the government, and that
is happening in a context
of rapidly growing wealth
of the richest.
Yeah, and now, I mean,
in places like the US,
although it's happening in other
countries at a lower
level, you know, now
there's blatant
money politics, yeah?
Yeah.
Well, I saw on the
news this morning- we
had Elon Musk offering
people a million dollars-
Exactly,
if you voted his way.
Yeah.
Well, this is another
point I like to make
a lot, which is,
distribution of wealth
is distribution of power
and, it's control over
resources, but it's also
control over the media
and it's also control
over the politicians.
Exactly.
Now, we're in a
downward spiral
because it's
feeding into each other.
So, the more inequality,
economic inequality
gives more power to
this rich people
Yeah.
Which they can then
use to take more power.
Yeah, that's right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I talk about
this a lot actually.
I talk about basically
these dynamics
which you're talking
about, which is
the more power they have,
the more they can... The
quicker they can take
the rest of the power-
which means they will
then have more power.
And I think that this is
the kind of spiral that,
that we are in, and
yeah, I'll be honest,
I speak about it a lot.
I'm really worried
about where this goes.
Like, on the first
level in terms of living
standards, but also in
terms of, in terms of
politics, because... Well,
first, I suppose, I'll
ask you this question.
I think, unfortunately,
that unless we get
some change on taxation
inequality, which I don't
think we will get, at
least in the short term,
I think living
standards in... for
the West, for the
working class, for
the middle class, will
continue to decrease.
Do you think
that's likely?
You have so-called
Labour Government
cutting benefits, yeah?
Yeah.
Disability benefits
of all things, yeah.
I think unless... I know,
you know, I'm trying to
get some influence with,
with the Labour Party
obviously the government
of this country.
Why do you think they're
so reluctant to discuss
taxing the riches?
Well, I mean, a
a kind of charitable
interpretation is that
they are scared of the
financial market, yeah.
Yeah, but you know...
Yeah, but I think-
If you borrow a lot,
so I think at the moment
we're in this space
where they, they want
to borrow, it's just
borrow, borrow, borrow.
But if you borrow from
the financial markets,
you know, you are
essentially borrowing
from the rich.
Yeah.
If borrowing is
your only plan
then you are a slave to
the financial markets.
You know, if I...
if my plan is to
borrow from you,
then I need you
to agree to that.
If my plan is to tax
you, I don't need
you to agree to that.
So I think really the
way to break out of that
fear of financial markets
is to start talking about,
about taxation and, and...
well, I'll tell
you what I think.
You didn't ask, but I'll
tell you what I think.
I think these guys,
they're being pressured
by their rich funders.
I think they don't want to
push back on it basically.
But I think also,
I think there is a
real lack of economists
in looking at things
like the distribution.
Yeah, so unfortunately I
think that economists
in the Labour Party, they are still living
in this mental
cage built by
Margaret Thatcher, yeah?
Yeah.
So the high taxation
for the rich is
bad, you know, the
private ownership
of everything is good, that kind of...
I mean, unfortunately,
I'm sure that they
are uncomfortable
with it, but
they haven't been
able to develop a
counter-narrative, yeah?
No, let's look
at some facts.
You know, in the
1960s and '70s, Britain
was one of the most
equal countries in
the world, you know?
People don't
often realise it.
The country was growing faster than what
it is... has been
growing in the last
30 years,
despite having,
you know, top income tax
rate of 80%, yeah?
Yeah.
In the US at the time, the
top income tax rate was
even higher, 90%, yeah?
But it was growing much faster
than what it is doing today, you know?
At least try to use those
historical facts
to develop some
counter-narrative,
you know?
But since they haven't developed
this counter-narrative
and basically
given up on the taxing
the rich taxing
wealth and so on
what do they do?
There's
only one way to
spend more which is
borrowing which that creates
the problem that you
just talked about.
Yeah, I th- I think it's,
I think it's kind of the
same thing which I said
before, which is like
a bit of an inability,
and I think maybe we kind
of teach this a little bit
in the way that we... the
way that we educate people
in university now. An
inability to step back and
look at the big picture.
And the big thing which
I often talk about was,
you know, and the reason
I started my channel was
at the beginning of COVID,
it was very clear that the
UK government and the US
government and basically
all Western governments
were going to give a
huge amount of money out.
And the UK deficit as
I said is £1 trillion,
and all wanted to know,
because my background is
distribution inequality,
who is going to get
that £1 trillion?
That's the only thing
I wanted to know.
Because you know, the
US number is, I think,
$13 trillion, you know,
huge numbers, you're
obviously going to change
the distribution here,
you're obviously going to
change the distribution
but I think it
was so amazing,
just nobody asked.
Nobody, and I
think we've...
I think personally, it
goes back, I honestly
think it goes back to
the way that we teach
our economic students.
This way that we just whip
them into do the maths,
do the maths, do the
maths, don't question the
model, don't think about
the big picture, and then
you reach a point where,
you know, we can give
out £1 trillion, the
Americans can give out
$13 trillion, and because
our models never question
distribution, nobody
even asks where it's
going to end up.
I think it's,
I think it's amazing.
Well this extra
money was
basically given to
banks and other
financial institutions,
which they refused
to give it to productive
enterprises that need this
money for investment,
to give to
ordinary consumers...
sorry, ordinary
citizens, yeah?
Yeah.
I mean, why couldn't they
do it with more
kind of taxation
you know I mean?
Okay, I mean if you think generally high
level of taxation
is not a good
thing, at least you can,
have emergency
taxations, yeah?
A lot of countries
did that, yeah?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
During wartime and
in the post-war
reconstruction, they
would kind of,
occasionally impose a special levy
of whatever percent on the rich people for
five years or whatever.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think it's
interesting you mention
wartime periods, because,
you know, we've... So the
channel has really been
growing and it's becoming
really popular, and
you know, this... this
argument of why are you
not taxing the rich is
growing and growing and
growing and growing. And
I think we actually
made some good progress,
because for a long time
we would get this kind
of economic pushbacks,
it's not good for
the economy, it's not
good for the economy.
There's no
evidence for that.
No, there's not
and, but increasingly
people are not
believing that
but the argument against
has kind of shifted
to this like, well,
it's not possible
you can't tax rich people
and this kind of
fatalistic, well,
things always get worse
you can't do anything.
But then if you look back
at especially the Second
World War in Europe,
in the West, there
was a massive decrease
in wealth inequality.
Oh, absolutely.
So it's obviously,
it's obviously doable.
Why... I don't know,
have you got anything
you can say about
whether it's possible, and
also why so many people
are so quick to say it's
impossible when we have
this historical example?
I think one reason
why it is more difficult
than before is that
downward spiral that we
have talked about, yeah?
Increasing inequality
feeding into
increasing
inequality of power
and democracy being
more and more
constrained.
Yeah, yeah.
So, that's one reason why I think
it is more difficult
to do that now than
Yeah.
it was possible
in the 1950s or '60s.
I think this is a really
good point because I
think people push back and
they say it's impossible
because you can't do it
technically, but the
Second World War proves
it's technically possible.
The truth is, what makes
it very, very difficult,
in my opinion, is that
control of the media
and the control of
politicians because
whenever I go
on TV or radio
to campaign for wealth
taxes, I'm always
doing it for free
and I'm self-funded.
And I'm up against
somebody who works
for a think tank
funded by billionaires.
And sometimes people...
if you wonder why
there's not more voices
like me in the media
because who funds it?
The billionaires are
actively paying for
people to go on TV
go on the radio and
say it's impossible
to tax the rich.
Who is paying
for people like me to
make the counterargument?
You know,
basically nobody.
So that shows you
really, the way they
block it is by fighting
that narrative battle.
And winning that narrative
Yeah, exactly, yeah, but
there you have, Nelson
Mandela once said, "It
always looks impossible
until it is done," yeah?
Yeah.
We can do it, we
have to do it.
We have to start
somewhere, yeah?
I mean,
okay, I mean
change the narrative,
maybe put
more pressure on your
politicians, yeah, and
do more mass
economic literacy
campaigns so that
more people know
about these things
like you are
doing in a very,
very effective way.
I mean, we have to
change this, yeah?
Yeah.
And it can be done.
Okay, maybe the 90% is too much, yeah?
But why should it
be 40% or 50%?
It could be the
60%, 70%, yeah?
And I always talk
about how it's not even
necessarily just about
what rates we tax income.
You know, we have
these very, very
wealthy families-
That's right, we have-
they don't pay income tax.
tax wealth, yeah.
Yeah, I think this
is the big thing.
They don't have
income in the-
Yeah, their
income is not
classed as income.
Exactly.
But, you know, they
do receive billions
of pounds in
their lifetime.
I think...
I think often what is,
what is often done is
when I say want to tax the
rich, my opponents try to
convince the public that
means you, that means you.
And they, they try
to ignore, you know,
there are families out
there with hundreds
of millions, billions
of pounds of wealth.
Their wealth is growing
and growing and growing
and they're
squeezing people out.
Yeah.
They're squeezing
people out.
This is the worry I have.
But, I think...
I look at the growth
of this narrative
the massive growth
and support for it.
I think we can win the
public battle for it, but
I think we need more
support from economists.
Which is why I'm always
glad to hear you're doing
the work you're doing.
And I'm hoping
we get more young people
going into economics
to push this...
push this narrative.
I think that, I
think that's really good.
I guess I would like to
end on just asking you,
I can often be a little
bit pessimistic and a
little bit depressing,
but I do this work
because I think we can
make things better.
So at these times
when living standards
are falling and we have
increased political
turbulence, what is
it that gives you
hope for our future
as a society and our
future as an economy?
Yeah, well, I, yeah, you
know, try to live by the
dictum of the Italian
Marxist philosopher
Antonio Gramsci who said
that we need the pessimism
of the intellect,
but optimism of
the will, yeah?
Yeah, so you have to
be realistic about
what can be achieved
at the moment.
Yeah.
You know, so that
makes you pessimistic
because debts
kind of stack
so much against the ordinary people, but
in the long run, you know,
the world has
changed hugely, yeah?
If changes
weren't impossible
you know, we'd be still
living in a society
with slaves and
most people are
you know, tied to
their land and do not have
any freedom to choose their profession.
You know, the women
will not be allowed
to vote, you know.
There'll be explicit racial
discrimination.
But these things
all have changed
because people have fought for it, yeah?
So if you take the perspective of 50
years, 100 years, yeah?
We can change
this, you know.
I think that's the
key thing is because
people fought for it.
Yeah.
Because people
fought for it.
Exactly.
I think we can.
I'm fighting for it.
I know you're
doing your bit.
Yeah, thank
you very much.
Thanks for coming
on the channel.
That's great for me.
Is there anything you
wanted to, you wanted
to bring up or anything
you want to speak about?
I mean, I'm very
honored to be
the first outside
speaker in your
great series.
Yeah, I mean, please
get other
speakers so that you
can diversify
your... I mean,
what you are doing
is great, but, you
know, we need
kind of different
people coming in too.
Yeah, I think we need-
Give, different
perspectives.
it's important for
us to have more
economists, I think.
Because this channel is
like, it's getting so
popular with the public,
but, you know, we have all
of these rich posh guys,
"Oh, no, I never work.
Oh, no, I never work."
And, you know, we live
in a very class-focused
society. And, I
think... I'm from a
working-class background,
and think one of the
reasons why the channel
is popular is because
the country's from a
working-class background.
They're happy
to hear that.
But the fact is,
the guys who control
the levers of power
they're normally
not from working-class
backgrounds.
Yeah, but there
are some kind of
good economists
working on these issues.
You know, get Piketty or Zucman, yeah?
Yeah, you know, I
think we'll reach out.
We'll reach out.
I think Piketty and
Zucman are great.
They're French economists
working in inequality.
But yeah, thank you
very much for coming on.
Ha-Joon has not
asked me to, to recommend
his books, but,
I think Ha-Joon
has a lot of books out.
His recent one is
Edible Economics, which
is here on the table.
He didn't ask me to do
this, honestly he didn't.
I think Ha-Joon
writes really well
economics in a way that
is enjoyable and relatable
to ordinary people.
So, if you're watching and
you find economics
inaccessible, and
you want... I obviously
haven't written any
books about economics,
like straight books
about economics, but
I think Ha-Joon's
books are really good.
And if you've
got questions for
Ha-Joon, send them in
and maybe we'll get
him on again someday.
But, yeah, basically,
thank you very much-
Thank you.
for coming on.
I really enjoyed
this time.
Great.
And, yeah, good
to see you again.
Thank you very much.
And thank you very
much for your support.
Keep watching, share
the videos with your
friends, with your mum.
It's all about
stopping the economy
from getting worse.
It's about taxing
wealth and not work.
Support us.
Thank you very much.