Welcome back to Gary's Economics.
Today we are going to talk about asset price inflation.
So the main thing I want to explain
today is the difference
between asset price inflation
and goods and services inflation,
which you might call shop price inflation and why it is important.
The first obvious thing to say
is the rate at which asset price increases
is not always the same as the rate
at which prices in the shops increase.
And in general, in the last 20, 30 years,
there's been a significant trend for assets
to increase more quickly than
goods and service prices, and also wages,
which has, of course, made housing less affordable.
The first thing you need to know
is in the main measures of inflation,
which you will see on the news.
The most well known one is CPI,
consumer price inflation.
But you might also see RPI, retail price inflation.
These measures of inflation
only look at the prices of goods in the shops,
the regular things that you buy
and also services, transport,
basically your regular expenditures,
but they do not look at asset prices.
So these measures of inflation
do not look at asset prices,
which means that these measures of inflation,
I would argue
they basically underestimate actual inflation
because I think house prices and other asset
prices are a part of inflation.
But these are only looking at prices in the shops
which are going up more slowly.
So the second thing is
in my opinion,
there is a structural tendency in our economy
for asset prices to go up more quickly
than shop prices.
And the reason for this is, in my opinion,
growing inequality.
Now, I have looked at this for a very, very long time.
This is actually what I wrote my thesis on at Oxford,
which is on my website if you want to look at it,
I'll put a link in the comments.
The reason for that is very simple.
So ordinary people
spend almost all of the income
they receive in their lifetime.
This means that over the course of their life,
everything they receive,
they spend on goods and services.
Rich people act very differently.
They spend the majority of their
income on buying assets.
The richer you are,
the greater percentage of your income
you are likely to spend on assets
and the lower percentage of your income
you're likely to spend on goods and services.
So as an economy becomes more wealth unequal,
what you then have is a greater share of the assets
and a greater share of the purchasing power
being held by the rich and the very rich,
and a smaller share of the assets
and the purchasing power being held by ordinary people.
Since ordinary people
like goods and services and rich people like assets,
as the economy becomes more and more equal,
the society as a whole will start to desire more assets
and desire less goods and services, which means that
asset prices tend to increase
relative to wages over time.
This makes housing increasingly unaffordable
over time in a way
that basically tends
to get often ignored by economists,
because economists focus only on
shop price inflation, CPI inflation.
So housing just gets more and more unaffordable
and basically nothing gets done about it.
The next thing you need to understand
is that central banks
such as the Bank of England here in the UK
or the Federal Reserve in the US,
they try to keep inflation at a 2% level,
but when they talk about inflation,
they are only looking at
shop price inflation, wage inflation.
They are not talking about inflation.
So basically the central bank,
not only is it doing
nothing to
stop housing from becoming more unaffordable,
in a sense it's exacerbating the problem
because while they
almost completely ignore rising
asset prices, rising house prices,
they are pretty much refusing to allow wages to rise
more than 2% or 2.5% a year.
So this creates a structural problem.
We have a system
in which
it is almost inevitable
that housing will become more expensive over time
and we are not allowing wages to rise.
So we can kind of see inevitably
this gap will increase.
But we have a double problem.
So as house prices go up and wages
don't go up as quickly,
there's only basically two ways to fix this problem.
One is more rapid increases in wages,
which the central banks won't allow,
and one is falls in house prices.
So if you have rapid falls in house prices,
which is what we would need
to make housing significantly more expensive,
this causes massive problems, essentially.
We see these kinds of collapses.
People buy houses with big mortgages.
So if your house price suddenly collapses,
you are basically immediately bankrupt
because you've bought a half million
pound house, you borrowed £450,000.
Now your house is worth only £300.
Your net worth is -150.
So people immediately become bankrupted
and it can cause massive economic problems.
So basically, we've created an unfixable problem.
We need wages to go up, central bank won’t allow it.
We need house prices to come down.
If house prices come down quickly,
it causes an economic collapse,
causes people to be bankrupted.
So the situation is essentially unfixable.
And I think the way that you fix
it is basically to understand that inflation is not one
single measure, right?
It's not just simply CPI.
What you have is three different things, essentially.
I think three different main categories of inflation
you want to look at, which is goods
and service inflation.
And within that we can divide luxury goods
and services and essential goods and services,
wage inflation and asset
inflation like house prices inflation.
Now, the kind of inflation
that we've had in the last four or five years
is basically the worst possible kind of inflation.
It's been driven
primarily by
goods and services,
especially basic essentials like food and energy.
Wages have lagged behind,
which means ordinary people's
living conditions have fallen,
and yet houses
have become extremely more expensive in that period.
So it is the worst possible
combination of inflation for ordinary people.
But it's probably worth bearing in mind
that it's a really good combination
for people who own assets and consume labour.
So if you're a very wealthy person,
you own a load of assets,
you own a lot of natural resources,
and what you do is you consume other people's labour,
then your situation is great
because the things you own have become more expensive
and the workers
who you might use to do your goods and...
to do your services have become cheaper.
In a sense, it's a kind of a
you could describe it as a class warfare
kind of inflation.
And we've kind of built that into the system
we have baked into our system
a kind of inflation where assets,
which is a measure of the power of the rich, continue
to become more expensive,
whereas wages,
which is a measure of the power of ordinary people,
are basically not allowed to go up by the central bank.
I think it should be obvious
the best way to fix
the housing crisis is to stabilise
house prices and encourage specifically wage inflation.
Now, there is no other way to make housing affordable.
And I would encourage economists to think about this.
It's the only way to fix it, really.
You need to get wages to go up.
I think the best way to make wages
go up and house prices not go up
is to move that spending power back.
Ordinary people buy goods and services.
You as a worker, produce goods and services.
If you get money into the hands of ordinary people,
they will buy the stuff you produce
and your wages will go up.
If instead we put all the money
in the hands of the rich.
They will buy assets. They will buy your houses.
Housing will become more expensive
and they will become stronger.
You will become weaker and you will lose your house.
So that's it, basically.
To conclude, there's not just one measure of inflation.
Asset inflation is very important,
the kind of inflation on the news
only ever looks at goods and services
and wage inflation is important as well.
Secondly, not all kinds of inflation are bad
If your wages are going up
faster than the price of goods and services
and faster than the price of housing,
your life will get better.
If housing and goods and services
are going up faster than the price of your wages,
your life will get worse.
I want your life to get better.
So let's ask for higher wages
and let's not accept the myth
in the media that if your wages go up, it's bad.
Pretty obviously your wage going up is good,
especially if they're going up faster than house
prices and goods and services.
And the way to do that
is to take purchasing power away from the rich,
put it in the hands of ordinary people.
And the way to achieve that is to tax the rich more
and to tax you and ordinary working people less.
We campaign for that on this channel every week.
Send the video to your friends,
send the video to your Mum.
Thanks for your support. Take care.