Okay. Welcome back to Gary's Economics.
Today we are going to talk about meritocracy.
Okay.
So today
we're gonna respond
to one of the biggest criticisms
we get for our campaign to tax wealth more,
which is that's not fair.
That's not meritocratic.
You want to go after people who've worked really hard
their whole lives to make money,
and you want to tax them more.
That's not capitalism, that's not meritocracy.
So we're going to address this head on.
First things first,
I've said it a million times on the channel.
I'll say it again.
We are not campaigning to tax working people.
We are campaigning to tax
individuals and families who have hoarded
enormous amounts of wealth, £10 million or more.
Secondly, let's talk about meritocracy in society
that we live in today.
So I am talking to you here from London.
I grew up in East London in quite a poor community.
I went to a grammar school,
so I know some richer people.
And then I went to a very fancy university.
So I know some much richer people.
And then I work in the City,
so I know so much richer people still,
most of my friends from poorer
backgrounds are working really, really hard.
I know a few of them who are earning
much, much higher than average salary.
They went to some of the top
universities in the country.
They're making 60, 70, 80 grand a year.
They're sleeping on their mum's sofas,
and they're saving up every single penny
they can to buy a house.
And they can't buy a house because house prices
go up faster than their savings.
At the same time,
I know people from richer families who don't work,
who own houses
because their parents gave them £700 grand tax free.
Is that meritocracy?
This is a question I want to ask you.
Let's look at what's happening
in our society at the moment.
House prices are rising very, very, very, very quickly.
if you've been watching this channel for a long time,
you’ll know I'm a firm believer
that wealth inequality drives asset prices up.
If you don't understand why that is, I would recommend
that you watch our recent video, part
two of our online course,
What is wealth inequality
and how does it affect the economy?
If you give all the money to rich people,
they will try and buy all the assets
and that will drive asset prices up.
What that means is ordinary
people can no longer afford assets.
We increasingly live in a society
where whether you are able
to have things like a comfortable family
or have things like home ownership
are basically nothing to do with how smart you are,
how hard you work, what job you have,
what university you went to
and are increasingly just a faction
of how rich your parents are.
Listen, we do not live in a meritocracy.
Nothing could be more obvious.
I think one problem we have is that...
So I'm 37, and my parents
generation lived in a much less unequal
and much more meritocratic society.
They lived in a world
where if you worked hard, you could save up some money,
you could buy property,
and you could reach some level of wealth.
That is not really true anymore.
Younger people are increasingly seeing that it's
basically impossible to get rich
unless you are from money.
Listen,
wealth exists in our society,
and there are basically two ways
in which wealth can be distributed.
One is through work.
People who do more valuable work, more high paid work
get the assets, they get the wealth,
and they become rich.
The other is basically through aristocracy
and inheritance, where people who are born
which die rich, and people who are born poor, die poor.
We can't really exist in a system where ordinary,
hardworking people from poor families like myself
pay 50 or 60% tax if they make money.
People from extremely wealthy families,
like the Duke of Westminster,
can inherit billions of pounds and pay nothing.
This is not a meritocracy.
I'm pushing for a meritocratic society.
What I want is an economy
where very rich people pay
their fair share of tax
instead of all of the tax burden
landing on ordinary working
people like you or your kids.
I want a meritocracy.
I want people who work hard to make money.
Unequal societies are not meritocracy.
They are societies in which people from rich families
get all the assets.
If you want meritocracy,
you should tax the rich rather than working people.
So that's my answer. How do you get meritocracy?
You tax the rich.
That way
we can get the assets to ordinary working people
rather than just the people with rich dads.
That is a meritocratic society.
Support us, support the channel. Thank you very much.