Welcome back to Gary’s Economics.
Today we are going to talk about why growth is stupid.
Okay, this is a thing
which I've been thinking about for a while.
And, it was prompted this week by an article
which I read in the New Yorker,
a good long article about British economics,
by a guy with Sam Knight
where he talks
about basically the collapse of the British economy,
the collapse of British politics.
A lot of people are looking at us saying,
what's going on in Britain. It's falling apart.
And he interviewed a guy called Mark Carney,
who is a former governor of the Bank of England.
He was a governor of the Bank of England back
when I was a trader.
And Mark Carney
had this very pithy way
of describing the British economy
and the British economic problem.
And I've got the exact quote here.
What he said was, it's just not that productive
an economy anymore.
This is Mark Carney, former
head of the Bank of England.
The problem with Britain is that it
is just not that productive an economy.
And we hear these kinds of arguments
all the time on the news,
from the Conservative Party, sometimes
even the Labour Party.
The problem with Britain is
we're just not productive enough.
We as Britain's have a fundamental problem,
our productivity is lacking,
we're sort of fundamentally weak,
we need to fix productivity.
And
I have a problem with this way
of describing the economy.
First of all, I'm not against productivity.
I'm not against economic growth.
I think these things are all good things.
If fundamentally the biggest problem was a lack of UK
productivity,
number one, what we'd be seeing is living
standards falling specifically in the UK.
And I think a lot of people who live in the UK
feel that what we have is a specific UK problem.
It's very important to recognise
living standards are falling for middle
classes all across the world, all across the world.
So this YouTube
channel is watched all across the world.
We've got a lot of viewers
in America, in Australia and places like Germany,
the Netherlands.
We get messages all the time saying
living standards are collapsing here
in the US, in Germany, it's
definitely happening in places
like Italy and Spain, even a country like Australia,
which is generally considered to have
strong living standards,
a good place to live, living
standards are falling there.
So if the problem was specifically UK productivity,
and I'm not saying
we don't have a problem with productivity,
if that was the main problem,
why are living standards
collapsing all across the world?
The second thing is to say,
if the problem was a lack of growth in productivity,
and I'm not saying
we don't have a lack of growth in productivity,
why are living standards falling?
So in the last five years specifically,
we have seen really a collapse
in the living standards of the average British family.
This has happened at the same time
as enormous growth in inequality.
We've reached a situation now when,
you know, about half of the families
in the country
struggle to simultaneously feed their kids
and turn the heating on in the winter.
And this has not coincided
with the collapse in British productivity.
Yeah, we can argue that a stagnation
in British productivity,
but productivity is not collapsing
and yet living standards are collapsing.
So again, we have a second disconnected.
The third thing, and I think
the most important disconnect is
if the fundamental problem
in the British economy
or even the global economy is a lack of productivity,
why is wealth of the richest people in the country,
the richest people in the world,
millionaires and billionaires,
why are these people's wealth
exploding through the ceiling?
So I'm sitting here now.
We're filming this at the beginning of April.
In the last couple of weeks,
we have seen
almost every single stock market in the entire world,
hit a new record all time high.
Does that sound like a world
which has a problem of fundamental productivity growth?
So we saw
another piece of news that came out yesterday
was that the world
gains 141 new billionaires
last year, and an amazing year for rich people.
I always remember
in the middle of the depths
of the cost of living crisis,
the Financial Times ran an article
and the headline was ‘Will
the boom in luxury goods ever stop?’
That was the article.
You know, we saw in the first year of Covid,
the largest and fastest ever increasing wealth
of the richest people in the country.
We saw the average US billionaire double their wealth
in a single year.
The average UK billionaire made £630 million
Does this sound to you
like a country and a world
where the fundamental problem is productivity growth?
And I'll keep saying I'm
not against productivity growth, productivity is great.
If you live in a country and a world
where living standards of ordinary people
are collapsing
and living standards of the richest
are exploding through the roof,
stock markets are exploding to new all time highs.
The gold price hit a massive
new all time high yesterday.
Do you really think the problem is productivity growth?
Do you not think there might be a deeper problem
with inequality?
So I think we need to look a little bit closer
at who this guy Mark Carney is right.
So Mark Carney as I've said,
was former head of the Bank of England.
He's actually a Canadian, he's not British.
Before that he was head of the Bank of Canada,
and before that he was a very well paid banker
for Goldman Sachs.
So what you have here is a very wealthy man
who has been very well paid throughout his career.
I'm sure him and his family are all very rich.
They are part of a class of very wealthy
people who are getting richer
very rapidly, who’s living standards are increasing
very rapidly.
Turning around to you and saying
the problem is productivity.
You guys are just not productive enough.
And I think what we have here
is one single example of a much broader problem,
which is that economists and politicians who
very often are very rich,
live in an economy which is
seeing lifestyles of the very rich get
fantastically better.
Seeing the wealth of the very rich explode very quickly
while your living standards collapse,
turning around to you and saying
the problem is your productivity.
And let's unwrap
a little bit what productivity is,
because I think productivity
sounds like a very moralistic term.
Productivity is basically GDP per worker,
or sometimes it's GDP per hour worked.
So essentially,
unless, you know,
people are working rapidly more hours,
which in the UK they are,
essentially it comes down to GDP growth.
And these guys are basically saying
the reason you're poor
is because GDP growth is not high enough.
And first to say GDP is not falling.
GDP of the UK
now is higher than it was before Covid,
GDP of almost every Western country is higher
now than it was before Covid.
GDP is enormously higher than it was 30,
40, 50 years ago
when people like my dad, possibly
your dad were able to work regular jobs and buy houses.
GDP goes up and up and up and up and up.
The wealth of the richest goes up and up and up.
Living standards for the rich go up and up and up.
Ordinary people are really getting poorer very rapidly.
And wealthy men like Mark Carney
turn around and say it's
because your productivity is not good enough.
We had a very similar example where Andrew Bailey,
who is the current governor of the Bank of England,
said that inflation is your fault
for asking for high wages
and Andrew Bailey is paid £500,000 a year.
We have an increasing problem of economists
trying to tell you
that it's your fault
and in many cases even saying it's not happening.
There was a conservative politician on TV
just last week
saying that
living standards are better than they've ever been.
It's very, very important
that people like you understand inequality is growing
and inequality is growing very quickly.
And when inequality grows quickly,
living standards for the rich increase
and living standards for the poor fall.
Economists have a fundamental blindspot
about inequality.
What they are obsessed about is growth.
And they will always be obsessed about growth,
and they will always tell you
that growth is the problem
and lack of productivity is the problem.
In my opinion,
and I've got lots of videos
where I hope I’ll convince you,
we have a fundamental problem of growing inequality.
And what I see is a sick economy
which has a growing cancer of inequality.
Going to the doctor and the doctor
saying, listen, don't worry about your cancer.
Grow your way out of it.
Listen, we grow year after year
and living standards fall
and it's not going to work.
And growth is great,
but I think it has become basically
a mantra, basically
a prayer of our intellectual classes,
which is don't worry about anything else, just grow.
Just grow.
And I think it's basically reached the point
where growth has become essentially a codeword
from the very rich, which is I'm an idiot.
I don't understand this problem.
I have no real solutions, but just f**king grow
with no plan.
We're in this absolutely absurd
situation in this country where
we have a conservative government
whose plan is just grow,
whilst absolutely starving
people and government of the funds
they need to provide any sort of growth.
We have a Labour government are going to come in
and their plan is we're going to grow the economy
without doing any investment,
without putting any money in your pockets.
I think growth has become
such a meaningless word that it's just something
economists and politicians scream
about with no real plan.
I would like you
to turn around to these economists
and these politicians and ask them with what money?
What money do you want us to grow with?
If we have no money to go out
to our shops, to our high streets, and to spend,
then where is the economic growth going to come from?
And if the problem is a lack of growth,
then why do the wealths
of the richest people in our country
and the richest people of the world
keep growing more and more?
So
I would like to leave you with a message
that growth in our modern age,
as much it would be wonderful,
has become basically a signal of stupidity.
People with no plans, people with no understanding of
the problem of growing inequality,
are insisting that the problem
is our lack of economic growth.
we won't go anywhere good
when all the money goes to the rich
and nothing goes to anybody else.
People like Mark Carney, people like Andrew Bailey,
people like our very wealthy politicians,
they're not going to do anything about it.
It has to be you. It has to be me.
We have to scream at these politicians and say,
the problem is not economic growth.
The problem is growth of inequality of wealth.
If you don't fix it,
our living standards will collapse.
So I’ll keep making videos about it,
if you keep talking about it.
It's not growth,
it's not Mark Carney, it’s inequality stupid.
We have to fix it. Thank you.