[Ian] This is LBC from Global, leading Britain's
conversation with Ian Payne.
Good evening, it's Ian Payne sitting in
for Tom Swarbrick, who's sitting in for breakfast
all this week. Now, a coalition of some of
the world's wealthiest people have
signed an open letter urging governments
to tax them
more, to pay for the coronavirus crisis.
I will repeat that. They have asked
governments to tax them more heavily,
to pay for the coronavirus. Some 83
millionaires
from the US, UK, Germany, New Zealand,
Canada and the Netherlands
signed a letter organised by
Millionaires for Humanity. Let me read
you a crucial quote.
"To our fellow global citizens," they write,
"as COVID-19 strikes the world,
millionaires like us have a critical
role to play in healing the world.
No, we are not the ones caring for the
sick in intensive care wards.
We are not driving the ambulances that
will bring the ill to hospitals.
We are not restocking grocery store
shelves or delivering food door-to-door.
But we do have money,
lots of it. Money that is desperately
needed now and will continue to be
needed in the years ahead,
as our world recovers from this crisis.
Today,
we the undersigned millionaires ask our
governments to raise taxes on people
like us.
Immediately. Substantially. Permanently."
We thought this was a very
interesting story. One of the 83 is
a man called Gary Stevenson. He's an
economist, he used to work in the City
as a trader, and he retired at the age of
27,
having become a multi-millionaire. Gary
is one of four
British millionaires who've added their
name to the group. I rang him earlier
tonight,
started by asking him where the idea for
this letter came from.
[Gary] This letter originates in the US, from a
group called
Patriotic Millionaires. Obviously you can
probably tell I'm not from the US.
I'm from London, I live in London. I
was connected by a group called Tax
Justice UK.
So I've been basically looking around
the area
of tax reform ever since I quit the
City a few years ago,
and I've been attached to this
organisation, Tax Justice UK.
I did a big article in the Guardian a
couple of months ago saying how I think
there's going to be a lot of inequality
resulting from coronavirus, and the best
way to fix it will be
a wealth tax, and that organisation
got in touch with Tax Justice UK, they put
them in touch with me.
[Ian] Why will a wealth tax, in your opinion,
help various economies?
[Gary] So I think the big problem that we're
going to have in this economy
going forward, well, there's a couple of
things. The first thing is
we need to get spending in the economy,
and I think it's going to be very
difficult to get that
if the ordinary workers are struggling,
and I think we're going to see that
definitely going forward. This furlough
scheme ends
this month in terms of the first time
companies have to make payments.
A lot of people are going to lose their
jobs. At the same time,
we can see lots of data that high-income
people have accumulated a lot of money
during this crisis.
But if confidence is low, the chances are
that money is going to be
saved, it's going to be put into assets
like housing, like stocks.
We've already seen stocks go up hugely,
they've gone up about
40 or 50% in the last few months.
I'm expecting to see house prices go up
more.
If that's the situation that we're in,
then a lot of ordinary working people,
which are the
driving force of the economy and the
people we need spending, are going to be
struggling.
So if we don't find some way to get
demand and spending power
from the richest in our society, I think
we're going to really struggle to get
out of this crisis.
[Ian] I'm a bit confused. You say stocks have
gone up 30,
40%. Every index I look at, it sort
of fluctuates every day.
It's certainly down since March.
Where are those stocks that are so
wonderful coming from?
[Gary] Yeah, the UK market is still pretty much
down since pre-COVID levels.
If you look at the US market, they're
already
above the levels, I think, at the turn of
the year. Some of the tech stocks, such as
the NASDAQ, are flying.
I personally invested in gold, and gold
is up
hugely. Yeah, they're still down on
pre-crisis levels, but
I traded in the 2008 crisis, and at this
stage in that crisis,
stocks were enormously down. We've seen a
phenomenal bounce back
since the bottoming of the stock market,
much faster than anything we saw in 2008,
and I'm predicting that will go up a
lot more,
very quickly, even in spite of a weak
economy. And that's a result of the huge
amount of money printing that's
happening at the Bank of England.
[Ian] Do you believe that every rich person,
say in the UK, would agree with you
and would like to be taxed more?
[Gary] I think it's very, very unlikely, to be
honest. You know, I'm sure you'd find a lot of
opposition.
[Ian] So your view is that if the
wealthiest get taxed,
then that will be distributed. Is that
trickle-down economics? What is that
called?
[Gary] Well, you could call it demand-side
economics. I mean, I think,
absolutely, talk a little bit about the
economic situation as it has been since
2008. Okay,
interest rates have been zero in this
country,
pretty much every country, almost
constantly since 2008.
And the reason that that has happened is
because the central banks
are desperately trying to get people
spending, and it's just failed year after
year after year.
And most economists expected that
these very low interest rates would get people
spending,
but it hasn't happened. And my belief, the
reason why that hasn't happened,
is because most of that money is ending
up going to very rich people,
who don't tend to spend extra money they
get.
And, you know, I don't come from a rich
background. I was
poor. Now I'm not poor. I know people
all through the spectrum. Rich people
don't spend
money when it's given to them in the same
way that normal people do.
So if inequality increases, you're going
to struggle
to get demand and get consumer spending.
[Ian] I'm fascinated by your story. I read that
Guardian article that you were referring
to. I mean,
the very first line caught my attention:
"I made my first
million the year Greece went under. I was
24 years old at the time."
You were basically betting on gloom, were
you?
[Gary] Yeah, pretty much, yeah. So I started
working in the
City in 2008.
[Ian] So how old were you then?
[Gary] Yeah, in 2008 I was 21 when I first started.
Okay, and obviously that was when the
crisis happened,
and really my job was to predict
interest rates. So,
just a quick explanation: the central
bank pushes interest rates down when
they think the economy is weak and they
want people to spend,
and they bring interest rates up when
they think the economy is hot, they want
people to save.
So in 2008, interest rates collapsed
massively,
hugely. So previously they would move
rates like four and a quarter to four
and a half.
Here they fell from five and a half all
the way to zero, and everyone expected
we'd see a big surge in spending.
So everyone predicted in 2009 we'd have
a recovery. It didn't happen.
In 2009, everyone predicted it would be
2010. That didn't happen.
In 2010, it was it would be 2011. And by
then I started to become suspicious and
started to really question these ideas
of why
is the spending not happening? What do we
need to do to get the spending happening?
And we had this big meeting with the
senior guys at the bank where they
explained basically the financial
situation of all of the governments in
Europe, US, Japan, most of the major
governments in the world.
Big deficits, big debts. I mean, that's
very reminiscent of the situation now.
And I couldn't help but realise, you
know,
people I knew back home, in a similar
situation,
they're running losses month to month
and they've got debts.
If the governments are in debt and the
people are in debt, it can only mean
there's a small group of people
who have a huge amount. And if you need
to get the economy spending, which is
what central banks have been trying to
do now for
12 years, you can only get that spending
from the rich.
So I bet that, because I couldn't see
inequality improving,
I went back and I bet that this is not a
temporary crisis, a permanent crisis. And
that's what I believe.
[Ian] So we could
all become millionaires if we bet
on interest rates
staying low because this economic
situation is as bad as I can remember in
my lifetime.
[Gary] Well, that's a good question. You would
have been able to do that in 2009,
2010, 2011, 2012, '13, '14, '15,
'16, '17, or even the beginning of this year.
You would have made loads of money
betting on that.
Oh no, unfortunately, at the moment pretty
much everyone in the world
thinks interest rates will be low
forever, which is not a great
sign for the future of the economy. I
mean, we can look now at, for example, the
interest rate you would get
on 30-year bonds at the moment.
What interest do you think you'll get
on a 30-year UK bond?
[Ian] Oh, don't ask me, for goodness' sake, Gary.
I've no idea.
[Gary] It's
just over half of one percent, which
basically means they think rates will
stay zero for the next
20 to 30 years. So that is the realistic
situation. So I've been saying
for the last 12 years, rates will be zero
forever, we're not going to come out of
this crisis unless we address inequality.
And finally the world's come around
to my point of view,
which is probably not a great thing,
unfortunately.
[Ian] When you say you multi-
millionaires want to be taxed more, I
mean, what sort of percentage rate are we
talking about?
As I remember, in the '70s, you know, people
moving overseas because
here they were being taxed. I mean, I
think Heath was taxing people over 90%
who earned as much as you.
[Gary] So for me, the big thing here is, and I'd
like to point out,
the different signatures on this letter
will have different opinions. For me and
my background in economics, what I think
the big thing is, we need to start
looking at ways to tax wealth,
rather than just income, because at the
moment we have a situation where the
richest in society
are able to pay very, very low taxes
because they don't get their income from
work, like the rest of us do. Yeah, and the
current tax system is not really set
up to tax very well this non-work income.
Yeah, so you end up with a situation
where, you know, I made a lot of money but
I paid 50% on that. And I'm comfortable now, but I'm
a lot less rich than, you know, some of
these Barons of Westminster, who
are billionaires and have paid nothing.
So we really need to develop a tax
system that taxes
this accumulated wealth of the very rich.
Personally, I don't want to be going
after doctors and
lawyers and radio presenters. I'd rather
be going for the
very, very wealthy. And to be honest,
I think if you don't do that,
I think we're going to be in a very, very
bad situation.
[Ian] Okay. And the question I've
always wanted to ask somebody with a lot
of money is, what do you do all day?
You've retired.
[Gary] At the moment, I
write articles trying to explain to
people the importance of wealth
inequality. I've actually
been putting a video together this
last week and that will go on my
YouTube, Gary's Economics,
tonight. Okay, that's explaining how the
coronavirus is increasing inequality.
We're going through the cash flows very
simply,
just to explain that. So yeah, I'm
working on videos, I'm working on ways of
spreading this message,
that wealth inequality is very damaging
to the economy.
I don't need to do that, I don't get
paid to do that. But the truth
is,
I make my money by betting on what's
going to happen. I've done very, very well.
I think I'm a good economist.
I think I know what's happening here. I
think that unless you fix inequality,
things are going to be really, really bad
for my family,
my friends, for all the normal working
people in this country.
So yeah, I'm coming on radio shows
like this and
trying to spread the word.
[Ian] So that was economist Gary Stevenson speaking to me
earlier, one of 83 very wealthy people
who formed a group called Millionaires
for Humanity,
calling for themselves to be taxed more.