[Tom] Eight minutes past ten. Gary Stevenson is
an economist who focuses on inequality,
a former trader who retired from the
City as a multi-millionaire,
aged 27, after correctly predicting that
the 2008 financial crash
would happen. Mr Stevenson, thank you for
joining the programme tonight.
[Gary] Thanks for having me, Tom.
[Tom] Who's going to pay for all of this?
[Gary] Well, you said a very interesting thing
in your introduction, which was that
we're breaking all the rules this time,
and I think that really
sums up quite well, because what is
happening right now with
government borrowing is very, very
different from what normally happens
with government borrowing.
Now normally, when the government needs
money, it goes out and borrows from wealthy
investors,
pension funds, maybe foreign governments.
This time, that's not happening.
All the money that the government has
borrowed to deal with the COVID crisis
so far
has been borrowed from the Bank of
England. And the Bank of England, as you
know,
is essentially a government institution,
an independent one,
but it is one. The Bank of England has
got this money by printing it.
And that's what's taking a bit of time to
think about here.
You know, this is literally quantitative
easing, right? We're just
printing the cash to keep the cash coming.
[Tom] Yeah, exactly. The Bank of England...
but the Bank of England is printing money,
just like it did after 2008, but this
time the amount of money the Bank of
England is printing
is pretty much exactly the same as the
amount of money the government is
spending.
Which means essentially all of this
money is coming from
government printing. Now, that puts us in
a very interesting situation.
[Gary] It is, as you say, breaking all the rules.
When you start funding with printed
money,
it really raises the question:
do you pay it back?
[Tom] Yep.
[Gary] Because the government here is...
it's printing the money.
It's borrowing it from the Bank of
England, but the Bank of England is
printing it.
And in the past, whenever we've seen
governments do this, the money does not
get paid back.
And interestingly, the money does not
have to be paid back, because the money
is being borrowed from another branch of
government.
You don't have to pay any interest on it,
and in all the time this has been done
in the past,
we've been doing it for more than ten
years now, many countries have.
When it has come to maturity, the central
bank has said, "Okay, have another ten
years," and they've continued to allow
it to be extended. So, you know,
really, what is a debt if you don't have
to pay any interest and you never have
to pay it back?
[Tom] So, yes, it depends, I guess, what
proportion of the amount that we are
borrowing, at nearly a billion quid a
day,
is being done through the printing of
money by the Bank of England. Because
the country does borrow, and it's a
question that a lot of people, I think,
ask perfectly legitimately when we talk
about government borrowing.
Who are they going to borrow the
money from? Who do they ring up to say,
"Okay, can you put the money in my account
by Thursday?" You know, the £258 billion
that are being borrowed.
And it's normally, as you say, pension
funds and other nations.
But this time you say that's not
happening, it's coming from a different
source. And the source...
[Gary] Yeah, this time it's... yeah, it really
matches really well. The amount of
money the government's borrowing
in this crisis, the amount of money it's
spending, its deficit spending, to help
deal with COVID,
is almost exactly the same as the amount
of money that the central bank is
printing, which in this case I think is
£300 billion. An enormous amount of money.
I think that works out something like
£5,000 per person in the country.
Huge amount of money. So it's being
printed by the central bank, which is
essentially part of the government.
What that means is it will not be paid
back. Yeah, I used to work in financial
markets, I still talk to people in
financial markets. Everyone in financial
markets knows that money is not being
paid back.
Really, which raises the question: why
don't governments do this all the time?
[Tom] So, hang on a second. So, Gary,
you're saying that the people that
you're speaking to,
the... you're now presumably retired from
at the age of 30 — my God, I need to
ask you about that in a minute —
but that all the finance guys down in
the City, they're all saying to
you, "Gary, this is never going to be
paid off." This is just not going to
happen?
[Gary] Yeah. They stopped looking at
government debt. What they look at now is
government debt
minus the amount borrowed from the
central bank, because nobody ever expects
that to be paid back.
Which raises the question: what is going
to happen?
[Tom] Yeah, what are the consequences of it?
[Gary] Yeah, quite. And I think really the
interesting question is what does that
mean, because,
like you say, we're breaking all the
rules here. We're doing huge amounts of
deficit spending funded by printed money,
and we really need to ask... I mean, the
question which people are asking, "How do
you pay it back?" — that's the wrong
question.
The question is: what are the
consequences of printing such huge
amounts of money to fund a government
deficit? That is the question we need to
ask.
[Tom] And what would be your answer?
[Gary] Well, you need to look at what happens to
the money. You know, the reason
governments don't normally do this is
because it leads to a huge increase in
the money supply,
and that has an effect on the economy. So
in this crisis, what's happened is, you
know, a lot of
ordinary people have lost their income,
they've lost their jobs and they're
losing money. But if you
look at richer people, those people have
often kept their incomes, and their
spending has collapsed.
So if you actually look at the amount of
money being saved by higher-income
people and richer people,
it's gone through the roof. So richer
people are accumulating a lot of money in
their bank accounts as a result of this
policy.
So when we talk about going back to
normal after COVID, we're not going to be
going back to normal. No, we're going to
be going back to a normal where the
richest people in the country have
massive bank accounts
full of a lot of cash.
[Tom] And, Gary, to ask, what does that do?
And, Gary, the
difference too, which I'm sort of still
trying to get my head around again, being
an absolute dunce on this stuff,
the difference between what you see in
the stock market — and the stock market
prices did...
I mean, in America, the stock market
there, it's like nothing happened, I mean
it's just carrying on
normal. House prices — you look at house
prices, we're expecting... someone was
saying the banks were predicting an 18%
drop in house prices — they're carrying
on, just chugging along, ticking over.
That the asset economy seems to be
carrying on as normal. The real economy —
bricks and mortar shops on the high
street, people's jobs —
is falling apart. Why is that?
[Gary] Yeah, oh, that is exactly right, and it's
exactly because of what we just said
here. The government has printed huge
amounts of money,
and that has ended up in the bank
accounts of wealthier people.
Now, you know, I come from an ordinary
background, but I work with a lot of
wealthy people from the UK, from the US.
If you give wealthy people a lot of
money, they're going to invest it.
Yeah, and in the US, they're often in
stocks and shares. In this country,
that means... yeah, you can go back and
look at my... right at the beginning of
the crisis, a lot of people were
predicting a fall.
I was predicting a rise, and I was buying
everything, because if you give rich
people a load of money,
they will buy things. If you look at
2008, everybody thought prices would
crash, but in the end,
London house prices doubled, and that was
because of huge amounts of money
printing going to richer people.
That will happen again here. That is the
real cost.
[Tom] Let me talk about who's going to pay for
the crisis. What happens if London house
prices double again? What happens though,
Gary?
[Gary] It's so interesting. The house price
thing is really interesting. What happens
if there is an inflationary shock? If
inflation is at 0.5%, it's gone up but
it's still only at 0.5%. If you just
print money,
you get to some examples like, you know,
everyone knows the pictures of the
wheelbarrows of cash being run around
Europe in the 1930s.
[Tom] So if there's an inflationary shock,
we're screwed?
[Gary] With this amount of cash flying around,
whether you're screwed or not depends on
who you are.
If you're one of the people who's sitting
with a bank account full of cash now,
which a lot of the richer people in this
country are,
then that's just fine for you. My worry
is what happens to the ordinary people
when prices go up. What happens to
ordinary people if house prices double?
You know, it's hard enough for
some ordinary families to get houses in
this city, right? If they double again,
you're telling, like,
two-thirds of the kids, "You're never
going to get one." So really,
if you're talking about how do we deal
with this crisis, who's going to pay it
back, it's going to be the poorer kids,
because the richer
guys, those guys are loaded, they're
making a fortune on this.
So really, it's a problem of inequality
and distribution. That is the problem.
So actually, the way in which you pay
this back... as you say, it's the wrong
question that's being asked, because it's
not the...
the debt that we're borrowing to fund
the COVID response, we're never going to
pay that back.
That's fine, we'll write that off. What
needs to happen is the payback to
deal with the inequality that is about
to come. Because, as you say, all the
rich people sit there getting richer,
buying their houses,
you know, trading off property — property
guys — and the poorer people whose
real economy has been decimated by this,
they're left with nothing because they
don't have any assets.
[Tom] Exactly.
[Gary] Exactly. That is a big question. The
media is asking, "How do you pay the debt
back?"
That's the wrong question. Everybody in
finance knows the debt doesn't get paid
back. The real question is: what's going
to happen to the money?
That's going to rich people. It's going
to push asset prices up. It is going to
cause a crisis in home affordability and
inequality.
So really, the problem we're going to
have coming out of this is: how do we
deal with that massive rising inequality
and the impossibility of getting housing
for ordinary people?
[Tom] And just a word on, because I'm getting
lots of people texting and saying,
"Inflation, inflation, inflation."
How do you keep inflation low enough so
that you don't
have wheelbarrows full of cash being
wheeled around?
[Gary] There's two different kinds of
inflation, which is inflation out on the
streets
and inflation in asset prices. After 2008,
we didn't see much inflation in shops.
We didn't see... but we saw a huge amount
of inflation eventually in assets. So the
thing that's happening here is loads and
loads of people are losing their jobs,
and when people lose their jobs, that
makes the job market really, really weak,
and people don't get pay rises.
As long as pay rises aren't happening,
then you don't get much inflation.
So that's the reason why after 2008 we
didn't see inflation. Now, I'm not saying
necessarily that's going to happen again.
The amount of money being printed here,
it's... well, it's much quicker,
definitely, than it was in 2008. There is
a risk that we lose control of it and
inflation does increase,
especially once COVID passes and, like
we've said, all of these people with huge
amounts of cash in their bank start
trying to spend it. That is definitely a
possibility.
I think, if you remember, after 2008,
2010, 2011, we did have quite high
inflation, five percent...
[Tom] Yeah, coming up to six percent.
[Gary] That's right. And then
the Bank of England, rather sensibly I
suspect, decided to leave the money out
there, not take any money back.
Leave the easy money. The Bank of England,
if it happens, you know, if it's five,
six percent, which,
you know, I don't want to make any exact
predictions, but it could be at some
point coming out of this,
I think the bank will allow it to
continue, but what that will cause is a
cost-of-living crisis for ordinary
people, just like it did after 2008.
[Tom] Gary, you've been fascinating talking to
you. I'm already incredibly late for the
bits I need to hit on the programme.
I've got to ask you, what's it like to
be 27 with multiple millions in the bank
account?
[Gary] Well, it's unusual. Like I said, I
didn't grow up with money,
and I made the money very quickly, and it
all came very quickly to me.
[Tom] Okay, well, let me ask you this, it's
very funny, you're gonna have to be
really brief, Gary. I am
obsessed with this idea, right? So there
you are, it doesn't matter what age you
are, who you are,
there is a moment in your life where you
suddenly realise you've got more money
than you ever possibly could have dreamt
of,
that it's there for you, and your whole
world has just shifted on its axis
because you've got this money in your
bank account,
and it's for you. When was that moment
for you?
[Gary] For me, when was that? Well, that was
when I got my first bonus and I realised I
should have spent my whole childhood
buying Boots meal deals. Yeah, that was
it. But before I go, I'd just like to
suggest that if anyone
wants to know more about the effects of
money printing, there is a really good
video on my YouTube, Gary's Economics,
explaining exactly how it works.
[Tom] Great, man. Gary Stevenson, thank you for
your time. An economist focusing on
inequality, former trader, retired from
the City. Multi-millionaire, aged 27.