[Michael] Are you confused? Don't worry if you are,
because I have Gary Stevenson,
former city trader, now inequality
economist, on the show to explain it all.
Gary, thank you so much for joining us.
[Gary] Hi, Michael. Thanks for having me.
[Michael] So, to start, now, you know, you're talking to
someone with not a great deal of
knowledge about the stock market. And so
what I know about, you know, hedge funds,
they normally gamble on the stock market,
sometimes they win money, sometimes they
lose.
The same goes for retail investors, they...
lots of ordinary people
bet on the stock market, sometimes they
win, sometimes they lose.
You know, on one level, that's just
what's happening
here. So what's special about
what's been going on with GameStop
this week?
[Gary] Well, I mean, the reason it's all over the
news, the scale of what's happened
this week is phenomenal, right? Like you
said, it's gone seventeen
hundred
percent in about two weeks. That's,
you know, it increases 17 times.
The speed and the scale is
enormous. And
we don't normally see things like this.
It's basically taking down a massive
Wall Street hedge fund.
I think we need to put this in a
little bit of context of what's been
happening over the last year, right?
Obviously, the US is in the middle of
corona. It's like us, there's millions of
people sitting at home, they can't work,
they're not able to get an income. And in
that period, the stock market has been
flying through the roof.
Amazon stock price has doubled, that's
Jeff Bezos's net worth.
Tesla's up about five times, Bitcoin's
doing whatever Bitcoin is doing.
Ordinary people are sitting at home, trying
to work, but work's not working for them,
right? They can't make any money
and they're just seeing the wealthiest
people, their money in the stock market
just
absolutely making tons. And this is on
[Gary] top of 12 years since 2008, when the
stock market has gone up I think five or
six times.
So I think what you're seeing is
ordinary people starting to realise that,
you know, we have a stock market that
goes up in good times and it goes up in
bad times.
Whatever happens, the rich seem to be
protected and ordinary workers are not.
So they want to get involved.
I think really this is the culmination
of many years of ordinary people getting
left behind,
of the stock market getting bailed
out when ordinary people aren't.
And yeah, obviously this is
the culmination of it. People getting
together on Reddit and starting to...
it's not really... it's not even just
GameStop, they're going into other things
now.
I think this is ordinary people, they
don't want to...
well, they want their share of the pie,
basically. They see it keep going, just
the stock markets, and they want to get
involved.
[Michael] Yes, you brought up, this is, you know,
ordinary people against Wall Street.
That's what we're going to discuss
next, you know, the extent to which this
is a popular uprising or just a
get-rich-quick plan by some
people on Reddit. But before we do that,
to sort of frame this discussion, I want
to go to a couple of clips
from CNBC. So that's the financial
news channel in the United
States. So the first clip I'm going to
show you is from William Legate. He is
founder
and CEO of a cryptocurrency platform, and
a follower of the Wall Street Bets
subreddit. He explained how he
characterises the GameStop phenomenon.
[Legate] These people are just
in general wanting to give Wall Street
the finger, quite frankly.
They view the system as being
rigged against them. I think that this
entire movement has
really validated that and made it very
clear to most Americans that is the
case.
You have... if I personally invested my
own money and lost half of my portfolio
overnight,
no one on Wall Street would, you know,
care at all. If a hedge fund loses
half their money overnight, all of a
sudden
you can't trade anymore. And, you know,
they stop
the free market in order to allow these
funds to rebalance their positions. I
think that's extremely wrong and
against, you know, everything that the
market's supposed to be standing for.
[CNBC Host] From your following of them, do the
people in this subreddit
who are calling to take down the hedge
funds realise that there could be some
serious unintended consequences that
could hurt everyday people?
[Legate] For the most part, I think, absolutely.
This subreddit is pretty
crude, I guess you could say. And a lot
of people, a big part of it, even before
this Wall Street Bets movement, was
posting people's
losses. And that's just part of the
culture of the subreddit.
A lot of these people are not in
this necessarily for the money.
Certainly some retail traders are, and
I
feel like some people will end up, you
know, getting left holding the bag.
But for the most part, these people
are just wanting to make a statement. And
they kind of view this as class warfare,
quite frankly. Kind of
Occupy Wall Street 2.0, but on their
own terms, and with real financial
consequences.
[Michael] Saying this is class warfare, but with
real financial
consequences. Now, someone from the ruling
class who was getting pretty upset about
it is a Wall Street trader, Leon
Cooperman. Now, he is a hedge fund manager,
he's worth $3.2
billion. Here again, he is
speaking. This, again, is on CNBC.
[Cooperman] The reason the market is doing what it's
doing is people are sitting at home
getting their checks from the government.
Okay? And this "fair share" is a
concept...
it's just a way of attacking wealthy
people. And,
you know, I think it's inappropriate. We
all got to work together and pull
together.
[Michael] So, he... "fair share" being a
concept that was about tax,
I think. But he basically has the
analysis that the problem here is that
too many people are getting government
checks,
and then the plebs are investing on
the stock market, and this is messing the
whole thing up.
Gary, I want to bring you in. I mean,
they've brought up class war there.
Is this a genuine sort of redistribution
of wealth and power from corporate
elites to the ordinary man?
Is that a legitimate analysis of
what's
been going on over the past week?
[Gary] I wish, I wish
there was, Michael. It's so... it's so
fascinating, isn't it? That sort of...
this is the space we've reached now,
where it's such an interesting
combination of
people out there trying to make money in
the markets, which is such a sort of
individualistic, "I want to
make money
for me" idea, but they're coming together
on this message board to try and do it
together. It's this... so it's this super
combination of
"I want to make money for me" and "we need
to do it together." I think this is...
in a sense, it was kind of inevitable
that we were gonna reach this space,
right? Because,
you know, people are told that you live
in a meritocracy, you have to do what you
can, get a job, save up your money, buy a
house.
But increasingly, that doesn't work. And
then at the same time, you see people...
you know, I come from a poor background.
I made my money in the City, basically
gambling. And I don't know many people
who come from ordinary backgrounds
who've been able to, for example, buy a
house
just by working an ordinary job. But
people see, oh, this guy's made money on
Bitcoin,
that guy's made money in the stock
markets. So I think it's kind of reached
this inevitable conclusion where
people have realised that even just to
achieve your basic goals,
it's not working. Work isn't working. So
they've tried to get together and
they've tried to rebalance it, you know,
on an internet messaging board. But,
to be honest, I don't think this is gonna
look fantastic for the people who made
money on this. But my concern really is
people are gonna maybe watch this, or
it's been all over the news the last
couple of days, they're gonna see it now,
they're gonna think, well, this is my
chance. They're going to jump in. And,
you know, at some point this stock is
going to fall. And I just want
to tell the people that are listening,
don't take any mad risks and run into
this now, because it's not easy
money to be made, basically. And
this is, you know... I wish the revolution
could happen
from people at home trading the stock
markets in their underpants, but I think
it's not going to go like that.
[Michael] I'm not sure anyone watches this show
for financial advice, so you probably
don't need to worry too much
about that. But
I do want to focus on that question
actually, in terms of what is going to
happen
next for the people who've invested in
this company, especially because
presumably at this point GameStop is
overvalued. So it's worth a hell of a lot
on the stock market at the moment, even
though the underlying business
isn't particularly valuable. And if
you've got a bubble, you normally expect
it to burst at some point. So
that share price is going to collapse,
and if you're still holding shares at
that point in time,
then you lose a lot. Is that
inevitable now? Are we just going to
inevitably see lots of Reddit users or
people who've piled in because of this,
you know, because of the publicity
around this, lose a bunch of
money? Or is there a different possible
route, you know, out of this current
moment than that?
[Gary] I mean, this is such an interesting
bubble, right? Because normally when you
have a bubble, there's some people out
there saying, "No, it's not a bubble,
it's different, this is real fundamental
value." Here is a bubble, here is a
massively overvalued stock, where
literally everyone who's driving the
bubble
thinks it's overvalued. It's just...
everybody knows it's a bad investment,
they're still doing it. And,
you know, I use this message board, Wall
Street Bets. Like, I've been going on it
for
a year. If you get some free time,
have a look, it's a fascinating place.
I was on it this morning. People are
going... it's like a religion. People are
screaming at each other, "Don't sell!"
They think they're starting a revolution,
basically. So,
it's driven by this sort of collective
madness. And I totally understand, I
totally understand this feeling that
these guys on Wall Street are making
millions, you know, Jeff Bezos is making
billions, Elon Musk is making billions.
We're sitting at home, we can't even work.
I totally, I totally understand that
sentiment.
But, to be honest, I cannot see this
playing out any other way than it
eventually
collapsing. And there will be people left
holding it that will lose
money when it happens. I would be very,
very, very surprised. And, to be honest,
I think even the people driving it would
surely be surprised. It's the most
phenomenal
bubble where everybody knows it's a
bubble. But,
[Gary] I think it's important to understand,
this is not coming out of nowhere, right?
Last year, in the COVID crisis, the
government spent £450 billion,
right? That's £10,000
for every adult in the country.
They didn't raise any taxes,
they didn't borrow money from external
investors. They printed all of that money
and they pumped it into the system.
So what you have here is a government
that thinks we can deal with the crisis
by printing money and giving it to the
rich, because the data shows all that
money ended up with the rich.
Look, if you try and fix a crisis that
has inequality at its core
by giving money to the rich, you can't be
surprised when suddenly you see massive
stock market bubbles.
And my big concern is that that spreads
into UK property and we see a massive
rise in UK property now.
And what that will mean for young people
in this country...
if we start seeing this bubble move into
UK property, which I think quite possibly
it will...
[Michael] I think we should definitely... let's park
the UK property question for a moment,
because I think we should definitely get
you back on,
you know, especially on that
question, which might have more practical
significance for a lot of people
watching this. But I want to stick to
this phenomenon
of GameStop and specifically now move on
to the role of Robinhood.
Because Robinhood is the
app where people can trade stocks and
shares without any commissions. So this
is the kind of app which has
allowed ordinary people to trade
on the stock market without having,
you know, a broker or an agent. And
yesterday,
when this, you know, the prices of
GameStop were really surging,
they suspended trading. And this was
incredibly controversial. People thought
this was sort of market manipulation,
the big guys coming in to stop the
little guy
having some influence. And opposition to
the suspension came from
all sides of the political spectrum.
So, to
prove that to you, the evidence: this is
[Michael] Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez.
She tweeted, "This is unacceptable. We now
need to know more about Robinhood app's
decision to block retail investors from
purchasing stock,
while hedge funds are freely able to
trade the stock as they see fit.
As a member of the Financial Services
Committee, I'd support a hearing
if necessary." You also got someone from
the right wing of the Republican Party,
Ted Cruz,
tweeting in agreement. So he quote-
tweeted that tweet I've just read to you,
saying,
"Fully agree." Now, Robinhood
themselves, the firm, the CEO has gone
on television saying this is just
because of volatile trading, meaning that
they had a bit of a cash flow problem,
not them intervening on behalf of any
hedge funds who were losing money.
Although, I can see in the comments,
someone has tweeted
with a £10 superchat. That's Kishor
Kukandraja. I hope I pronounce your
name correctly.
They say, "Gary, what do you think of
Citadel's role in Robinhood in all of
this?" And that's a reference to... some
people are suggesting
that there could be connections between
Robinhood and Citadel, who are a hedge
fund who are losing money
on GameStop shares because they'd short-
sold it. And they think that maybe there
was some collusion going on here. I don't
know. Gary, what
do you make of this decision by the
Robinhood app to suspend
trading? [Gary] I mean, it's such a story, isn't
it? Who would have thought, finally the
thing to unite the political divide in the
US would be
the right of people to do wild
speculative gambling on the stock market.
Finally,
finally something that everybody can
agree on. Listen,
I would have loved to have been a fly on
the wall in that Robinhood head office
when they decided to suspend
trading. And there's lots of people
with lots of ideas about what's
happening. People are saying that,
yeah, it's owned by Citadel, and Citadel's
got powerful political connections, and
they don't want Wall Street to get hurt.
Listen, I can't tell you whether that's
what happened. I'm sure that Robinhood
themselves would say, "We're trying to
protect investors," or, "We have legitimate
financial reasons why we can't do it."
Listen, I guarantee you, there'll be
people on Wall Street that are not happy
about
[Gary] suddenly a huge amount of financial
market power being held by
random guys trading on Reddit.
But I wouldn't be able to tell you with
any certainty
whether there was actually a shady
meeting behind closed doors between
Wall Street bankers and politicians and
the guys who own Robinhood.
I would love to know more, and hopefully
Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez will
get her request for more information,
because the people on Reddit are
furious about it. And I can totally
understand. I mean,
they've got a massive position and
suddenly they can't trade. If it was me,
I'd be furious too. But
I wish I could tell you the exact
reasons, that there were some shady
dealings behind closed doors. I'm afraid
I don't know the truth.
[Michael] I want to talk now a bit more about
whether this phenomenon, which is sort of
like
individual retail traders,
individual people
in their bedrooms,
trading on the stock market but
talking to each other about it, could
transform capitalism in some way. Now,
there are lots of people saying,
discussing, quite rightly, that this sort
of adds an element of unpredictability
into the stock market. Because it's not
just
GameStop who have gone up in value, it's
lots of
other brands which were seen as not
having much of a future by
Wall Street. And they're often brands
which, you know, people have some
emotional connection to. So GameStop was
a shop people
shopped at in their childhood.
A bit like, you know, you think of
Blockbusters
[Michael] here. I know, you have Game. It wasn't
particularly meaningful to me.
Also, I think Nokia's doing quite well,
BlackBerry's doing quite well, there's a
cinema chain
in the United States that's doing
quite well, because people are piling in
money.
And one analysis is that this is sort of
basically, you know, it's kind of like
financial shitposting, in a way.
Other people, though, are arguing that
this distributed manner of investing
could itself be
a more efficient form of capitalism than
that which is managed on
Wall Street. And, to introduce this point,
I want to show you
a video which is of the CEO of Social
Capital, explaining, again, to CNBC,
why he thinks that Wall Street Bets is
not just an FU to the Wall Street
establishment. It is also that,
but that it's also the site of better
investments than what hedge funds
are capable of. [Chamath] And I would encourage
anybody who
is dismissive of this thing to go into
Wall Street Bets and actually just read
the forums.
And I think that you're going to see
three kinds of posts.
The first kind of content are a lot of
people doing some
incredible fundamental diligence on
companies,
trying to think about long-term value.
And, in my opinion, many of them are doing
as good, and, frankly,
a better job than a lot of hedge fund
analysts that I work with.
That's number one. The second are a lot
of people who believe
that, you know, coming out of 2008, what
happened was Wall Street took an
enormous amount of risk,
and they left retail as the bag holder.
And a lot of these kids
[Chamath] were in grade school and high school
when that happened. They lost their homes,
their parents lost their jobs. And
they've always wondered, like, why
did those folks get bailed out for
taking enormous amounts of risk,
and nobody helped, and showed up to help
my family?
And then the third thing is a
realisation that, instead of having
idea dinners, or, you know, quiet whispered
conversations amongst hedge funds in the
Hamptons,
these kids have the courage to do it
transparently in a forum. And I'm not
saying all of it is perfect
by any means. But I think it takes
an enormous amount of faith in the
system to be that transparent,
to talk about things, and then for each
individual to make their own mind up
and to do things, whether it's to buy
into...
[Michael] So, what I found quite interesting there
was this phrase, "the faith in the system."
You know, because most people are talking
about this as a deeply, you know,
anti-establishment movement, potentially
anti-capitalist.
What that commentator there was
suggesting was that, potentially,
this could reinvigorate capitalism. If
you've got all of these people
trading stocks in their bedrooms, who can
make, you know, collectively, more
efficient and more transparent decisions
than
hedge fund managers having quiet dinners
with each other, then potentially this
could,
you know, this could be a boost to
overall economic growth. Potentially, I
mean, you're almost looking at kind of,
you know,
democratic capitalism, but of the sort of
individualistic,
Thatcher kind, in a way. I mean, what do
you make of that, Gary? This idea
that actually these could be more
efficient investors
than the Wall Street brokers? So it's not
just a disruptive force, it could also be
a highly
efficient force? [Gary] I mean, I've spoken a lot
this year
about what we've seen in the last 10
years, because governments and central
banks have been trying to deal with
crises, like I say, by printing huge
amounts of money.
We've come to this position where, as I
say,
if the economy does well, stock markets
go up. If the economy does badly,
the central bank prints loads of money
and stock markets still go up. And we've
really had this divergence here. Whatever
happens, stock markets do well
and ordinary people do badly. And, you
know, I've put out videos on my Instagram
and on my Facebook, Gary's Economics,
explaining
how people can deal with this, because
when house prices and stock prices go
through the roof, but wages don't,
it really, really hurts, especially young
people, because they can't save up money,
they can't get a house. And
for this reason, I totally understand why
people have surged towards online
trading platforms
as an easier way to access stock markets,
because they want to get a share of the
returns that have largely been going to
the richest people, because most stocks
are owned by the richest people.
For that reason, especially in this last
year, we've seen a massive, massive uptick
in the number of people using online
trading accounts, like IG Index in this
country, Trading 212, this kind of thing.
And I think it's really important to
talk about this, because on the one hand,
it's important that ordinary people are
able to participate
in these markets and take some of the
returns that super-rich people are
getting.
But the truth is, if you're super-rich
and you've got £1 million, £2 million, £10
million,
you can make loads of money on the stock
markets. If you're an ordinary person
saving with £10,000, £20,000,
it's going to be very difficult for you
[Gary] to do that. And often these people, they
go onto these trading platforms, they
don't really have a full idea of what
they're doing.
Sometimes these trading platforms can
allow you to make very risky bets, and
people don't realise just how much risk
they're taking. And people can lose
all of the money they put in, potentially.
And I think 75% of people who use
this IG Index trading website lose money.
So I don't want to give the
impression this is some mad
democratising force, because, look, I'm a
market professional and I've made quite
a bit of money. And I make money when I'm
trading the stock markets. But if some guy
who doesn't know what he's doing
puts his life savings in there, he's
probably going to be in that 75%.
So I think the end result is,
I don't think we're gonna transform
capitalism and radically redistribute
wealth just by everybody becoming a
stock market trader, because, in the end,
the best stock market traders are going
to end up working for the wealthiest
people. And,
you know, if you're just an
electrician or a hairdresser sitting at
home
on the internet, you're probably not
going to quadruple your money. In fact,
you are likely to be in that 75%.
So, you know, it's very typical that the
way the world is
right now, you know, all this Wolf of Wall
Street, the idolisation of money and
trading. People think, well, we can reform
capitalism by all becoming traders.
But I think, in reality, the most likely
situation is the professionals will make
money, the people with the most
experience make money, and the ordinary
people
will be left with the losses.
[Michael] Well, that's a... well, it's a downbeat note to
end our coverage of this story.
Jane Hayward, with a fiver, says, "Great
story, great coverage, great
guest." I couldn't agree more. You've
been a great guest, Gary Stevenson.
Thank you so much for joining us this
evening. We'll definitely get you back
soon.
[Gary] If there's a housing crisis next, if the
housing bubble does pop, which actually
maybe wouldn't be a crisis, but...
[Michael] We'll save that conversation. Yes, yes, we
will. Until next time.
[Gary] Thanks so much, Michael.
Have a good day. [Michael] Nice one.