Okay, so I want to do one on avocado on toast, actually.
No, that sounds like a joke, but I think
actually this is an important issue that people
need to understand. So one thing that I've
realised recently, and I'm sure people watching
would have seen this, is a lot of newspapers
running articles saying, "I gave up Starbucks
and I gave up avocado on toast for three years
and then I bought this five hundred thousand pound
flat." And the article was always like, "How I managed
to buy this £500,000 flat in London," or, "How I
managed to be mortgage-free by the age of 35."
This kind of thing, like all stories about how
young people managed to be and get this amazing
property, or manage to have their mortgage, alright.
And it's always, you know, "I really scrimped and
saved, I gave up avocado on toast, I stopped going
to Starbucks, I bought my own packed lunch to work."
And then if you read these articles, and
I promise you, go and read through them,
you will always see about two thirds of the way
down they just slipped in, "And then, you know, I used
that money plus 200 grand which I borrowed from
my mum, and then I bought this property." And it's
always like, wait, wait a minute, wait a minute. So
you stopped eating avocado toast, and you... but
also you got 200 grand from your mum? And I think
this is important for a couple of reasons. Firstly,
because one thing that I see amongst my friendship
group, right, like I went to a grammar school and then I
went to like elite universities, so I know some
people from pretty well-off families, but I also
know some people from families that are
poor or not well off, right. And what I see is
the kids from well off families buy properties,
and they get a gift from their parents, you know,
maybe it might be 50 grand, it might be 150
grand, it might be 250 grand, alright.
Because that's what you need to be able to buy
a property in London nowadays, or in a lot of
cities, you know what I mean. A lot of Australian
cities are even worse, the amount of money you
need to get a deposit. And then my kids...
my mates from poorer families,
they see other people buying property and there's
no way they can do it, because they can't get their
deposit, and they don't understand, "How are these guys
able to buy property and I'm not?" And the reason is
because increasingly the only way to get property
nowadays is to get a massive gift from your parents,
and people from poor families don't see that.
So the first thing I want to do is open this up,
because these newspapers give a misleading idea
that if you just worked a little harder, if you just
saved a little more, you can get a property. But
the reality, if you look in these articles, is it's
almost impossible in many places without a massive
gift from your parents. So if there are people out
there who are watching, feeling bad, like, "I can't
afford property," it's not what these articles are
saying. The truth is, realistically, if you're from
the wrong family nowadays, it's almost impossible
to get property. That's the first thing. But the
second thing is, I think it highlights a little
bit something important about how economics and
the media works, right. Like I did an interview the other day,
and the person I was up against works for the IEA,
Institute of Economic Affairs. Sounds really fancy,
right. That's a think tank funded by billionaires.
They pay people to go on the radio and say, "Don't
tax billionaires." That's all it is, basically. And
so much of the media is owned by billionaires.
The Times, owned by billionaires. The Sun, owned by
billionaires. Talk Radio, owned by billionaires.
The Daily Mail, owned by billionaires, right. So all
of these newspapers and all these radio stations,
Sky News, owned by billionaires, they're
all owned by billionaires. So obviously
they are going to send people out
there to say, "Don't tax billionaires."
And bear that in mind whenever you
see what these newspapers say. But also,
I think they wanna give the impression that
things are okay as they are, because at the moment
they don't want things to change, cause things as they are are
working super well for the billionaires. And at
the moment we have this situation in this country,
and also in a lot of countries, where for older
generations who own their own property, things
look okay because the property prices have gone up.
And I'll talk a lot about this in my video on
housing. But for younger generations, they're in
a situation where it's impossible for them to
purchase property, and it's impossible for them to get
financial security, and to save up the assets
you need to have a pension or to raise a family.
But older people often don't see this, and as
a result they vote for parties which are not
doing anything about supporting those people.
But if they knew, I think if a lot of older
people realised how difficult the situation was for
younger generations, they would vote against it. But
the newspapers tell them, "Oh, it's okay, as long as
they pull their socks up, stop buying avocado toast,
stop going to Starbucks, they'll be okay and get
property." But the reality of it is, increasingly,
more and more families in this country, and
then a lot of countries around the world,
are unable to afford property. And these newspapers
are giving a misleading idea, like it's just a
problem of young people being silly. But it's not,
because house price... the average house price in
London is like 600 grand now, and the average
wage is like 30 grand, you know. You're gonna
have to stop buying coffee for, what, like 300 years
or something? It's not going to happen, right. So,
yeah, you know, it's about avocado toast, but it's
not about avocado toast. It's about understanding
that very rich people spend a lot of money
to give you these ideas about economics, and
understanding that a lot of the economic
messages we receive are biased, and often
they're designed to stop you from pushing back,
because the system as it is is working really,
really well for the super rich. And yeah, you
know, watching my other videos where we talk about
inequality, the ones we talk about how taxes are
being raised on working people and not on the rich,
like "Why Is Rishi Sunak Raising Your Taxes?", watch
"What Is Wealth?", and watch the housing video. But
understand that we've got a serious problem here
that will not get better unless we do something,
and a lot of the people in power are not
incentivised to do it. So if we want change,
we're gonna have to make it happen
ourselves. So yeah, educate yourselves,
watch my videos, share the message.
And yeah, let's make things change.