What's going on? Gonna get a flat white.
How much is that? £2.90.
Do you take Gascoin?
Gascoin, the new crypto for
Gary's Economics, the YouTube channel.
It's Gascoin. It's worth £147.20,
more than a flat white.
Let me have a go.
I hate to break it to you, boss.
Worth nothing.
Gone down to zero, yeah.
Okay. You keep the coffee.
We're gonna do one on crypto.
Crypto, Bitcoin, NFTs, everybody's talking
about them. If you take away one single
message from this video, I want it to be
this: all of these investments are
extremely risky, and it's completely
possible that you can lose 100% of any
money you invest in them. But right now,
these things are being advertised on
buses, they're being advertised on
footballers' jerseys, there's millions of
people all over Instagram and YouTube
telling you they've made thousands of
pounds on it. Probably even your friends
are saying this. Every single video I
post on this channel,
I get spam comments saying you can
make loads of money on Bitcoin. All of
these things come together to give the
impression that these are safe, reliable
investments. Nothing could be further
from the truth. Okay, I'm in touch with
gambling organisations, and they're
seeing a massive increase of people with
addictions to crypto trading, and massive
losses from it. I've had friends
personally lose enormous amounts of
money. You need to understand, these are
super dangerous investments, and you can
lose any money you put in.
Next, we're going to talk about what
cryptocurrency actually is.
Cryptos like Bitcoin are an unbacked
monetary system.
What that means is they're not backed by
anything real.
Look, if you buy Apple stock, you own a
part of those Apple stores and some of
those Apple products. If you buy Tesco
stock, you literally own a part of those
supermarkets. If you buy a house, you get a
house you can live in. If you buy gold,
you get a little bar of gold. If you buy
Bitcoin, all you have is a Bitcoin. You
can't exchange that legally for anything.
It gives you no legal ownership rights.
Nothing could make this more clear than
the situation of NFTs, non-fungible
tokens. In this case, celebrities like
John Terry and Paris Hilton sell little
pictures of monkeys on the internet that
look a little bit like them, sometimes
for millions of dollars.
People who buy them often think it gives
them the legal copyright rights to these
pictures.
But then they find actually they don't
legally own anything. All they've bought
is a little token on the internet saying
they own it, with no associated legal
rights.
It's the same with Bitcoin. It's the same
with crypto. You don't own any real
assets. You don't have any legal rights.
It is a totally unbacked monetary system.
I know exactly what you're thinking.
You're thinking regular money is exactly
the same.
Central banks are printing hundreds of
billions of pounds and dollars, and
they're devaluing the pound in your
pocket, they're devaluing your savings,
they're devaluing your wages, and you're
looking for a safer place to invest. That
is 100%. Sure enough, I've said the same thing
on my channel. But listen, just because
money is a bad investment, that doesn't
mean you should start buying made-up
internet money.
Look, if some guy came to your city and
said, "Look, your money is a bad investment,
you should buy
this brand-new internet money I've
created," would you do it? Look, the vast
majority of the owners and creators of
these cryptocurrencies are very, very
wealthy people, and they're convincing
you to buy their internet points with
your real money, and they're using that
real money to buy your mum's houses. That
is what's happening here.
And listen, I know there are people who
are not going to want to hear this
message. There are people who might even
be getting angry. There are people who
are invested in Bitcoin who desperately,
desperately want it to go up. Listen, I
know that.
And I know we've created a country here
where ordinary, hard-working young men
and women can work every hour of the
week and save up every penny and still
not even be able to buy a house.
Listen, I know we've created a society
where it's almost impossible for people
from poor backgrounds to become rich. And
I know if you create that society, then
ordinary people are going to be
desperately looking for another
alternative, a way out.
And I know that these very wealthy
people are using those fears and
insecurities to try and get you to buy
into these points on the internet,
and they're taking your real money in
return for that.
Listen, this is not a way out. This is a
trap.
But you know what upsets me more?
We live in a country where ordinary
families are getting poorer, generation
after generation.
The homeownership rate is collapsing.
People are being pushed further and
further into debt.
We've got a billionaire chancellor who's
raising taxes on ordinary people whilst
cutting taxes on millionaires and
billionaires. And while all this is
happening, some of our smartest, brightest
young people have been convinced that
the only thing they can do against this
is trade pictures of monkeys on the
internet.
Listen, there's a real fight going on
here, okay? The rich and the super rich
are getting richer and richer, and taking
the real resources that the families of
these countries need.
Ordinary people are getting poorer.
They've got the money, the power, and the
newspapers. The only thing we've got is
that there's more of us, and we're
smarter.
The only way we can protect the
financial position of ordinary families
in this country is by coming together.
Look, if you're a crypto trader out there,
we need you. Come together and help us
fight back.
Look, these guys are telling you a dream
here.
It's a dream that if you trade their
coins and their monkeys on the internet,
then you can be a millionaire.
And while you're doing that,
they're gonna take our wealth and our
houses.
It's the trap.
Don't fall for it.
So what do you do instead?
Number one, you educate yourself.
I've got a video on this channel about
the basics of investing. I've also got a
video explaining what is wealth.
Understand what real wealth is and what
you can do to protect yourself and your
family.
Number two is push back, man. Don't accept
a system that is so unequal.
Push for better wealth distribution, and
for a tax system that taxes billionaires
on a higher rate than you pay your tax.
And number three is share this message.
We need to get people together if we're
gonna push back and make things better.
Anyway, I've been looking for an investment
that's safer than Bitcoin, and
I think I might have finally found one.
Keep watching.